<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The secret history of the court of the emperor Justinian written by Procopius of Cesarea ; faithfully rendred into English.</title>
            <title>Secret history. English</title>
            <author>Procopius.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 264 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55987</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3641</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21705</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12361586</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12361586</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60251</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55987)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60251)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 645:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The secret history of the court of the emperor Justinian written by Procopius of Cesarea ; faithfully rendred into English.</title>
                  <title>Secret history. English</title>
                  <author>Procopius.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 162 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Barkesdale ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Anecdota.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Justinian --  I, --  Emperor of the East, 483?-565.</term>
               <term>Rome --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60251:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60251:1"/>
            <p>THE Secret Hiſtory OF THE COURT Of the Emperor JUSTINIAN.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN By <hi>PROCOPI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S of Ceſarea;</hi> Faithfully rendred into <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Barkeſdale</hi> Bookbinder, over againſt the Five Bells in <hi>New-ſtreet,</hi> between <hi>Fetterlane</hi> and <hi>Shooelane.</hi> l674.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:60251:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60251:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> SECRET HISTORY OF <hi>PROCOPI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat hapned in the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, in its Wars with the Barbarous. Nations, I ſuppoſe I have exactly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and the order which I have obſerved, is ſo juſt, every Action and Accident is to be found with its proper, and due Circumſtances, both of time and of place. In what I am now about, I do not hold my ſelf bound to ſo ſtrict a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, becauſe the ſubject is of things which paſſed in ſeveral places of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire at the ſame time. When I writ my firſt Hiſtories, I thought it not expedient to be too particular, by reaſon the main Agents were then living; and I could not long have concealed, or ſecured
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60251:3"/>my ſelf againſt ſome exemplary puniſhment, if my Book ſhould have been publiſhed; and I judged it very dangerous, to commit ſuch a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret to any Friend whatſoever: So that in my firſt Hiſtory of all, I was obliged to omit the Motives and Cauſes of ſuch Actions and Events as I related there. Moſt people do eaſily, and without conſideration, give themſelves to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Actions of their Anceſtors, and do fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their ill examples, without any care or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe: For my own part, nothing excited me ſo ſtrongly to this work, as that ſuch perſons who are deſirous to govern in an Arbitrary way, might diſcover, by the misfortune of thoſe whom I mention, the deſtiny that attends them, and the juſt recompence they are to expect of their crimes. Beſides, it is not impoſſible, but the fear of leaving the Hiſtory of an infamous life behind them to poſterity, may reſtrain them in ſome meaſure, and occaſion a greater averſion to ſuch deteſtable actions. And indeed, who would have abhorred the debauches of <hi>Semira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis,</hi> the effeminacy of <hi>Sardanapalus,</hi> and the cruelties of <hi>Nero,</hi> had not great Men under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken the Hiſtory of their times, and tranſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it to poſterity. For the ſame reaſon I ſhall begin with the exorbitancies of <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> after which, I ſhall repreſent the Impieties of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dora</hi> and <hi>Juſtinian. Antonina</hi> began to lead her life with more diſſoluteneſs and liberty, and to tranſgreſs publickly without any ſhame or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret. There was, at that time, in the Family of <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> a young Thracian called <hi>Theodoſius,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:60251:3"/>whoſe Relations being Eunomians; <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> before his departure in <hi>Africk,</hi> cauſed him to be Baptiſed, and having held him at the Font himſelf, he and his wife, adopted him with all the Ceremony which the Chriſtians uſed in their adoptions. From that time <hi>Antonina</hi> took all imaginable care of <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> (which was but juſt, having made him her ſon) ſhe cheriſhed him exceedingly, and kept him conſtantly with her; but before their paſſage into <hi>Africk,</hi> ſhe fell in love with him ſo deſperately, and her paſſion was ſo uncontroulable, That ſhe loſt not only all Shame, but the ſence of all Laws, both Humane and Divine. At firſt, indeed, ſhe was baſhful in her debaucheries, and all her aſſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were with great caution and ſecreſie, but by degrees ſhe began to commit them in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and before her women ſervants, not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending any oppoſition againſt her wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, after the vehemence of her love, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported her to careſs him before all people. <hi>Belli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarius</hi> himſelf found her faulty with his own eyes; not far from <hi>Carthage,</hi> but he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded again, and wheedled by his wife, and I think not unwillingly. The buſineſs was thus. He found them together in a private Vault, and the ſight of them put him into a very great paſſion; but <hi>Antonina</hi> was ſo far from being out of countenance at the ſurpriſe, that ſhe advanced to meet him, and told him, That <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and ſhe, were come thither to hide ſome of the richeſt things which they had taken from the Enemy, that the Emperor might never hear
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60251:4"/>what was become of them. With which ſudden pretence, ſhe excuſed her ſelf to <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> who, good Man, was not hard to be perſwaded (though he obſerved the point of <hi>Theodiſius</hi> his Codpeece was untied;) but ſuſſering himſelf to be deluded by the careſſes of his wife, he choſe rather to ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pect the teſtimony of his own ſenſes, then be obliged to have any differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with her.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, the exorbitancies of <hi>Antonina</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing daily, and the ſcandal of them grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hourly more publick all the ſervants and friends of <hi>Belliſarius</hi> beheld him with much trouble, but none of them had the courage to give him any advertiſement. There was one Woman (called the <hi>Macedonian</hi>) only, who waited upon her in her Chamber, and had the holdneſs to give him notice. This <hi>Macedonian,</hi> after <hi>Belliſarius</hi> had conquered <hi>Sicily,</hi> and was Reſident in <hi>Syracuſe,</hi> came to him, and having drawn from him ſeveral great and indiſpenſible oaths, That he would never diſcover to <hi>Antonina,</hi> what ſhe ſhould tell him; the told him the whole intrigue, and brought two of the Maids of her Chamber to atteſt it. <hi>Belliſarius</hi> being convinced of the diſloyalty of his wife, commanded ſome of his Guards to ſtab <hi>Theodoſius;</hi> but the young Gentleman having notice of their orders, got away, and eſcaped to <hi>Epheſus:</hi> For the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which <hi>Belliſarius</hi> imployed, underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his temper, and that he was naturally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant, thought it more wiſdom to oblige his Lady with the diſcovery, then to truſt their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60251:4"/>fortunes upon the uncertainty of his favor. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> who was one of the Lieutenant Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals to <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> ſeeing him much diſcompoſed at the buſineſs, and pitying his misfortune, told him inconſiderately, That if the caſe had been his, he would have made an example ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his wife, then <hi>Theodoſius:</hi> Which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion being reported to <hi>Antonina,</hi> ſhe locked up her reſentment for ſome time in her Breſt, that when ſhe had opportunity ſhe might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge her ſelf more effectually. For ſhe was the perſon of the whole World, who knew how to diſſemble her indignation, and cover that venome which lay boiling in her Soul; and the truth is, ſhe carried her ſelf ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly, that in a ſhort time, either by the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of her charms, or the inſinuation of her tongue, ſhe perſwaded her Husband that the report of her diſloyalty to him was unjuſt, and that nothing was more falſe, then that accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Whereupon <hi>Belliſarius</hi> ſent for <hi>Theodoſius</hi> back again to <hi>Antonina,</hi> and promiſed to deliver up the <hi>Macedonian,</hi> and the two Chamber-Maids, which he performed very punctually. This cruel Woman, had no ſooner got them in her power, but having firſt cut off their Noſes, ſhe cauſed their Bodies be hacked into a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pieces, and then cram'd into a Sack, and thrown into the Sea. Her main agent in this horrid execution, was one of her ſervants called <hi>Eugenius,</hi> who had been a great Miniſter like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the miſeries which Pope <hi>Salverius</hi> had ſuffered. At length, <hi>Belliſarius</hi> at the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60251:5"/>of his wife, put to death <hi>Conſtantine</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe and what we have ſaid in another place, about the Dagger and <hi>Preſidius,</hi> hapned about the ſame time. For when <hi>Conſtantine</hi> was ready to have been acquitted for what he had done againſt <hi>Preſidius</hi> and <hi>Belliſarius, Antonina</hi> could take no reſt till ſhe were revenged for what he had ſaid againſt her. But this proceeding of <hi>Belliſarius</hi> drew upon him the hatred of the Emperor, and of all the great Lords of the Empire.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, <hi>Theodoſius</hi> in anſwer to the invitation of <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> ſent him word, That he would not come back into <hi>Italy</hi> (where <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonina</hi> and he were reſident then) till he had baniſhed <hi>Photius,</hi> who was <hi>Antoninaes</hi> own ſon. This <hi>Photius</hi> was naturally haughty, could not brook to ſee others in greater favor then himſelf, and by conſequence thought he had great reaſon to be diſcontented. He could not with patience behold himſelf neglected, and rendred incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, being a Son of their own family, whilſt <hi>Theodoſius</hi> (but adopted) was in great authority, and his riches proportionable; for the report was, he had got little leſs then Ten thouſand Livres of Gold, whilſt he was Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer in <hi>Carthage</hi> and <hi>Ravenna:</hi> Which was no hard matter, ſeeing the whole Treaſure, both in the one place and the other, was under his ſingle, and abſolute adminiſtration. <hi>Antonina</hi> underſtanding what <hi>Theodoſius</hi> required, fell immediately upon conſpiracy againſt her ſon, and her plots were ſo well laid, and ſo artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60251:5"/>managed, That <hi>Photius</hi> finding there was no ſafety where he was, was forced to retire to <hi>Constantinople,</hi> as not being able to protect him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf againſt her perpetual ambuſhments: When <hi>Photius</hi> was gone, <hi>Theodoſius</hi> was recalled into <hi>Italy,</hi> where <hi>Antonina</hi> continued for ſome time in as much luxury and happineſs, as the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces of her Gallant, and the ſtupidity of her Husband could contribute: But at length ſhe returned with both of them to <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> There it was, that <hi>Theodoſius</hi> felt his firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punctions of Conſcience, and began to be in no little perplexity to find how to demean him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; for he could not hope to conceal his courſe of life any longer, ſeeing <hi>Antonina</hi> was ſo far from making a ſecret of her paſſion, that ſhe abandoned her ſelf wholly to the tranſport of her luſt, without the leaſt care or regret for the imputation of an adultreſs. Upon this ſcore he went off again to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and having ſhaved according to cuſtom, he entred himſelf into a Monaſtery. This accident put <hi>Antonina</hi> out of all patience, inſomuch, that not only her habit, but her looks and deportment, repreſented no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſadneſs: She wept, and lamented up and down the houſe (though her Husband was then preſent, and in health) declaring publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That ſhe was undone in the loſs of <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> whoſe fidelity, whoſe friendſhip, whoſe diligence, and magnanimity were incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and ſhe brought over <hi>Belliſarius</hi> to be of her opinion, inſomuch, as he ran up and down with the ſame complaints, and left no means
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60251:6"/>unattempted, that might bring <hi>Theodoſius</hi> back again to his wife. Having tried ſeveral ways without effect, he came at length to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror and Empreſs, and obtained of them; by extraordinary importunity to have him recalled, as a perſon abſolutely neceſſary; as well for his future, as his preſent affairs: But <hi>Theodoſius</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed himſelf, pretending a reſolution to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue where he was; the inſtitutions of that Convent agreeing ſo exactly with his humor: Nevertheleſs this was but a copy of his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and a deſign, that he might come to her afterwards, with more privacy when <hi>Belliſarius</hi> was gone.</p>
            <p>The Emperor in the mean time, ſent <hi>Belli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarius</hi> and <hi>Photius</hi> againſt <hi>Coſroes,</hi> King of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> and <hi>Antonina</hi> continued at <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> contrary to her cuſtom; for till then, ſhe had always accompanied her Husband in all his expeditions, how tedious, and how dangerous ſoever, fearing perhaps, leaſt when he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, he ſhould return to himſelf, and take up ſome reſolution that might prove to her ruine, when freed from her inveiglements and charms: However, that ſhe might not be wanting in any thing that might contribute to the recovering of <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> ſhe undertook to rid her ſelf of <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius;</hi> to which purpoſe, ſhe ſuborned ſeveral perſons about <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> and perſwaded them not to let a day paſs without affronting <hi>Photius,</hi> and if poſſible, provoking him to mutiny: On the other ſide, Letters paſſed from her continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, by which, ſhe incenſed all people againſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60251:6"/>her Son; which, by degrees, put him upon a neceſſity of diſcovering the impieties of his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to <hi>Belliſarius;</hi> he ſent a perſon inſtructed from <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and obliged him to tell <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſarius,</hi> how the Court rung there with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauches of his Wife and <hi>Theodoſius. Belliſarius</hi> being ſinartly touched, ſuffered himſelf to be tranſported to what ever Indignation and Fury could ſuggeſt: He threw himſelf at <hi>Photius</hi> Feet, and entreated him to revenge himſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo highly offended by perſons, who by all Natural Obligations ought to have uſed him otherwiſe. <hi>Dear childe</hi> (ſaid he to him) <hi>you are not ſenſible who was your Father, for you ſucked when he died; his eſtate was no great advantage to you, for it was ſmall, and inconſiderable: You have been brought up ever ſince with me, though I was but your Father in Law; and you are now at an age, in which you have power to aſſiſt me in vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the injury has been done me. I have preferred you to the dignity of a Conſul, I have heaped wealth on you; ſo that I have ſerved you for a Father, a Mother, and for all that is of near Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for which reaſon, yon may call me by thoſe titles very juſtly: For Men are not uſed to limit their Friendſhip according to the degrees of conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinity, but rather according to merit and obligations. You have now a fair occaſion preſented, if you have any reſpect for a Perſon, whoſe honor, eſtate, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, is in evident danger; and if you diſdain not to concern your ſelf for your Mother, who by her ill conduct, runs a great hazard of making her ſelf the Scandal and Reproach of all intelligent Men.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60251:7"/>You may conſider, the frailties of a Wife have not ſo great reflexion upon the Husband, as the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, upon whom the ignominy remains as an ill diſeaſe, which they had contracted from their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. For my own part, I would have you believe I love</hi> Antonina <hi>excecdingly, and would never be induced to do her any miſcheif, if I could but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge my ſelf of him, who is the plague of my Family; But I ſhall never forgive my Wife, whilſt</hi> Theodoſius <hi>is living. Photius</hi> heard him with great patience, and promiſed his utmoſt aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, but his greateſt apprehenſion was, what might befal him, if he ſhould repoſe any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> who was the lighteſt and moſt unconſtant of his Sex, eſpecially in a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſo contrary to <hi>Antonina.</hi> Several examples of his levity, gave him reaſon to fear, but none was ſo terrible as the misfortune of the <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian.</hi> Hereupon he preſſed, and prevailed with <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> that they might mutually oblige themſelves by the ties that are moſt ſacred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtians, never to betray or deſert one another, though their lives or fortunes were in moſt imminent danger: But for all theſe precau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Photius</hi> believed he could not attempt any thing ſecurely; and therefore he concluded to expect, till <hi>Antonina</hi> was departed from <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius</hi> was returning to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus;</hi> at which time, he thought he might with more eaſe, ſeiſe upon <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and all his vaſt treaſure. In the mean time, <hi>Belliſarius</hi> with his whole Army invaded <hi>Perſia,</hi> whileſt ſeveral things hapned at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> which I have
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60251:7"/>related elſwhere, as the loſs of <hi>John de Cappado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, &amp;c.</hi> I only omitted on purpoſe, to ſay, That <hi>Antonina</hi> betrayed both the ſaid <hi>John</hi> and her Daughter, notwithſtanding millions of oaths and imprecations to the contrary. After this, ſhe ſent <hi>Theodoſius</hi> back again to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> relying extreamly upon the kindneſs of the Empreſs, who without any apprehenſion, removed into the Eaſt. It was not long before <hi>Belliſarius</hi> had taken the Fort of <hi>Siſauranum,</hi> and news was brought him, That his wife was at hand; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he cauſed his Army to retreat, and ſeemed to prefer his own private intereſt, before the benefit of the Empire. True it is, There was another reaſon which moved him to diſcamp with his Army, and I have mentioned it in my other Books, but the arrival of <hi>Antonina</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed much: And this was one thing which I durſt not communicate in the Hiſtory which I publiſhed, as not thinking my ſelf ſafe, if I ſhould chance to be diſcovered.</p>
            <p>From that time <hi>Belliſarius</hi> loſt much of his reputation, both with the Emperor and People, for having preferred his own private, to the affairs of the publick: That which did princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally induce him, was, That the extravagancies of his wiſe lying heavy at his heart, he could not without ſome trouble, reſolve to quit the Frontiers of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, as knowing, That the nearer he was, with the more eaſe he ſhould be able to revenge himſelf upon <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> as ſoon as his wife was arrived. In order thereunto, he commanded <hi>Arethas,</hi> with part of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60251:8"/>his Troops, to croſs the <hi>Tigre;</hi> but <hi>Arethas</hi> not executing his Orders, he returned into his own Countrey, without the honor of having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed his duty. <hi>Belliſarius</hi> reſolution was to keep himſelf within a league of the Frontiers, though the Fort of <hi>Siſuranum,</hi> which I menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned before, was not above a days journey from the Frontiers, by the way of <hi>Niſibe;</hi> and by any other way, it was not half ſo far diſtant. In ſhort, had he paſſed the <hi>Tigre</hi> at firſt, with his whole Army, I make no queſtion, but he had been Maſter of all <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> and without any difficulty extended his Conqueſts as far as the City of <hi>Cteſiphont;</hi> and before his return, might have delivered the Inhabitants of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and all the <hi>Romans</hi> which were priſoners; beſides, his unexpected departure, favored the Retreat of <hi>Cofroes,</hi> who was at the ſame time in <hi>Colchis.</hi> The caſe was thus, <hi>Coſroes,</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and Son of <hi>Cabades,</hi> having ſubdued <hi>Petra,</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed all the exploits which I have mentioned in my other Hiſtories; his Army was much weakned and impoveriſhed, not only by its En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements and Sieges, but by the inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the ways, (being over Mountains and almoſt unpaſſable Rocks) and by a Contagion (which carried off a great part of his Army) beſides the want of ſuch things as were neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary. In this juncture of them, news arrived out of <hi>Perſia,</hi> That <hi>Belliſarius</hi> having vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Nabades,</hi> had taken <hi>Siſuranum,</hi> and in it <hi>Beleſinaches,</hi> and Eight hundred <hi>Perſian</hi> Horſe, and was marching with his Army in good order
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60251:8"/>directly towards <hi>Niſibe,</hi> with deſign to beſiege it: That another way he had ſent a ſtrong party under the command of <hi>Arethas,</hi> the cheif of the <hi>Sarrarius,</hi> who had paſſed the River <hi>Tigre;</hi> ſo that the whole Countrey of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> which before had never been ſubject to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roads of the Enemy, was at preſent infeſted, and become a prey to any that would invade it. Moreover, a Body of <hi>Huns</hi> which <hi>Coſroes</hi> had ſent into <hi>Armenia</hi> (a Province belonging to the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire) had unfortunately encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred with the Troops of <hi>Valerian,</hi> and been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt utterly cut off. This news being brought to the <hi>Perſian</hi> Camp, which was already per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed with the incommodities which they had ſuffered a long time in the Countrey of the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riens,</hi> cauſed them to apprehend, That if the Enemy ſhould cut off the Paſſages, after all the Diſtreſſes and Calamities they had endured, they ſhould again be reduced to a neceſſity of ſtarving among the Rocks and Deſarts, and their ruine be attended by the diſtruction of their Wives and their Children, and the inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Conqueſt of their whole Countrey, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially at a time when their Army was ſo afflicted with diſeaſes. Hereupon they began to mutiny againſt <hi>Coſroes,</hi> and to upbraid him for having broken his Oath, and violated the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which is Sacred even among the <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians;</hi> they could not forgive him, that after a ſolemn Peace with the <hi>Romans,</hi> he had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded their Territories, undertaken an unjuſt War againſt them, and attacked an Empire,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60251:9"/>not only the moſt antient in the World, but ſo powerful, That they could not in reaſon hope to overcome it, though their Army was much more conſiderable then it was. Theſe diſcourſes had ſo prepared the minds of the <hi>Perſians</hi> for Sedition, that it was ready to break out, had not <hi>Coſroes</hi> applied a remedy in time, by reading the Letters which <hi>Zaberganes</hi> had received from the Empreſs, almoſt in theſe very terms.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Zaberganes,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOu might eaſily perceive, when you were Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador with us, how ready we were to oblige you, and how little we diſputed any thing that was to be done in your favor. You have now an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, effectually to anſwer our good opinion of you, and that is, by prevailing with King <hi>Coſroes</hi> your Maſter, to continue that good intelligence with us, that the Peace did procure. I do engage, that the Emperor, my Husband, ſhall recompence any good office you ſhall do him, to the full; and let me tell you, he does nothing now without my counſel and approbation.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>When <hi>Coſroes</hi> had read the Letter, he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the cheif Officers of his Army, That he could not but wonder the <hi>Perſians</hi> ſhould call that Empire invincible, which was governed by a Woman; and by this means he put a ſtop to their mutiny: Nevertheleſs, being ſtill ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive, leaſt <hi>Belliſarius</hi> ſhould poſſeſs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of the Paſſes, he diſcamped immediately, and finding no oppoſition, he returned into his own Countrey without any impediment.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:60251:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Belliſarius</hi> being retreated into the Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of the Empire, found that <hi>Antonina</hi> was arrived from <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and without the leaſt token of kindneſs, he cauſed her to be taken into cuſtody, and a Guard clap'd upon her: Many times it was in his thoughts to have put her to death, but he could never determine. I am of opinion his fondneſs was the cauſe, though others affirm, ſhe uſed charms and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments to render him irreſolute. In the interim, <hi>Photius</hi> arrived in great fury at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> having brought along with him <hi>Caligonus</hi> the Eunuch, who was <hi>Antinonaes</hi> great Confident, and privy to all her debaucheries. This <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligonus</hi> being brought in Chains, and well laſht by the way, confeſſed the truth in what ever was asked him: <hi>Theodoſius</hi> having notice of what had paſſed, retired into the Church of S. <hi>John,</hi> which is of greater veneration then any other in <hi>Epheſus;</hi> but that would not ſerve his turn, for the Biſhop (called <hi>Andrew</hi>) being corrupted with Money, delivered him up into the hands of <hi>Photius.</hi> On the other ſide, the Empreſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving advertiſement from <hi>Antonina,</hi> and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome ill accident might befal her, ſent orders to <hi>Belliſarius</hi> to come back with her to the Court. This order came no ſooner to the ears of <hi>Photius,</hi> but he ſent <hi>Theodoſius</hi> into <hi>Cicily,</hi> where his Army was in its Winter Quarters; To thoſe who conveyed him, he gave inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to carry him as privately as poſſible, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver him into the hands of the Cicilians as ſoon as they were arrived, and to tell no body where
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60251:10"/>they had diſpoſed him. <hi>Caligonus</hi> he took along with himſelf, and all the wealth of <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> and carried them to <hi>Gonſtantinople:</hi> Then it was, that the Empreſs <hi>Theodora</hi> would give an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to all mankind, by recompenſing the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of <hi>Antonina,</hi> by actions of greater cruelty, and crimes of greater infamy then her own. <hi>Antonina</hi> not long before had betrayed <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Cappadocia</hi> to the Empreſs; but the Empreſs out did her in the requital, For ſhe cauſed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral perſons to be put into <hi>Antoninaes</hi> hands, who (notwithſtanding that they were inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent) were all of them put to death. In brief, many Friends and Relations, both to <hi>Photius</hi> and <hi>Belliſarius</hi> (whoſe only guilt was acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with them) were drubbed and conveyed away where no body could ever hear of them; others were baniſhed by her, and for no other crime, but for being intimate with them. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt, there was one <hi>Theodoſius</hi> who had accompanied <hi>Photius</hi> to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> ſhe cauſed this <hi>Theodoſius</hi> to be apprehended, and having ſeiſed upon his eſtate, ſhe gave order to put him into a Dungeon where no day was to be ſeen, and made him be tied up by the Neck to a Rackſtaff ſo ſhort, that he was forced to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the ſame poſture, without being able to turn himſelf; ſo that he was forced to eat and ſleep, and evacuat as he ſtood, without any thing but his ſpeech, to diſcriminate him from a Beaſt. In this cruel condition he continued four Moneths; after which, (though the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs gave him his liberty) yet his ſpirits being
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60251:10"/>depreſſed with his afflictions, he died with the very thoughts of what miſeries he had ſuffered. She conſtrained <hi>Belliſarius</hi> to reconcile himſelf with his Wife, in ſpight of his averſion, and what ever he could do to prevent it. <hi>Photius</hi> had a thouſand ſtripes with a Stirrup-leather up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Reins and the Shoulders, to make him confeſs what he had done with <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Caligonus.</hi> But though he was much weakned and dejected with his uſage (having been natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally tender, infirm, and exceeding careful of his health, which care, till that time, had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved him from any conſiderable affliction) yet he would never forfeit his Oath, nor diſcover his intrigue with <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> though not long after it came out another way, for <hi>Theodora</hi> found out <hi>Caligonus,</hi> and returned him to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonina;</hi> and having got intelligence where <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> was, ſhe ſent for him to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and concealed him in her Palace. The next morning ſhe ſent for <hi>Antonina,</hi> and told her, <hi>Dear</hi> Antonina, <hi>this day I have been preſented with a Jewel, I conceive not to be matched in the whole World: If you have a curioſity to ſee it, I am ſo far from refuſing you that priviledge, I ſhall think, my ſelf happy to ſhow it. Antonina</hi> not dreaming what it ſhould be, was impatient to ſee it, and the Empreſs entring into the Chamber of one of her Eunuchs, brought out <hi>Theodoſius</hi> in her hand. At the unexpectedneſs of the ſight, her joy put her into ſo ſudden an amaze, for ſome time <hi>Antonina</hi> was not able to ſpeak; but being a little recollected, ſhe made a thouſand ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60251:11"/>of thankfulneſs to the Empreſs, called her excellent Miſtreſs, incomparable Benefactreſs, and the Preſerver of her happineſs in this World. <hi>Theodora</hi> kept <hi>Theodoſius</hi> in her Palace, and uſed all means poſſible to re-eſtabliſh him, and put him at the head of the Emperors Army, and in the mean time entertained him with all kind of delights; but Divine Juſtice (which ſooner or later, overtakes all ſuch criminals) ordered it otherwiſe, for he died not long after of a fit of the Cholick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theodora</hi> had her Dungeons ſo deep, ſo pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, ſo remote, and ſo horribly dark, the night, and the day were not poſſibly to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed in them. In one of thoſe diſmal places, the poor <hi>Photius</hi> was kept cloſe along time, though (I know not by what good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune) twice he had eſcaped. The firſt time he got into the Church of our Lady (which is of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal veneration in <hi>Conſtantinople</hi>) and threw himſelf before the Altar; but the Empreſs ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving notice, fetched him out by violence, and recommitted him to his Dungeon. The ſecond time he hid himſelf in a Vault belonging to <hi>Sancta Sophia,</hi> a place of no leſs eſteem among the Chriſtians; but ſhe made no ſcruple to force him from thence, there being no place ſo ſacred, that ſhe was fearful to violate, nay rather, ſhe boaſted and inſulted in her Sacriledges, were the places never ſo holy. The People and the Clergy abominated her impieties, and made a thouſand Imprecations againſt her that committed them; but neither the one, nor the other, had the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60251:11"/>to oppoſe them. About three years, <hi>Photius</hi> had been recluſe in this manner, when the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Zachary</hi> appeared to him in a Dream, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired him to eſcape, and promiſed his aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. This Viſion having encouraged him, he got out of his Dungeon as he could, and having paſſed unknown thorow hundreds of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors, he came at length to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where (having ſhaved) he took the habit of a Monk, and evaded the cruelty of <hi>Theodora.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Belliſarius</hi> having neglected him in his perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions (though he had ſworn ſolemnly to aſſiſt him, and his ſufferings were only for his ſake) no wonder if afterwards God Almighty deſerted in him all his affairs. Being a while after ſent with an Army againſt <hi>Coſroes,</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> who was the third time ravaging the Provinces of the Empire, though he repelled him with honor enough, yet he was ſuſpected of Treaſon: For <hi>Belliſarius</hi> continuing in his Camp, inſtead of purſuing <hi>Coſroes,</hi> who in his retreat over <hi>Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> had made himſelf Maſter of <hi>Callinicum</hi> (a very populous City) and taken many <hi>Romans</hi> priſoners in it, gave occaſion of jealouſie to the World, That it was either want of Fidelity, or Courage; beſides which miſcarriages, there was another accident which augmented his diſgrace. The ſickneſs being at that time in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and many people dying, the Emperor fell very ill among the reſt, and a report was raiſed, that he was dead: The report being general, came at length to the Army of <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> and ſome of the cheif Officers began to talk, That if the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60251:12"/>People of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> were permitted to elect a new Emperor, they ſhould run a great riſque of being continued in the Army, as long as they lived, and never ſee their Countrey again. Not long after the Emperor recovering, the Officers of the Army began to impeach one another, and <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>John Helluo</hi> affirmed, That <hi>Belliſarius</hi> and <hi>Buſez</hi> were the Authors of that diſcourſe. The Empreſs having heard the accuſation, was ſo highly incenſed, that in a great paſſion, ſhe ſent for the cheif Officers to come back to <hi>Conſtantinople:</hi> Having inquired into the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and diſcovered the Authors, ſhe ſent for <hi>Buſez</hi> into her Cloſet, pretending to ſpeak with him about ſome buſineſs of importance: There was a private priſon in her Palace, not to be come at, but by ſeveral turnings. Into that priſon ſhe cauſed <hi>Buſez</hi> to be put, where the poor Man (though he had been Conſul) was kept priſoner a long time, before it was known what was become of him: The Dungeon was ſo perpetually dark, he could not perceive when it was day, and there was no body to inform him, but a poor mute appointed to carry him his victuals, as if he had been a wilde beaſt; the whole World thought he was dead, and no one durſt mention, either him or his memory. When he had been in this manner, as it were, buried alive, two years and four moneths, and in meer pitty was inlarged; he looked like a man come out of another World, loſt his eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight immediately, and began to ſuffer great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities in all parts of his body.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:60251:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Belliſarius</hi> could not be charged with any crime, yet the Empreſs prevailed with her Husband to have him caſhiered, and put <hi>Martin</hi> over his head, to command the Army in the Eaſt. Beſides, ſhe divided the Command of the Targetters, and the Pikemen, and the Guards, which belonged formerly to <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> and were the readieſt and beſt Diſciplined Troops in the whole Army, among certain of her Eunuchs, and other favorites of the Court, who drew Lots for the command of the braveſt Soldiers in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; and by degrees ſhe proceeded ſo far, as to forbid all the friends of <hi>Belliſarius</hi> to have any future correſpondence with him. It was an object well worthy compaſſion, and indeed not eaſily to be believed to ſee the Great <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> who had commanded the whole Force of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, and ſignalized his Conduct and Valor in <hi>Aſia, Europe,</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> creeping a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſtreets of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> alone, without authority, or attendance, melancholly, dejected, and expecting every ſtep to be knocked on the head. The Empreſs deputed one of her Eunuchs to ſeiſe, and bring to her Court a vaſt him of Money which <hi>Belliſarius</hi> had hoarded in the Eaſt.</p>
            <p>All which, <hi>Theodora</hi> did in kindneſs to <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nina,</hi> who was then at a diſtance with her Husband; for ſhe loved <hi>Antonina</hi> exceedingly, upon account of the ſervice which ſhe had done her in the deſtruction of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Cappadocia:</hi> So that if ever <hi>Belliſarius</hi> was to be eaſed of his miſery, or readmitted into favor, the poor
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60251:13"/>man was not only to deſiſt from doing ill to <hi>Antonina,</hi> but to own his life to her, and make himſelf a perfect engine and property of her triumph, <hi>Belliſarius</hi> going to Court one morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, according to his cuſtom, to pay his devoirs to the Emperor, and the Empreſs (though his equipage was but thin, dirty, and in very ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Liveries) he found them very ſower and ſevere upon him, and the Buffoons and Raſcal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Court, began to deſpiſe him: At night he went home, but in great fear, and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing behind him every ſtep, expecting ſome body would have ſtabbed him. When he was got to his houſe, he went up to his chamber, and in great penſiveneſs he ſate down upon his Bed: Thoſe brave maſculine thoughts which do uſually preſent themſelves to great Men, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch occaſions, were far from his mind; on the contrary, his fear had put him into a ſweat, his terror into a trance; and he was in as great confuſion, as the meaneſt caitiff in the World. <hi>Antonina</hi> knew nothing of the matter, and not imagining it in the leaſt, was walking up and down the room, pretending indiſpoſition, to take off her Husband from greater ſuſpitions; when after Sun ſet <hi>Quadratus</hi> came from the Palace, to the houſe of <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> and running up the ſtairs, preſented himſelf ſuddenly at his chamber door, and ſent in word he was come to him from the Empreſs. At the very naming of the Empreſs, <hi>Belliſarius</hi> fell down backward up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Bed, with his arms and his legs ſtretched out, and ready to receive his doom without
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60251:13"/>any defence; ſo ſtrangely had his ancient cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage forſaken him: But <hi>Quadratus</hi> preſented him a Letter from the Empreſs which was almoſt in theſe very terms.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YOu cannot be ignorant,</hi> Belliſarius, <hi>what you have done againſt me, and how highly you have offended; but my obligations to your Wife pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with me, to pardon your crimes, grant you your life, and give you hopes of enjoying your old fortune for the future: But you muſt know, it is your behavior to</hi> Antonina <hi>that muſt give me aſſurance of your intentions.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Belliſarius</hi> was tranſported with joy at the reading of the Letter, and being deſirous that <hi>Quadratus</hi> ſhould be a witneſs in what manner he received it, he threw himſelf down in his preſence, before his Wife, and embracing her knees, and kiſſing her feet, he called her his ſafety and preſervation; proteſting, that for the future he would own himſelf, not only her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, but her Vaſſal and Slave. Moreover, the Empreſs having detained Three thouſand Livers of Gold, out of the ſum which had been taken from <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> ſhe returned him the reſt, which was the ſame meaſure had been uſed with <hi>Gilimere</hi> and <hi>Vitiges,</hi> whom he had conquered not long before.</p>
            <p>The Emperor and Empreſs had caſt an ill eye for a long time upon the immenſe riches of <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> looking upon them as worthy to be added to their own Royal Revenue. They
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60251:14"/>complained; that he had kept to himſelf, great part of <hi>Gilimeres</hi> and <hi>Vitiges</hi> eſtate, not bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it into the Coffers of the Emperor, as a thing of little or no value or concernment. However, they thought it not fit to diſcover their reſentment, becauſe of the many great things he had performed, and leaſt their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods ſhould be blamed in confiſcating the eſtate of a perſon, againſt whom there was no accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, nor any appearance of offence that might give any lawful occaſion againſt him. But the Empreſs knowing that he ſuſpected it, and had loſt his antient conſtancy, ſhe found out a way to ſecure that eſtate by an alliance, and that was by promiſing her Grand-child <hi>Anaſtaſius,</hi> to <hi>Jane,</hi> the only Daughter of <hi>Belliſarius.</hi> In the mean time <hi>Belliſarius</hi> requeſted that he might be reſtored to his charges, and return at the head of the Army, into the Eaſt, to make War upon the King of <hi>Perſia. Antonina</hi> on the other ſide clamored in the ears of the Empreſs, That ſhe would never conſent her Husband ſhould return into thoſe Provinces, where ſhe had ſuffered ſo many indignities, and been ſo barbarouſly treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. The contrariety of their demands obliged the Emperor to make <hi>Belliſarius</hi> Maſter of his Horſe, and ſend him the ſecond time General into <hi>Italy,</hi> but with this condition, That he ſhould defray the whole charge of that War him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, without any expectation from the Emperor. Some there were, who ſuppoſed <hi>Belliſarius</hi> had come to this agreement with his Wife, and the Emperor, with deſign, when he was out of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60251:14"/>
               <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to put himſelf into a poſture of acting againſt <hi>Antonina,</hi> and the reſt, who had uſed him ſo cruelly: But the event manifeſted the contrary, for he forgot all that had paſſed, and inſtead of reflecting upon what he had ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenmly promiſed to <hi>Photius,</hi> and the reſt of his friends, he became a very ſlave to his Wife, and was moſt deſperately enamored, though ſhe was already threeſcore years of age and upwards. Having deſerved the indignation of Heaven, he was no ſooner in <hi>Italy,</hi> but he began to find his fortune adverſe. In his firſt War againſt <hi>Theodat</hi> and <hi>Vitiges,</hi> though the deſigns he undertook (in that juncture) ſeemed raſh and unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, yet they hapned generally to ſucceed well, and had a very good effect. In his ſecond, he was judged a Man of good conduct, and one who underſtood how to take his meaſures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, for he had been well acquainted with the ſtrength, and the weakneſs both of the <hi>Goths,</hi> and of <hi>Italy;</hi> but when things declined, and failed of the ſucceſs that was expected, the World began to quarrel with him, and his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, and he was ſo unhappy, as to confirm them by his future miſcarriage. Certainly the affairs of Man are not regulated by their own Reaſon (whoſe bounds are too narrow and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted) but by the Wiſdom and Providence of God, who governs them as he pleaſes, though ſome (who are ſpectators of events, but know nothing of their cauſes) would attribute all to Fortune; but of that, let every one argue as he pleaſes.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:60251:15"/>
            <p>After his ſecond expedition into <hi>Italy, Belli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarius</hi> was forced to return with diſhonor, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing been five years (as I have ſaid elſwhere) in diſtreſs, not knowing where to be ſecure, or retire with his Troops. <hi>Jotila,</hi> how deſirous ſo ever he ſhewed himſelf to come to an engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, could never bring him to a Battle; ſo great was the terror, as well in himſelf, as his Army: So that inſtead of re-eſtabliſhing the Emperors Affairs in <hi>Italy</hi> (which were in an ill condition) he loſt <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſeveral other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces before his face.</p>
            <p>In all this War, the Emperor ſupplied him not with one farthing of Money, which put him upon great exactions in <hi>Italy,</hi> inſomuch, that his thoughts were wholly applied to the raiſing of Money. He ſlead (as a man may ſay) all the <hi>Sicilians,</hi> the Inhabitants of <hi>Ravenna,</hi> and indeed all <hi>Italy</hi> beſides: For of all who had the misfortune to fall under his power, there was ſcarce one that eſcaped the tyranny of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion, but he made him pay, and ſometimes for things done before he was born. At this rate he would have dealt with <hi>Herodian,</hi> he preſſed him for Money, and preſſed him with all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of threats; but <hi>Herodian</hi> choſe rather to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver up <hi>Spoletto</hi> (where he was Governor) to the <hi>Goths,</hi> not regarding the Fidelity which he had ſworn to the Emperor.</p>
            <p>I think it not improper, in this place, to give an account of the difference which broke out about this time, betwixt <hi>Belliſarius</hi> and his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew <hi>John,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Vitalian;</hi> which differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60251:15"/>was the cauſe of great loſſes to the Empire of <hi>Rome.</hi> The Empreſs had ſo great an averſion for <hi>Germanus,</hi> and diſſembled it ſo little, that no body durſt ally themſelves with him, though he was the Emperors Brothers Son. In ſhort, he had ſeveral Sons, but none of them could marry whileſt <hi>Theodora</hi> was living: He had a Daughter likewiſe called <hi>Juſtina,</hi> which was already eighteen years of age, and unmarried; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Germanus</hi> was conſtrained to propoſe a match betwixt the ſaid Daughter, and <hi>John,</hi> whom <hi>Belliſarius</hi> had ſent to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> though indeed in condition <hi>Belliſarius</hi> was much inferior to <hi>Germanus.</hi> The overture being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, it was thought neceſſary by matual and inviolable Oaths, to oblige one another to uſe all poſſible means to conſummate the match; for they were jealous on both ſides, <hi>John,</hi> becauſe the Lady was above his quality; and <hi>Germanus,</hi> becauſe if he loſt him, he deſpaired of another. The Empreſs inraged at this alliance, plaid them a hundred tricks to have broke it off; but find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all of them fail, and that her menaces were not able to divert them, ſhe ſignified to <hi>John,</hi> that his life was in danger: Whereupon having order to return into <hi>Italy,</hi> he had no farther communication with <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> whileſt <hi>Antinona</hi> was with him in <hi>Italy,</hi> apprehending (with good reaſon) the deſigns of that wicked Woman; for it was too probable, and not irrational for him to ſuſpect, that the Empreſs had given her order to make him away, and it was the more credible conſidering the nature of <hi>Antonina,</hi> and the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60251:16"/>fondneſs of <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> who indulged his Wife in what ever ſhe deſired; ſo much was his love, beyond all limits of reaſon.</p>
            <p>This fear being grounded upon ſo many ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances of truth, made a deep impreſſion in the mind of <hi>John.</hi> From that time the affairs of the Emperor went utterly to wreck, as want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a perſon that was able to buoy them; for <hi>Belliſarius</hi> finding the <hi>Goths</hi> extreamly ſucceſsful, and advance in all their undertakings, he deſired liberty to return out of <hi>Italy;</hi> which being granted by the Emperor, he took his leave of the <hi>Roman</hi> Troops without any trouble, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of all <hi>Italy;</hi> the greateſt part of which, he left in the hands of the <hi>Goths. Peruſia</hi> was at that time diſtreſſed by a long ſiege, and being taken whileſt he was in his journey to <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> it endured all the miſeries to which Towns that are taken by Aſſault, are uſually ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed: But the State was not unhappy alone, <hi>Belliſarius</hi> had his private misfortunes in his own family. The Empreſs <hi>Theodora</hi> employed the utmoſt of her power to accompliſh the match betwixt her Grandſon <hi>Anaſtaſius,</hi> and the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> obliging him to write continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to her Parents to expedite the buſineſs. The Parents to gain him, deſired it might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted till they returned to <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> The Empreſs ſuſpecting their deſign, commanded them back, but they deſired to be excuſed, and wrote word they could not ſtir out of <hi>Italy.</hi> She perceived their cunning immediately, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Belliſarius</hi> had no other children, and that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60251:16"/>his daughter would infallibly be heir to his eſtate, ſhe reſolved <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> ſhould have her, let it coſt what it would; for ſhe began now to be jealous of <hi>Antonina,</hi> and not to place that confidence in her as formerly, apprehending, That as ſoon as ſhe was dead, <hi>Antonina</hi> would forget the friendſhip ſhe had ſhown her in all her exigences, and abandoning the Intereſts of her family, break off all the leagues and engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments betwixt them.</p>
            <p>Theſe conſiderations put her upon an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe full of wickedneſs and impiety. She lodged the daughter in the ſame Chamber with <hi>Anaſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> contrary to all Modeſty, and ſacred Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: It was reported at the ſame time, that he had violated her privately, that the Emperor might not oppoſe himſelf the Wedding, when it was ſo far advanced, as the loſs of her virginity. After which, <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued with her about eight moneths, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to love one another, and their paſſion to grow ardent and ſtrong.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Antonina</hi> arrived at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and the Empreſs was dead, ſhe pretended to be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of what had paſſed, and not regarding what might be ſaid to the diſhonor of her daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (ſo ſhe could find her another match) ſhe forced her to renounce <hi>Anaſtaſius;</hi> which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered her the moſt perfidious Woman upon the Earth: Yet all that could not hinder, but ſhe got <hi>Belliſarius</hi> of her ſide, when he returned out of <hi>Italy.</hi> This it was which gave the World a perfect view of his humor and ſpirit. When he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60251:17"/>brake his engagements with <hi>Photius,</hi> and the reſt of his friends, he was eaſily pardoned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was not thought ſo much the charms of his Wife, as the fear of the Empreſs, that made him violate his oaths. But when the ſaid Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs was dead, it was obſerved, that inſtead of thinking upon <hi>Photius,</hi> and the reſt, he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted himſelf intirely to the dictates of his Wife, and her confident <hi>Caligonus,</hi> he began to be deſpiſed, as a man of no courage, and to be laughed at as a fool. And theſe to ſpeak freely, were the faults of <hi>Belliſarius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What <hi>Sergius</hi> the Son of <hi>Bacchus</hi> performed in <hi>Africk,</hi> I have mentioned elſwhere; and it was he who was the cauſe of the diſorders in that Countrey. He paſſed his Parole to the <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cathians,</hi> and confirmed it by a ſolemn oath up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Evangeliſts, and yet made no ſcruple to break it. He cauſed fourſcore of their Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, ſent to him about their affairs, to be ſtabbed, when there was not the leaſt ſuſpition of any evil deſign; yet he invited them to dinner, and cauſed them all to be ſlain, without any care or reflection upon his oath: And this was the cauſe, not only of the death of <hi>Salomon,</hi> but of the loſs of the <hi>Africans,</hi> and Imperial Forces.</p>
            <p>After the death of <hi>Salomon,</hi> the remaining Generals and Armies ſhew no great deſire to fight, eſpecially <hi>John,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Siſinius,</hi> who appeared not upon any occaſion, till <hi>Ariobindus</hi> arrived in <hi>Africk.</hi> This was an effect of their hatred to <hi>Sergius,</hi> for beſides that, he was nice,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60251:17"/>and effeminate, and without courage; he was young, impertinent, angry with the whole World, and inſupportably proud. But having married the Neice of <hi>Antonina,</hi> Wife to <hi>Belliſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> the Empreſs would not ſuffer him to be queſtioned, nor permit her Husband to turn him out of his Government of <hi>Africk,</hi> though it was viſible enough, his affairs in that Province were in danger of ruine. She obtained likewiſe, that the Emperor diſmiſſed and pardoned his young Brother <hi>Salomon</hi> for the murder of <hi>Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> which hapned as follows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pagaſius</hi> having redeemed <hi>Salomon,</hi> paid his ranſom to the <hi>Lencathians,</hi> and brought the <hi>Barbarians</hi> home, returned to <hi>Carthage</hi> with <hi>Salomon,</hi> and a few Soldiers in his company. By the way he remonſtrated to <hi>Salomon</hi> the wrong he had done, in having committed ſo great an offence, and that he ought to remember, That he was delivered out of the hands of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies by a particular providence. <hi>Salomon</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving he had reproached him as a ſlave, and being exaſperated, killed him upon the place, to requite what he had done for him in ſaving his life; and when he came to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the Emperor diſcharged him of the fact, and gave him his pardon in writing. As ſoon as he was cleared of that danger, <hi>Salomon</hi> departed to ſee his friends in the Eaſt; but by an evident puniſhment inflicted by Divine Juſtice, he died by the way.</p>
            <p>This being the paſſage betwixt <hi>Pagaſius</hi> and <hi>Salomon,</hi> I ſhall return now to <hi>Theodora</hi> and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60251:18"/>
               <hi>Juſtianian,</hi> and give an account of their humors, their manner of conduct, and by what methods of Tyranny they afflicted the Empire of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leo</hi> being in the Throne of the Empire, three young Men of <hi>Illyrium,</hi> called <hi>Zimarque, Yti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſte,</hi> and <hi>Juſtin</hi> (born in <hi>Bederiane,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to walk up and down the World) to avoid the extream poverty which they ſuffered, took a reſolution to put themſelves into the Army, and came on foot to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> each of them with an old naſty Coat on his back, and nothing with them but a few Bisket for their voyage. The Emperor having received them into pay, put them into his <hi>Gardes du Corps,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were very proper and perſonable men. When <hi>Leo</hi> was dead, and the Empire de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved upon <hi>Anaſtaſius,</hi> he ſent a brave Army under the command of <hi>John de Boſſu,</hi> againſt the <hi>Iſſaurians</hi> who were in Rebellion. After ſome few days march, the ſaid General cauſed <hi>Juſtin</hi> to be clapped in priſon, upon ſome enormity, with deſign to have had him executed the next day: But (as the ſaid <hi>Boſſu</hi> confeſſed many times ſince) he was diverted by a Viſion, which appeared to him in the night, in the ſhape of a more then ordinary Man, requiring him to ſet him at liberty, whom he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the day before. When <hi>Boſſu</hi> awaked, he regarded not his Viſion, and though it appeared again the next night, he took no more notice of it then before: But the third night being viſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed again, the Viſion threatned him more fiercely
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60251:18"/>then formerly, and told him, That when time ſerved, there would be great uſe of the priſoner, and his friends, and ſo commanded him to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge him, or he would make him ſenſible of his diſpleaſure; and by this means <hi>Juſtin</hi> was preſerved. In proceſs of time, the ſaid <hi>Juſtin</hi> came into great credit with the Emperor <hi>Anaſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> who gave him the command of his Guards, by whom after the death of <hi>Anaſtaſius,</hi> he was choſen Emperor of <hi>Rome,</hi> though he was ſo old he was quite grey, and (which never hapned to the <hi>Romans</hi> before) ſo ignorant, he knew not one Letter of the Book; inſomuch, That it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cuſtom for the Emperors to write all their Warrants under their own hands, he could neither write, nor ſubſcribe them, but left it to <hi>Prochus</hi> his Queſtor, who was continually with him, and gave out what Orders he pleaſed. That the Emperors hand might appear to every thing that was ordered, one of his Officers found out this invention; He took a piece of a Board, and ſhaving it very thin, he cauſed the Letters of the Emperors name to be cut tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in Latine Characters; and when it was finiſhed, clapped it upon the Paper, where the Order was written, and giving the Pen to the Emperor, another took him by the hand, and guided it in the cuts, till his name was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed; after which they retired, and their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were compleat, and in this manner <hi>Juſtin</hi> governed the Empire. His Wife (called <hi>Lupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cina</hi>) had been a ſlave, was born a <hi>Barbarian,</hi> and having been bought by <hi>Juſtin,</hi> and ſerved
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60251:19"/>him a long time in the nature of a Concubine, he married her, and ſhe lived with him to his dying day. <hi>Juſtin</hi> was not capable of doing his Subjects either good or hurt; for he was a Man of extraordinary ſtupidity and ſottiſhneſs, and extraordinary brutiſh. But <hi>Juſtinian</hi> his Siſters Son, who was young, and governed the State, brought more and greater evils upon the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, then were ever mentioned in all the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of former times. He made no ſcruple of ſequeſtring any mans eſtate, nor murdering any mans perſon, and could without any remorſe give orders for the putting to death a great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of innocent perſons at once. He never executed the reſolutions that were taken, but on the contrary was ſo great a lover of Novelty, that he delighted to ſubvert and undo all things that were well ordered, with a word. During his Reign, as I have ſaid before in my other Books) there hapned ſo great a contagion quite thorow his Dominions, that few or none eſcaped who were infected, and few or none eſcaped without infection: But as to the Tyranny of <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> there was ſcarce a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Empire but had had ſome experiment of it. This unhappy Prince (as if he had been ſent down from Heaven as a Plague upon his People) put ſome of them to death in a criminal way; and others he kept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, but in ſuch deplorable poverty, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired a thouſand times to be delivered by the greateſt puniſhment he could inflict. Not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented that he had ruined and ſubverted the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60251:19"/>
               <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, he imployed his Armies for the Conqueſt of <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Africk,</hi> to involve thoſe two brave Countreys in the ſame cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities which he had brought upon the other Provinces that had ſubmitted to his Dominion. He was ſcarce ten days in Authority, before he put <hi>Amantius</hi> to death (who was the cheif of the Court Eunuchs) and many others, upon no other grounds, but becauſe they had ſpoke too liberally againſt <hi>John,</hi> the Patriarch of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> which made him afterwards the moſt terrible Man in the World. About the ſame time he ſent for the Tyrant <hi>Vitalian,</hi> promiſed him (in the Emperors name) ſincere amity, obliged him to embrace the Chriſtian Religion; but growing jealous of him afterwards, and ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting he was not true to his intereſts, he cauſed him, and all his Relations and Friends to be ſtabbed in the middle of the Court without the leaſt compunction for the breach of his Faith, which is a ſacred thing among all Men.</p>
            <p>As I have ſaid before, there were at that time two contrary factions among the people; of which, having gained the <hi>Venetes,</hi> and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aged them along while, he had all the liberty he could deſire to moleſt and diſorder every thing as he pleaſed; ſo that having found the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire declining, he eaſily finiſhed its deſtruction, though the moſt ſeditious of that party, who ſerved him in the execution of his tyrannical deſigns, have paſſed ſince for the moſt moderate of all Men, becauſe they did not
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60251:20"/>abuſe that liberty to do miſcheif, which was given them, as they might have done. Thoſe of the oppoſite party (which was called the faction of the <hi>Praſinians</hi>) committed ſeveral murders and outrages as they had opportunity, and it was in their power, though from time to time, ſome of them ſuffered privately very cruel puniſhments, which did but animate the reſt; for it is frequently ſeen, that injury does but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperate, and provoke people to betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to force; and the deſire of revenge car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries them on to ſuch ill actions as they would not do, had they not been irritated before. The <hi>Venetes</hi> having got the priority, the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire was utterly overturned, and all things put into confuſion without poſſibility of recovery. The Cities and Towns were ruined, as if they bad been pillaged by an Enemy, or deſtroyed by ſome Earthquake or Inundation; all things ran into moſt deſperate diſorder. Juſtice and the Laws were quite out of force, the Face of the Government was intirely changed, and in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time all things ran headlong to ruine. The Factions began to be effeminate, to take delight in their Hair, and to cut it after a mode that was quite new to the <hi>Romans;</hi> they ſhaved not their Beards as formerly, but ſuffered them to grow long like the <hi>Perſians;</hi> they ſhaved the fore part of their Head to their very Temples, leaving it thick as poſſible behind, after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the <hi>Maſſagets;</hi> and this kind of cut they called <hi>The Mode of the Huns.</hi> They made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves rich Cloaths, embroidered very magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficently,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60251:20"/>and more coſtly by far then their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions would bear, had not the Money they had gotten by their Violences, furniſhed them with wherewithal. The Sleeves of their Veſts were extream ſtrait at their Wriſts, but from thence to their Sholders, they were extraordinary wide, inſomuch, that when upon the Theater, or in the Circus when they ſtretched forth their hands, either in ſpeaking themſelves, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing of others, they expoſed that part of the Body, that Sots and Fools might be induced to believe it was the ſtrength and greatneſs of their Arm, which obliged them to wear them ſo large, not perceiving that the vacuity and wideneſs of the Sleeve, did rather diſcover the ſmalneſs of their Limbs. They took alſo the Doublet and the Hoſe, and ſeveral other faſhions from the <hi>Huns,</hi> and gave them the names which they retain ſtill among the people. At firſt they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Daggers privately under their Coats, and meeting in little troops as ſoon as day was ſhut in, they took their Poſts, poſſeſſed themſelves of the corners of the Streets, robbed all that paſt by, took away their Cloaks, their Belts, their Gold Buckles, or what ever elſe they thought convenient for them. Some they killed after they had robbed them, that they might tell no tales, nor diſcover who had wronged them. All people were fellow ſufferers in theſe exorbitancies, but eſpecially thoſe who were not of the faction of the <hi>Venetes;</hi> finding they could not do otherwiſe ſecurely, they began to wear Claſps and Buckles of Copper upon their
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60251:21"/>Belts, and their Cloaths were made meaner then perhaps their qualities did require, leaſt the richneſs of their habits might bring their lives into danger, and every one went home be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore night, for fear of ambuſhments by the way. Theſe miſcheifs increaſed every day, and the ſeditious grew more inſolent, becauſe the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates of the Town puniſhed not the guilty; ſo that crimes increaſed eaſily, by the ſecurity of committing them; for they were not ſevere enough in their corrections to reach at the Root, and many were hurried into them by the impetuoſity of their natures. And this was the behavior of the <hi>Venetes;</hi> for the other faction, moſt of them changed their party, to revenge themſelves in their particular quarrels: Some hid themſelves where they could, others were maſſacred by their Enemies, or died of the puniſhments which the Magiſtrate inflicted. A good party of youth of the Town Joyned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with that faction, not for any inclination to them for their power, but becauſe the vigor of their age, and the liberty they affected, prompted them thereto: There was no ſort of crime uncommitted in theſe times, nor none that was committed, was puniſhed as it ought. At firſt they ſlew only ſuch as were of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary faction; but by degrees they ſpared no body, but killed the innocent, and thoſe who had never offended them. They ſuffered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be hired for Money to murder the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of other People, and their pretence was, That they were of the faction of the <hi>Praſinians,</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:60251:21"/>though they knew the contrary: They did not hide themſelves now to do their villanies as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: They waited not till night as they had formerly done, but committed their cruelties at noon day, in the midſt of the Town, and in the preſence of the moſt conſiderable Perſons; and they needed not to abſcond, for they were ſo far from fearing correction, That they eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it a great honor and reputation to them, when they could kill a poor unarmed man, which they met by accident in their way, at a ſingle blow. During theſe diſorders, no man was ſecure of his life, every man was in danger every moment; no time, no place could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect them, for the factions cut the throats of whom they pleaſed in the moſt ſacred of their Temples, and during the moſt ſolemn of their Ceremonies. No man could truſt either his Kinred or Friends, for commonly they murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moſt of them who truſted them too eaſily. No accuſation nor proceſs was made out againſt any man, and a million of perſons were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed without any oppoſition, and no body went about to ſuccor or relieve them. The Laws loſt all their authority, Contracts were void, and unprofitable, and all things were decided with violence and confuſion. In ſhort, the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire degenerated into a kind of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuable tyranny, ſubject every day to change and innovation. The great Men were cowed, and dejected like ſo many ſlaves, and all for the fear of one Man. The Judges determined not of their Cauſes according to Law, but as the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60251:22"/>parties were beloved or hated by the factions; for it was as much as the Judges life was worth, to reject the orders of the <hi>Venetes,</hi> or neglect to obey them. Several Creditors were forced to deliver up their Securities to their Debtors, and loſe all that they had lent them. Others were forced to manumit their ſlaves, young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the beſt Families of the City being of the factions, forced Moneys from their own Parents, and conſtrained ſeveral Women to ſubmit to the brutiſh appetites of their ſlaves. Children even in ſight of their Parents, were forced to ſuffer the effects of the brutality of the ſeditious, and married Women were no more exempted then they. It was reported, that ſome of theſe factions having met a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in no extraordinary habit, who was croſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Water with her Husband in little Boat, to go into the Suburbs on the other ſide, they forced her out of the arms of her Husband into their Boat. The Woman whiſpered her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band in the ear, and adviſed him not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, or fear that ſhe would do any thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of her, for ſhe was reſolved not to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any thing that might have reflexion upon his honor; and a while after, as he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining to himſelf, and following her with tears in his eyes, ſhe threw her ſelf over board, and was drowned.</p>
            <p>The violences uſed by the ſeditious in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> did not ſo much exaſperate the ſpirits of the people, as what <hi>Juſtinian</hi> himſelf did againſt the State; for the ſorrows of the afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60251:22"/>are much diminiſhed, whilſt they have hopes of revenging themſelves on their unjuſt perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors by the help of the Magiſtrate. In effect, when hope keeps up the heart, preſent miſeries are eaſily ſupported: But when we are perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by the Prince himſelf, who has all the power in his own hands, our ſufferings are more ſenſible, and we are more prone to deſpair, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have no hopes left to be revenged. <hi>Juſtinian</hi> was not only culpable in neglecting the cries of the diſtreſſed, but that in ſight of the whole World he gave protection to the young men of the ſedition, would have all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple know it, gave them vaſt eſtates, had many of them about him in his train, and advanced ſome of them to the dignity of Magiſtrates. In the ſame manner as things were carried in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> they were managed in the ſmalleſt villages; ſo that it was like a Plague, which having begun in the capital City, diſſuſed it ſelf, and ravaged the whole Empire, without any concernment in the Emperor, who took no notice of what was perpetrated in the <hi>Circus</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his very Noſe; ſo ſtrangely ſottiſh was he grown. <hi>Juſtinian</hi> having neglected his affairs, put every thing in diſorder; no ſooner did he find himſelf in the Throne of the Empire, but he made it his whole buſineſs to drain and exhauſt the publick Treaſures which he had in his hand. For beſides the great expence which he was at for the reception of the <hi>Huns,</hi> who came fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to viſit him, he gave them large pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents when they went away. From that time,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60251:23"/>the Provinces under the <hi>Roman</hi> Dominion were ſubject to the frequent inroads of the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> who returned often for their riches; for after they had once taſted the ſweetneſs of them, they would never be without them. He took a fancy to expend vaſt ſums of Money in building of Moles, and Stovadoes of prodigious extent, to break the force of the waves, and with immenſe pieces of Stone to put bounds to the Sea, and by force of his Money, to compel that Element to a ſence of his Empire. He ſequeſtred the eſtates of particular perſons, and ſqueezed them into his own Coffers, charging ſome with imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary crimes, and perſwading others, that they had given him their eſtates. Some to ſave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from death, having been accuſed of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racides and Murders, and other fictitious crimes, gave all they had to the Emperor. Others in ſuit with their Neighbors, and finding it was like to go againſt them in ſpight of their Law. yers, made over their right to their Prince, only to make themſelves known to him, and pleaſe him, who took all without giving them a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; by which unjuſt kind of Champerty they many times ruined their adverſaries, when they thought themſelves ſecure. His ſtature was neither too great nor too little, well proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and rather inclinable to be fat; his face was round and comely, his complexion was freſh, and ſome times when he had eaten nothing in two days. In a word, he was very like the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Domitian</hi> (Son to the Great <hi>Veſpaſian</hi>) whoſe ill deeds were ſo terrible among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:60251:23"/>that their hatred continued after they had torn him in pieces; and by an Act of the Senate it was commanded, That he ſhould not be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in any future Record, and that all his ſtatues ſhould be deſtroyed; and their command was ſo well executed, That there is not to be ſeen in <hi>Rome</hi> any inſcription of his name, unleſs in ſuch places where he is numbred among the other Emperors, nor does there remain in the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, any of his ſtatues except one, which was left upon this following occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Domitian</hi> had a Princeſs to his Wife, ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and good, ſhe never did miſcheif, nor ſo much as offended any perſon alive, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways diſapproved the crimes of her Husband; ſo that being exceedingly beloved, after the death of <hi>Domitian,</hi> the Senate ſent for her, gave her leave to make her demands, and promiſed to grant them without difficulty. The vertuous Lady deſired liberty to bury the Body of her Husband, and erect a ſtatue of Braſs for him, where ſhe ſhould think it convenient, and the Senate complying, ſhe contrived that of which I ſpeak, to leave to poſterity a Monument of the cruelty of thoſe perſons who made away her Husband: She cauſed the pieces of his Body to be found out, and having joyned and placed them in order as well as ſhe could, ſhe ſhewed them to the Statuaries, who taking his Mold, caſt him afterwards in Braſs, and ſhe cauſed it to be ſet up at the Foot of the Mountain of the Capitol, on the right hand as you come from
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60251:24"/>the Palace: And this is the only ſtatue in being, that gives us any remembrance, either of the Viſage, or Fortune of <hi>Domitian.</hi> By obſerving of this ſtatue, one may ſee the proportion and features of <hi>Juſtinian:</hi> His manners would be troubleſome to deſcribe exactly, and I queſtion whether I could do it or no.</p>
            <p>He was crafty, and yet eaſie to be deceived; ſo that he might be ſaid to be cunning and weak, both together: He never told, nor ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied any thing that was true, to any who had buſineſs with him; but by the malignity of his nature, he endeavored to circumvent every body, though he himſelf was continually ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the fallacies of other people. This was the ridiculous temper of <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> in whom I find verified what a Peripatetick Philoſopher maintained formerly, <hi>That as contrary colours accord well enough when they are mingled in the Paint, ſo contrary qualities do in the nature of Man.</hi> And to ſpeak what I found in him to be true, <hi>Juſtinian</hi> diſſembled ſo perfectly well, that there was no man concealed his ſentiments ſo well, conducted a fraud with more dexterity, acted ſo ſubtilly in every thing, and put a better coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance upon his anger and indignation: He had no need of the aſſiſtance of joy or of grief, to bring the tears into his eyes, having ſome of them ready in reſerve upon every occaſion; though he cheated by continued falſhoods, yet it was with premeditation. When he had paſſed his Parole, and ſet his hand to what he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and contracted with his Subjects, he
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60251:24"/>brake all without any remorſe, as audaciouſly as thoſe ſlaves who are forced only by threats to the performance of their promiſes: He was inconſtant to his friends, and inexorable to his Enemies: He was equally greedy of Blood and of Money: He was a great lover of novelty and troubles: He was eaſily perſwaded when any miſcheif was to be done, but obſtinate and unmovable to any action that was good: He was excellent at inventing new crimes, but the name of vertue he abhorred. Theſe were his defects, beſides other vices (which I omit) and he ſurpaſſed in ſuch ſort the common Impiety of Man, that it might be ſaid, There was drawn what ever was bad out of the reſt of mankind, to make in his perſon a perfect compoſition of wickedneſs: For beſides what I have ſaid, his car was always open to Informers and Traytors, and he impoſed great penalties and puniſhments upon ſuch as were accuſed: He never under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood any cauſe that he judged, but contenting himſelf with the accuſation, he gave ſentence without any reaſon, and many times by one ſingle word under his hand, he gave orders (ſuddenly) that Towns ſhould be ruined, Cities ſhould be burned, and whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys over-run; ſo that if one would exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all that has hapned in the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire from its foundation, and compare it with this age, he would finde more murders committed by <hi>Juſtinians</hi> order or permiſſion, then in all the ages before him: He ingroſſed the Eſtates of other people with incredible avarice: He ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60251:25"/>them without any pretence, and when he had them in his power, he thought of them no more, but gave them away in extravagant largeſſes to the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> or ſpent them in ridiculous buildings; and to conclude in few words, He had no Money himſelf, and would ſuffer no body elſe to have any, diſcovering in that, that it was not covetouſneſs alone which excited him to thoſe things, but malice and envy; ſo that having exhauſted the whole Treaſure of the Empire, he was occaſion of the univerſal impoveriſhment of the whole World. And this as near as I could, is the Character of <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> if he may be deſcribed by the Pen.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now ſpeak of his Wife, and give an account of her birth, education, manners, and by what accident ſhe came to be Empreſs, and how ſhe aſſiſted the Emperor towards the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Empire. There was at <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> a Man called <hi>Acacius,</hi> who had the charge of the Beaſts, which the Faction of the <hi>Praſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> cauſed to be kept for the ſhews in the Amphiteater. This <hi>Acacius</hi> died of the ſickneſs, under the Raign of <hi>Anaſtatius,</hi> leaving behind him three Daughters, <hi>Comitone, Theodora,</hi> and <hi>Anaſtatia;</hi> the eldeſt not above ſeven years old. Their Mother finding her ſelf a Widow, began to look out for another Husband, who might manage her affairs at home, and exerciſe her charge; but <hi>Aſterius</hi> being ſuperintendant of the ſhows which the <hi>Praſinians</hi> made, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bribed by Money, took her Husbands office
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60251:25"/>from her, and gave it to him who had corrupted him; for thoſe places are perquiſites to the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendants, and depend wholly upon them. The Mother of <hi>Theodora</hi> ſeeing the people aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled one day, to behold the combat of the Beaſts, preſented her three Daughters before them with Crowns of Flowers upon their Heads, and Bracelets of the ſame, and begged of them that they would continue their Fathers office to them; but the <hi>Praſinians</hi> refuſed it by common conſent. On the other ſide the <hi>Venetes</hi> having loſt the officer which had the care of their Beaſts, gave it to the Mother, and her three Daughters, to recompence what they had loſt with the <hi>Praſinians.</hi> The Mother finding her ſelf re-eſtabliſhed, preſented her Daughters up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Stage one after another, as they grew up, and occaſion was offered. <hi>Comitone</hi> the eldeſt was already famous among the reſt of the <hi>Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſans;</hi> and <hi>Theodora</hi> the ſecond, waited upon her as her Maid with little Sleeves, and ſhort Coats, carrying her chair upon her back when her ſiſter went into company. But when ſhe came to maturity, and her beauty began to be celebrated, her Mother devoted her to the Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and a while after ſhe took her place among the <hi>Courtiſans,</hi> which the Antients called the <hi>Barefeet,</hi> (for ſhe played not upon the Flute, or any other Inſtrument, nor ſung, but proſtituted her ſelf indifferently to all people that ſhe met) at length ſhe aſſociated with a company of Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, where ſhe perſonated all people, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented Farces, and ſuch kind of Comical Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60251:26"/>for ſhe was naturally very pleaſant, and ſpoke things very well; ſo that in a ſhort time ſhe drew the Eyes of the whole World up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her, and eſpecially, becauſe having no ſhame, nor vertue, ſhe acted any part, how unhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſoever. She was of ſuch a conſtitution, ſhe could take any injury or affront, and having complained to the full, ſhe would change her note, and laugh as if her heart would break. For this cauſe, when civil or vertuous people met her in the Palace or the Streets, they turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed another way to avoid her, leaſt approaching her, or by accident touching but her cloaths, they ſhould have participated of her debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; and they who encountered her in the morning, looked upon it as an ill Omen, and expected no good the following day; ſhe had a mortal animoſity againſt all Women of her own profeſſion.</p>
            <p>This being her life for ſome time, ſhe came into <hi>Syria</hi> with <hi>Hecebolus</hi> of <hi>Tyre,</hi> Governor of <hi>Pentapolis,</hi> as an inſtrument of his pleaſures; but ſome difference falling out, he turned her off, and diſmiſſed her. Falling afterwards into diſtreſs, her neceſſities obliged her to her old way of proſtitution. At firſt ſhe came to <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> aftewards (having practiſed quite tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the Eaſt) ſhe arrived at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving exerciſed a profeſſion that cannot with modeſty be named; nay, the Devil ſo wrought with her, that there was not a place in the whole Empire where <hi>Theodora</hi> had not left the marks of her immodeſty.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:60251:26"/>
            <p>Being educated in this manner, and her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation being agreeable, ſhe became the moſt famous of all Women that ever were debauched. She had not been long at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> before <hi>Juſtinian</hi> fell moſt deſperately in love with her. At firſt he entertained her only as a <hi>Miſs,</hi> though he preferred her to the dignity of a Patrician: The fondneſs of <hi>Juſtinian</hi> (to whoſe pleaſures ſhe devoted her ſelf wholly) made her way eaſie to a moſt eminent degree of authority, and to the amaſſing and heaping up immenſe riches in a very ſhort time; for (according to the cuſtom of thoſe Lovers, whoſe Paſſion is extravagant) he gave her what ever ſhe deſired, and ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired what ever was to be given, and the redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancy of her wealth added new fewel to his flames.</p>
            <p>This was the <hi>Theodora,</hi> which was <hi>Juſtinians</hi> colleague in the deſtruction of the State, and the ruine of the People, not in <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but in all places under the <hi>Roman</hi> Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and the rather, becauſe being both of the party of the <hi>Venetes,</hi> they had put the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into the hands of that faction, though indeed the evil was delayed for ſome time by this following accident.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Juſtinian</hi> was ſurpriſed with a long, and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious ſickneſs, and it was reported in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he was dead. During his indiſpoſition, that faction committed all the exorbitancies afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and they proceeded ſo far as to kill a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of quality, called <hi>Hypatius,</hi> in the very Church of S. <hi>Sophia:</hi> The wickedneſs of that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60251:27"/>action put the people into an uproar, they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, and went in a tumultuous manner to the Emperor <hi>Juſtin,</hi> (glad with all their hearts, that they had an opportunity, in which the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> permitted them to complain of the violences which they had ſuffered, and what miſeries he had brought upon others.) This addreſs of the people prevailed with the Emperor to ſend Orders to the Governor of the City called <hi>Theodotus Cucurbitinus,</hi> to inquire into the buſineſs, and bring the offenders to puniſhment. He obſerved his orders very punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, for having made inquiſition, and taken ſome of the offenders, he cauſed them to be puniſhed according to the ſeverity of the Law; ſome ſaved their lives by hiding themſelves in Dens and by places, and were reſerved to periſh afterwards with the Empire it ſelf. <hi>Juſtinian</hi> recovering miraculouſly of his diſtemper, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired againſt <hi>Theodotus,</hi> and accuſed him of Magick; but failing in that deſign, by violence and tortures he conſtrained one of his friends to bring in a falſe accuſation againſt him. The buſineſs coming before the Senate, and no body daring to oppoſe the vnjuſt deſigns of <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> it had like to have gone ill with him; for every body was fearful to ſpeak his judgment, and they thought it ſufficient to condole the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune of <hi>Theodotus</hi> whom <hi>Juſtinian</hi> had ſworn to deſtroy. But <hi>Proclus</hi> the Queſtor, judged him innocent by his authority, and maintained that he was not worthy of death; ſo that all <hi>Juſtinian</hi> could obtain, was his baniſhment out
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60251:27"/>of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and to have him ſent to <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> where having notice that there were plots againſt his life, he was forced to betake himſelf to a Monaſtery where he died: And theſe were the affairs of <hi>Theodotus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Factious after this, became the moſt moderate people in the World, for they made no uſe of the liberty they had at that time (more then ever before) of doing what miſcheif they pleaſed; in ſhort, a while after ſeveral aſſaſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inations were committed, but none puniſhed; for they who were appointed to make inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, gave the criminals opportunity to eſcape, and by their illegal indulgence, left them at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to illude and laugh at the Law.</p>
            <p>Whileſt the Empreſs <hi>Euphemia</hi> lived, <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> by all the art he could uſe, could not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain permiſſion to marry <hi>Theodora;</hi> for the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs oppoſed his deſigns, though otherwiſe ſhe indulged him in every thing. That Princeſs had no evil inclinations, but being (as is ſaid before) of barbarous extraction, her manners were ſo ridiculous and dull, ſhe continued as incapable as at firſt, and never underſtood any thing of matters of State. Moreover, ſhe was not ſuffered (being Empreſs) to retain the name of <hi>Lupicina</hi> (which was infamous) but was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Euphemia;</hi> and not long after <hi>Juſtinian</hi> was recovered, ſhe died. The Emperor <hi>Juſtin</hi> was grown ſo old and ſuperannuated, he had loſt his judgment, and was expoſed to the contempt and deriſion of his ſubjects; ſo that all people paid obedience to <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> who by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauches,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60251:28"/>and the liberty he took to do what he pleaſed, made himſelf formidable to every body. Then it was he took a reſolution of marrying <hi>Theodora,</hi> and there being an old Law in force, prohibiting the Senators marrying with the Courtiſans, he prevailed with the Emperor to repeal that by a new one, and then he married <hi>Theodora,</hi> giving by his example, authority to any who deſired it, to marry with the firſt Courtiſan they fancied.</p>
            <p>The next thing he affected, was to be arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and tyrannical, diſguiſing his own vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies with the pretence of promoting the affairs of the Emperor, who, at that time, was not capable of them himſelf. He cauſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be ſaluted Emperor of the <hi>Romans,</hi> in conjunction with his Uncle; but whether juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or not, is a queſtion; for he conſtrained the Senate and the People by his menaces to give their conſent. <hi>Juſtinian</hi> and <hi>Theodora</hi> began to govern two days before <hi>Eaſter.</hi> In which, it is not allowed to ſalute any body, or pay any other ceremonious reſpect. Not many days after, <hi>Juſtin</hi> died, having Reigned nine years com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, and left the Empire to <hi>Juſtinian</hi> and <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dora,</hi> whoſe extraction being as I have ſaid, and her education and conduct, being as I have deſcribed, ſhe arrived at the Empire without difficulty, after <hi>Juſtinian</hi> had condeſcended to marry her, when it was in his power to have choſen for himſelf out of the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritory, a perſon of the higheſt quality, the beſt education, eminent for modeſty, illuſtrious for
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60251:28"/>beauty, an immaculate Virgin, and in brief, one that had been accompliſhed in the higheſt perfection. Nevertheleſs, he choſe rather to take upon himſelf the common infamy of all Men, as not being aſhamed, nor making any ſcruple to admit to his Bed a Woman, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides other crimes, was guilty of the death of ſo many Children by her artificial Miſcarriages and Abortions. I ſuppoſe there wants nothing in my deſcription of <hi>Juſtinian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This marriage is ſufficient to diſcover his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. In effect, He who after the Commiſſion of ſo many ill actions, apprehends not the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, and is not concerned at what people ſay, nor at the contempt they have of him, does queſtionleſs believe there is no crime, but he may boldly commit, and undertakes the moſt deteſtable things with great impudence and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacity. There was not one of the Senators who oppoſed his deſignes, though they ſaw his marriage would inevitably be the ruine of the Empire: On the contrary, they diſpoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to give <hi>Theodora</hi> the reſpect of a Diety. There was not one of the Prelates which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed any regret for being obliged to call her their Soveraign: And thoſe who not many years before, had ſeen her upon the ſtage, addreſſed themſelves to her as her ſlaves, and held up their hands to her in token of their humility, when they came with any Petition: The Army made no difficulty to expoſe it ſelf for <hi>Theodora</hi> to all the perils, and incommodities of War. In ſhort, there was no man in the whole Empire,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:60251:29"/>that ſhowed any repugnancy, and the whole World contributed to the accompliſhment of a thing, which Heaven had long ſince decreed. I am of opinion, Fortune had a minde to make experiment of her power, and convince man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde of it, by governing the affairs of the Earth in that manner, that they might obſerve there is no neceſſity of any cooperation of Man to the effecting of any thing, or that humane affairs are to be conducted by humane prudence, when her unjuſt power ſhould advance to the top of all earthly honors, a perſon which was involved in inſuperable difficulties; and (to ſpeak in a word) to ſhow that nothing was able to withſtand her power. She pleaſes herſelf ſometimes to create obſtacles, which afterwards ſhe ſurmounts in a moment, and paſſes where ſhe pleaſes; and at the ſame time, whileſt ſhe places ſome upon the top of her Wheel, others are at the bottom, and thrown down by her partiality and violence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theodora</hi> had an excellent face, and though her perſon was ſmall, yet ſhe was exceedingly well ſhaped; her complexion was neither too white, nor too red; her eyes were extream quick, and ſhe caſt them a thouſand ways at once.</p>
            <p>To give a particular Narrative of all that hapned when ſhe was upon the Stage, we ſhould want time; but I conceive, what I have ſaid in few words of ſome of her actions, is ſufficient to give any one a notion of her manners and inclinations; I ſhall now repreſent what ſhe did
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60251:29"/>with her Husband, after they had made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Maſters of the Empire (for they did nothing without participation of one another, though they had ſtudiouſly pretended that they did not agree: But at length their hypocriſie was diſcovered, and it appeared, their animoſity was but deſign to keep their Subjects in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whileſt they remained uncertain with which of the two to joyn, or to what ſide they were to repair.</p>
            <p>The firſt effect of this counterfeit difference was to diſtract the Chriſtians, after which they made diviſion among the heads of the popular Factions. <hi>Theodora</hi> pretended great zeal for the Faction of the <hi>Venetes,</hi> permitting them to enterpriſe any thing againſt the contrary party, and themſelves to act what enormities they pleaſed. <hi>Juſtinian</hi> ſeemed in appearance to be angry, and to complain publickly, That his Wife ſuperceded his orders, and that he could not retain her in her duty; and ſometimes both of them aſſerted their authority together, <hi>Juſtinian</hi> ordered the puniſhment of the <hi>Venetes</hi> in crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal caſes; <hi>Theodora</hi> protected them, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt the Emperor the breach of his promiſe. In the mean time, the <hi>Venetes</hi> were the more moderate of the two, becauſe they did not abuſe the liberty which was given them, to that degree they might have done. In many of their Suits and Contentions, <hi>Juſtinian</hi> was on one ſide, and <hi>Theodora</hi> on the other, and it was a rule betwixt them, the weakeſt ſide carried it, and the ſum in diſpute went moſt into their
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60251:30"/>Pockets. <hi>Juſtinian</hi> received many perſons into the number of his friends, ſuffered them to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act upon the people, and commit many extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the detriment of the State; but when they had peeled what they could, and heaped up any conſiderable treaſure, as ſoon as <hi>Theodora</hi> gave the ſign, they immediately declined in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor. At firſt <hi>Juſtinian</hi> would promiſe to protect them, and to encourage them not to fear, for he would ſtick by them; but by degrees his kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs began to abate, and at length he referred them to thoſe who had none for them at all; for then it was <hi>Theodora</hi> began to play her pranks, and exerciſe her cruelty towards them; and the Emperor, as if he had known nothing that was againſt them, took their eſtates into his poſſeſſion, and kept them moſt injuriouſly when he had done.</p>
            <p>By this pretended diſcord (which was only a copy of their countenance, and done only to amuſe the World) having divided the hearts of their Subjects, they eſtabliſhed themſelves more ſtrongly in their power and tyranny. When <hi>Juſtinian</hi> was arrived at the Empire, he began to ſubvert, and perfectly to confound the affairs of the Empire, introducing things forbidden by the antient Laws, and forbidding thoſe which the Laws had formerly injoyned; as if he had aſſumed the Imperial Mantle, and put the Diadem upon his Head for no other end, but to change the face of the Government. In ſhort, he aboliſhed all the Laws, all the Cuſtoms of the Magiſtrate, and all the Military Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60251:30"/>bringing in others in their places, not that they were better for the publick, or of any neceſſity themſelves, but only out of a deſire to innovate, or that by giving them his name, at leaſt they might appear new. He could never ſatisfie his inſatiable deſire, either of Money or Blood: But when he had deſpoild one of what ever could be got, he removed to another, and treated him at the ſame rate; and when he had done all, ruined his good Subjects, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honored himſelf: How was all this immenſe treaſure employed? either in ridiculous preſents to the <hi>Barbarians;</hi> or in impertinent and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary building: Though he had ſoiled and polluted himſelf before, with the murders of ſeveral innocent perſons, he laid new deſigns againſt more, with intention to deſtroy them; and ſeeing the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire was in good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence with all Nations, by an unexampled fury he ſet the <hi>Barbarians</hi> together by the ears, and ingaged them in an expenſive, and pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous War; and having ſent for the principal of the <hi>Huns</hi> (without the leaſt occaſion in the World, he gave them vaſt ſums of Money out of his ſottiſh liberality, to gain (as he pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) their amity, and confirm it, as had been formerly done in the Reign of <hi>Juſtin.</hi> The <hi>Huns</hi> having got what they could, began to ſolicite the Heads of the other barbarous Nations, to fall upon the Empire, that they might ſell Peace likewiſe to him that was ſo ready to buy it. They needed not much perſwaſion, but taking the hint, they pillaged ſeveral Towns belonging
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60251:31"/>to the Empire; and yet all this while continued to take the Emperors pay. They were no ſooner gone, but others ſucceeded, who having plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered his Dominions, and carried away a moſt conſiderable booty, were rewarded by <hi>Juſtinian</hi> for their pains, who was grown the moſt liberal in that nature of any Prince in the World. In ſhort, from that very time, the <hi>Barbarians</hi> never gave over ravaging his Countrey, one party per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually following at the heels of another: For thoſe people having many Princes among them, being numerous themſelves, and of different in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts; this War (which derived its original from the extravagant Liberality of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror) begun with one, was continued with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and ſo perpetually carried on, that there was not a Mountain ſo little, a place ſo incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, nor a Cave ſo obſcure in the whole extent of the <hi>Roman</hi> Dominion, as to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from the pillagings of theſe <hi>Barbarians:</hi> Some Provinces were ſo unfortunate as to be plundered five times over. I have ſpoken of all theſe things before in my other works, as alſo of the inroads the <hi>Perſians,</hi> the <hi>Saracens,</hi> the <hi>Sclavonians,</hi> and other of the <hi>Barbarious</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions made upon the Empire. But as I ſaid at firſt, I ſhall make it appear to be cauſed only by the ill conduct of the Emperor: He gave a vaſt ſum of Money to clap up a Peace with <hi>Coſroes;</hi> and when he had done, by a ſtupid piece of obſtinacy he brake it again, having uſed all his art to draw to his Party <hi>Alaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dare,</hi> and the <hi>Huns,</hi> who were in alliance with
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60251:31"/>the <hi>Perſians,</hi> which I ſuppoſe I have deſcribed elſwhere well enough.</p>
            <p>About the ſame time when he had kindled this War, and given occaſion to ſuch Seditions as would be the ruine of the Empire, and all to inrich himſelf, and fill his own Coffers, by filling his Dominions with ſlaughter and Blood, to compleat their deſtruction, he made uſe of this following invention.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire there are ſeveral Sects of Chriſtians (differing from the truth) which are called Hereticks, particularly the <hi>Montaniſts, Sabbatians,</hi> and others, all of them Hetrodox. <hi>Juſtinian</hi> commanded, That all of them ſhould change their Belief; and to that, he compelled them, partly by threats, and partly by making their Children incapable of inheriting from their Fathers. In the Temple of theſe Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks (and eſpecially in the Temples of the <hi>Arians</hi>) the riches was incredibly great, for there is no compariſon betwixt the wealth of the Senate, or any other famous Body in the whole Empire, and that which belongs to them. There was ſcarce one of the conſecrated Veſſels, but were either of Gold or of Silver, adorned with great numbers of Precious Stones: The Prieſts, and inferior Miniſters, had their Houſes and Lands, and Revenues in all parts. In ſhort, they wanted nothing that might be had, being people to whom the former Emperors had been always indulgent; they maintained ſeveral of the true Religion as their Servants, imployed them as they were Artiſts.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:60251:32"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Juſtinian</hi> ſeiſed upon the riches of all theſe Temples, and poſſeſt himſelf thereof, to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ruine of many of them. He had likewiſe his Agents abroad, who went from one place to another, and obliged all they found to change their Religion; at which, the Countrey people being offended, as at an act of impiety, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed themſelves againſt thoſe Agents, but they had their revenge, and cauſed many of them to be ſlain. Some there were of them, who out of a deplorable ſuperſtition made away them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, while the reſt, in great throngs, fled out of the Countrey. The <hi>Montaniſts</hi> in <hi>Phygia,</hi> betook themſelves to their Churches, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting fire to them, burnt themſelves, their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and all that they had; ſo that from that time, nothing was to be ſeen in the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, but maſſacres and deſolations, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple quitting their Houſes. The Edicts of the Emperor put the <hi>Samaritans</hi> of <hi>Paleſtin</hi> into no leſs diſorder; whereupon thoſe where I was in <hi>Ceſaria,</hi> and in other Towns, thinking it weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and indiſcretion, to expoſe themſelves for ſo dangerous an opinion, quitted their Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and were called <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> by which means they avoided their deſtruction, which otherwiſe would have been infallible; whileſt others, whoſe Conſcience was better informed, continued ſtedfaſt in their Faith: But a good party of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> (diſſatisfied that they had been forced from the Religion of their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers) a while after became <hi>Manicheans</hi> and <hi>Politheiſts.</hi> In the mean time, the <hi>Peaſants</hi> took
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60251:32"/>Arms againſt the Emperor, and having made choice of <hi>Julian,</hi> the Son of <hi>Sabarus,</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them, they gave Battle to <hi>Juſtinians</hi> Army; for ſome time the Victory was doubtful, and a good while they fought before it could be known on which ſide it would incline, but at length the <hi>Peaſants</hi> were defeated, and moſt part of them ſlain, and their General <hi>Julian</hi> among the reſt; by report there were near 100000 Men killed upon the place. The greateſt of the loſs fell among the <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> for though they had no Men left to Cullivate their Lands, which were the fruitfulleſt of the World, yet they were forced to pay annual Taxes and Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Emperor, to a great value, which were extorted from them by all manner of cruelty.</p>
            <p>After this, he turned his deſigns againſt the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> killed ſeveral of them, and diſpoſſeſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the reſt of their eſtates: Some of them there were, who pretended to embrace the Chriſtian Religion, to avoid their torments, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their eſtates; but they were afterwards ſurpriſed in the exerciſe of their Idolatry, and in the impiety of their Sacrifices. I ſhall now ſay what he did againſt the Chriſtians. After this by particular Proclamation, he prohibited the infamous and unnatural uſe of Boys, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to be apprehended not only them who had been guilty ſince the publication of the ſaid Law, but thoſe who had been ſuſpected of it of old, and puniſhed them ſeverely without any Form of Juſtice, or Legal Proceſs: He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:60251:33"/>them upon the teſtimony of one Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who for the moſt part was ſome Child, or ſome Servant which had been ſuborned againſt their Maſter; and when he had got one of thoſe, he deſired no farther evidence. Thoſt who were convict of this crime, were expoſed to all the mockery in the World, having their Privities cut off in a moſt cruel and ignominious manner. At firſt they acted not with the ſame extremity againſt them all, the heat of their fury extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it ſelf more particularly againſt thoſe who were of the faction of the <hi>Praſinians,</hi> extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily rich, or in the diſpleaſure of the Emperor. He could not endure Aſtrologers, but appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Magiſtrates (deputed for the puniſhment of Felons) to ride up and down upon their Camels thorow the City of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and cauſe them to be beaten upon their ſhoulders with Rods, and expoſing them publickly as a ſpectacle of contempt, though they were antient; and in other things, very honeſt men, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached with nothing, but that having ſuch knowledge in the Stars, they ſhould remain in that Town.</p>
            <p>The Tyranny of theſe Actions, cauſed great numbers of all ſort of people to forſake their own Countreys, and betake themſelves, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the Countreys of the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> but into ſuch Nations as were at greateſt diſtance from the Dominion of <hi>Rome.</hi> In every Province, and in every Town, great numbers were to be ſeen from ſeveral Countreys, which had been harraſed by their Friends, with as much cruelty,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:60251:33"/>as if they had been their moſt implacable Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. And this courſe did <hi>Juſtinian</hi> and <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dora</hi> take to diſpoil of their goods and eſtates, the greateſt Perſons in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and all the reſt of the Cities; and for the Senators, they were treated as I ſhall tell.</p>
            <p>There was one of them called <hi>Zeno,</hi> Senator at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and Grandchild to <hi>Anthemius</hi> (who had formerly had that Empire,) this <hi>Zeno</hi> they choſe on purpoſe to make him Governor of <hi>Egypt.</hi> This Governor, without the leaſt jealouſie in the World, cauſed the richeſt of his Goods to be put on Board that Veſſel which was intended for his own tranſportation, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred his departure for ſome days, to put a Board a prodigious quantity of Silver, Jewels, Plate inriched with Emeralds, and other preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Stones of a very conſiderable value. The Emperor having notice of all, corrupted ſome of <hi>Zeno</hi>'s principal Servants, and by their means having cauſed all this vaſt wealth to be convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed privately out of the Ship, he made them ſet it on ſire in the Hold, and pretend to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter that it hapned by accident, and had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed all his great treaſure which he intended for <hi>Egypt:</hi> Not long after <hi>Zeno</hi> died, and the Emperor ſeiſed upon the remainder of his eſtate, producing a fraudulent Will which all the World knew to be forged. By the ſame arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice he got poſſeſſion of the eſtates of <hi>Tatian,</hi> and <hi>Demaſthenes,</hi> and <hi>Hilaras,</hi> the three princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Men in the Senat. There were many others likewiſe, whoſe Heirs he made himſelf, not by
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60251:34"/>any real Will, but by counterfeit conveyances: As for example, he made himſelf Heir to <hi>Denis</hi> (whoſe eſtate was near <hi>Liban,</hi>) and of <hi>John,</hi> the Son of <hi>Baſil,</hi> the Governor of <hi>Edeſſa,</hi> whom <hi>Belliſarius</hi> delivered againſt his will in hoſtage to the <hi>Perſians,</hi> as I have mentioned in my other Books. After he had been ſome time with the <hi>Perſians, Coſroes</hi> would not diſcharge him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ranſome, pretending <hi>Belliſarius</hi> had not performed according to the Articles, upon which, the ſaid <hi>John</hi> was given in pledge: Whereupon his Grandfather being then living, he treated for his redemption, and had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared Two thouſand livres of Silver, in order thereunto. The Emperor having advertiſement, and that the Money was conveyed, and lay ready at <hi>Dara,</hi> would not ſuffer it to be paid, but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, That it was not to be permitted that the <hi>Barbarians</hi> ſhould go away with ſo much Money of the <hi>Romans.;</hi> and whileſt that was in controverſie, <hi>John</hi> died of a diſeaſe of which he had been languiſhing a long time. When he was dead, the Governor of <hi>Dara</hi> (a Creature of the Emperors) counterfeited a writing from the ſaid <hi>John,</hi> by which the Emperor was made Heir to all his eſtate, and aſſured the World it was his laſt Will and Teſtament: But beſides theſe falſe Wills, and counterfeit Conveyances, it is ſcarce credible, how many people gave him their eſtates freely and <hi>bona fide.</hi> Before the Sedition broke out, by degrees he took away their whole eſtate from the Family of <hi>Victoria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> which was reported very rich: But when
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60251:34"/>thoſe troubles began, he cauſed moſt of the Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors Goods to be ſold, and of all deſcending from <hi>Patrician</hi> Families, he took the greateſt part, and appropriated it. to himſelf, leaving (as a falſe image of this clemency) the Tenths only to ſuch as were in poſſeſſion, and that only to continue them liable to his Taxes: For which, thoſe poor people were uſed with great cruelty by his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Collectors, and much dejected at the ſadneſs of their life, which was ſo unquiet to them, they would have choſe to have been put to death, which would have delivered them from a thouſand calamities.</p>
            <p>Hence it is, that theſe unmerciful Princes do not fall into my thoughts (or any bodies elſe of my opinion) as Men, but as evil Spirits, and pernicious Plagues, acting by common conſent towards the deſtruction of all people, and dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving on with uncontroulable fury, to ruine the whole World. In ſhort, though of late ages, ſeveral perſons have made themſelves terrible, and were naturally of that humor, or brought to it by the conſequence of affairs; as by the deſolation of ſome Countrey, the deſtroying of ſome Town, or the depopulating ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, yet there was never any went ſo near the ſubverting, not only the Government of the Empire, but the whole oeconomy of the World, and the ſpecies of mankind, as <hi>Juſtinian</hi> and <hi>Theodora.</hi> It is true, <hi>Fortune</hi> contributed to their deſigns, and added much to the miſeries which were endured: For at the ſame time there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſo many ill accidents as Earthquakes, Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60251:35"/>and Inundation of Rivers, that it was not unlikely, but what was done by the Emperor and Empreſs, proceeded as well as the reſt, from ſome ſupernatural agent. Moreover it was reported that <hi>Juſtinians</hi> Mother ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten declare to the principal of her Kinred and Friends, That the ſaid <hi>Juſtinian</hi> was not the Son of her Husband <hi>Sabbatius,</hi> nor of any other Man; but that before ſhe was with child, ſhe was viſited by a Spirit, preſent to her touch, but not ſight; which Spirit had coition with her, performed the office of her Husband, and vaniſhed like a dream. Some of <hi>Juſtinians</hi> Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber, whoſe courage and confidence were greater then the reſt, affirmed, That as they lay in his Chamber, about midnight, inſtead of him, they ſaw a moſt deformed ſpirit in his place. There was one among them, who maintained, That he ſaw <hi>Juſtinian</hi> riſe out of his Bed (where he never lay long) and walk about the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; and that in a ſhort time, his head diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, and yet the Trunk walked on; and that whileſt he was in an amaze, and ready to have diſtruſted his own eyes, of which, he began to be jealous, he ſaw the head return, and joyn it ſelf to the body. Another declared, That as he was in the preſence of <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> he ſaw the head of that Prince change on a ſudden into a maſs, and confuſed lump of fleſh, where he could not diſtinguiſh eyes, or noſe, or any other marks of a face: This I write not of my own knowledge, but I had it from perſons who aſſured me it was true, and they had ſeen it
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60251:35"/>with their own eyes. It was reported, That there was a Fryer of a moſt exemplary life, and of great eminence for it, who at the ſolicitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Brethren in the ſame Monaſtery, came to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> with deſign of ſpeaking to the Emperor for the eaſe of the Neighborhood, which was undone by his tyranny and oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. That when he arrived, he entred into the Palace, and the Emperors Apartment, with as much eaſe as he could deſire; but as ſoon as he came near his perſon, he ſtarted from him, and returned to his Monaſtery in great haſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, without being able to anſwer the Uſhers and other Officers who preſſed him to ſtay, and demanded what it was he feared. But being queſtioned by the Monks, be told them, <hi>That he ſaw</hi> Lucifer <hi>ſitting upon the Throne of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and that he had not power to accoſt, or ſay any thing to him.</hi> And indeed, who would not have taken for an evil ſpirit, or at leaſt for a fury, a Man, who though he loved more Women then any Man living, and that to the very height of laſciviouſneſs and debauchery, yet he ſcarce eat, or drank, or ſlept at any time; but having taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſipped of what was brought to the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, he walked about the Palace all the night after.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>Theodora,</hi> thoſe who had lain with her when ſhe was a Comedian, declared, That whileſt they were in Bed with her in the night, there came ſpirits into the Room, and frighted them away. There was a young Wench which danced well, belonging to the <hi>Venetes</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:60251:36"/>and called the <hi>Macedonian,</hi> who having great power with <hi>Juſtin,</hi> ſhe writ to her, and made her an inſtrument in the death of many of the principal Officers in the Eaſt, and in the confiſcation of their Goods. This <hi>Macedonian</hi> hearing <hi>Theodora</hi> complaining at her return from <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Africk</hi> of the ill treatment ſhe had received from <hi>Hecebolus,</hi> and of a loſs ſhe had ſuſtained in her journey, of a conſiderable ſum of Money; telling her by way of conſolation, <hi>That</hi> Fortune, <hi>as ſhe had taken them away, might, when ſhe pleaſed, return them in greater plenty. Theodora</hi> replied, <hi>That ſhe was not troubled in the leaſt; for the night before ſhe had ſeen a viſion, which had bid her not concern her ſelf, and told her, That as ſoon as ſhe ſhould come to</hi> Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople, <hi>ſhe ſhould be admitted to the Emperors Bed; and that by aſſiſtance which ſhe ſhould receive, ſhe ſhould marry him, and be put into poſſeſſion of as much wealth as ſhe could deſire.</hi> And this was the common report upon that ſubject.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Juſtinian</hi> (though he was as I have deſcribed) was of ſo eaſie acceſs, and ſo civil in all his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, that no man was ever denied to ſpeak with him; nor did he ſeem ever provoked or diſcompoſed, when any perſon failed in their reſpects toward him, either by word or deed. The ruine and miſery which he was preparing for other people, never made any alteration in him. He never expreſſed any Paſſion, nor the leaſt reſentment againſt thoſe he had deſtined to deſtruction, but with a countenance peaceable and ſerene; and a voice without any commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:60251:36"/>he appointed the murders of an infinite multitude of innocent perſons; the ſacking of ſeveral Towns, and confiſcation of Eſtates. In a word, by his looks no man but would have taken him for the gentleſt, the moſt affable, and beſt natured Man in the World. But if any one come to implore his mercy, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>o expoſtulate in behalf of one that was oppreſſed, then it was he would be angry, his colour riſe, and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt his ſubjects appear. He favor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Prieſts, who tormented their Neighbors; he gave any man thanks, who poſſeſſed himſelf of his Neighbors eſtate, and believed he did an act that was highly meritorious. When any controverſie was brought before him, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved himſelf bound in Conſcience to decide it in favor of the Defendant, eſpecially, if he had invaded the others eſtate, under pretence, That it belonged to the Church; in that caſe he thought he could not he unjuſt, let him do what he would, provided the cauſe went for the Eccleſiaſticks: He himſelf gave to the Church, ſeveral Lands that he had uſurped from other people (whether the lawful Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors were living or dead) to cover his impiety under the mask of devotion, and procure that the right owners ſhould never be reſtored to them again; and many murders he committed, under the pretence of Piety and Religion. He endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vored likewiſe with great induſtry, That all people under his Dominion ſhould be uniform in Matters of Religion, in order to which, he put many a man to death, as not believing it
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60251:37"/>homicide, to kill any of a perſwaſion contrary to his own. In ſhort, he took ſo much delight in the deſtruction of his People, that he was perpetually at <hi>Theodora</hi> not to ſuffer any oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to eſcape her, but rather to ſet her Brains a work to invent new; for having the ſame Paſſions, their Actions were the ſame, their Conduct the ſame, and their Wickedneſs the ſame, though they pretended great difference betwixt themſelves; but it was only to ſet their ſubjects at difference.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Juſtinians</hi> humor was as uncertain as the Wind; it was to be turned which way one plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, only he was not to be turned from doing miſcheif, nor kept from ſhowing moſt infamous avarice. He was a great lover of flattery, and loved them highly, who perſwaded him he ſhould be taken up into the Heavens one day, and traverſe the Air, and the Celeſtial Spheres. <hi>Tribonian</hi> was with him upon a time, and told him, <hi>That he was in great fear leaſt he ſhould be rapt up ſuddenly into the Heavens, when he little thought of it, and all, for his ſingular Piety:</hi> And the poor Emperor was ſo weak, as to believe, That that flattery (or rather mockery) had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it that might be true.</p>
            <p>If he had had experience of any mans ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, he would be ſure to diſcommend him ever after, and to repre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent him a miſchievous and perfidious man; and yet he had no ſooner ſpoke ill of a man, but he praiſed him immediately, paſſing inconſiderately from one extream to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, becauſe the Characters which he gave,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60251:37"/>did not many times conſiſt with what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired other people ſhould believe. His impreſſions of hatred or love, I ſuppoſe, I have ſufficiently deſcribed in what I have ſaid of his actions. His anger he puſhed on to the higheſt extremity, and when once he was provoked, he was ever implacable. His friendſhip was as unconſtant, as his malice was obſtinate; he put ſeveral to death who were his Creatures, but was never reconciled where he had once taken a Pique. He delivered up into the hands of his Wife, or ſome third perſon, thoſe who were thought the greateſt in his favor, and to whom he had given the greateſt teſtimony of his kindneſs, to be ſacrificed, and murdered with torments, though they would never have deſerved death, but for their kindneſs to him. In effect, <hi>Juſtinian</hi> was conſtant in nothing but cruelty and covetouſneſs, and thoſe two good qualities were not to be removed.</p>
            <p>The Empreſs, when he ſcrupled what ſhe deſired, would wheedle him with hopes of large ſums of Money from the buſineſs which ſhe recommended. He made no difficulty to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Laws, and to break them if it were to his profit, not judging of affairs according to the Laws which he had eſtabliſhed, but according as the bribes were more or leſs, that he was to receive. When he plundered his ſubjects, and took away their Goods, though he knew he had no right; had ſuborned people to ſwear againſt them, or forged fraudulent Wills; he thought he did nothing amiſs.</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:60251:38"/>
            <p>During the Reign of this Prince, there was no eſtabliſhed Faith or Religion; no Contracts or Agreements of which, any Man could be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure. When he committed an affair to any of his Friends, he, who in the ſhorteſt time, ruined the perſons he was imployed to deſtroy, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned him the moſt ſpoil, he was the welcome man to him, as having acted moſt unto his deſigns, and private inſtructions: But thoſe who were tender, and unwilling to do any man miſcheif, thoſe he abhorred when they came back, and not enduring that old merciful way which ſavored too much of the old <hi>Roman,</hi> (which he uſed to call lazy and phlegmatick) he never preferred them to any imployment after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <p>In compliance with him, many perſons affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſeem bad, and leud in their conversation, though their temper and judgments were quite contrary to what they profeſſed. He pretended to forget what Contracts he had made, though they were ſealed and ſigned ſome of them with his own hand, and thought it very honorable. And this he did, not only with his own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, but with the Enemies of the Empire, as I have delivered at large in my other Books.</p>
            <p>He never could endure to be idle; he never eat or drunk as much as he could, but touched the meat, which they ſet before him, with the end of his fingers, and then bid them take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, for he had eaten enough: Beſides, the violence of his nature obliging him to be more fierce and inſatiable in his buſineſs, he did not
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:60251:38"/>eat ſome time in two days and two nights, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in <hi>Eaſter</hi> week, in which he faſted two whole days, without any thing but Water, and wilde Grapes; and without ſteeping above an hour, imploying the reſt of his time in perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual walking. There is no doubt, but if he had uſed his faculties to do good, the very parts wherewith Nature had endued him, would have raiſed the Empire to the higheſt degree of grandeur and felicity. But he perverted them quite, and imployed them wholly to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of his ſubjects, and the ruine of their eſtates, applying all his watchings, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, and labor, to augment the miſery and deſolation of his people, which was the more eaſie for him to compaſs, by how much his wit and invention was mighty quick in forging of crimes, and as prompt in puniſhing them when he had done: So that the good qualities, both in his body and mind, were of no uſe, but to make the people more miſerable. At his firſt advancement, he had nothing of the Majeſty of an Emperor; on the contrary, he framed himſelf more to the habit, diſcourſe, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the <hi>Barbarians.</hi> When he was to return an anſwer in writing, he did not commit it to the Queſtor, as formerly was the way; but he delivered it himſelf by word of mouth, though he ſpake his own language, as ill as a ſtranger. Afterward the people met in the Court of Juſtice with ſeveral impeachments, but no Judge was to be found to take cognizance of them. Secretaries of State were of the antient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:60251:39"/>Offices in the Empire, yet he ſpoiled them quite; for he writ all himſelf, even to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Sentences which the Magiſtrates were to give in the ſmaller Towns, leaving none of them at liberty to do any Man Juſtice thorow all his Dominions. He aſſumed all to himſelf out of a vain piece of arrogancy, and obſerved ſo good order in all determinations; that when he had heard one party, he gave his ſentence, and obliged them both to acquieſs, which he did, not out of any conviction or opinion that his Sentence was juſt, but for ſome advantage to himſelf, which was generally known; for his covetouſneſs had for a long time taken away his ſhame, and left him eaſie to be corrupted by the preſents of any Man.</p>
            <p>It often hapned, that the Decrees of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and the Edicts of the Emperor, did inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fere and claſh; for the Senate had but the ſhadow of an Authority without the freedom of giving their advice, or obſerving the rules of honeſty and vertue; ſerving only to fill up their ſeats, leaſt the antient form of Government ſhould be totally deſtroyed; yet no body durſt murmur in the leaſt.</p>
            <p>But though their Power was inſignificant, the Emperor and <hi>Theodora</hi> examined all things themſelves, ſo that every thing paſſing by their order; if any Man ſuſpected his Cauſe, he had no more to do, but to make a preſent to the Emperor, and he ſhould be ſure to have it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched, how contrary ſoever it was to the Laws and Statutes that were formerly eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:60251:39"/>Again, if any Man deſired the reviving of any Law which he had revoked, he reſtored it without any difficulty, as done in War, when one recovers what he loſt, by what means he can, be it in whoſe hands it will; ſo that in his Decrees there was nothing ſteady or juſt, all was full of error and uncertainty, and the Scales of Juſtice inclined not to that ſide where the right and propriety was, but where the preſents were greateſt; which were carried publickly into the Court where the controverſie was to be decided, to be paid by way of advance, ſome time to the Judge, and ſome time to the other Magiſtrates; yet it was not without trouble, that the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors ſound time to preſent the Petitions of their Clients to the Emperor, or give him the true ſtate of their affairs; for they were forced to make uſe of many falſe accuſations, and bribe him well into the bargain. Being eaſily over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reached, they applied to their ſeveral parties, and not acquainting them what had paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them and the Emperor, they drew from them vaſt ſums of Money, and no body durſt to oppoſe. The very Soldiers of the Guards which were to attend the Judges in the Court of the Palace, forced from them what judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they pleaſed; ſo that no body was kept to his duty, but every man followed the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe of his own fancy as his paſſion inſpired. All Officers had loſt their authority and places, and their very names were not ſuffered to be continued in their Regiſters. In a word, the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire was ordered as it had been go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60251:40"/>by a leud child: But I ſhall forbear ſpeaking of it any further, as I propoſed in the beginning of this Book.</p>
            <p>The firſt that adviſed the Emperor to this corruption in the Adminiſtration of Juſtice, was one <hi>Leo,</hi> a Native of <hi>Cilicia,</hi> a Man of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious avarice, and the greateſt flatterer in the World. He was excellent at inſinuation, and wrought himſelf ſtrangly into the favors of the ignorant, and eſpecially of <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> by whoſe imprudence, and the aſſiſtance of his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, he prevailed, and put him into a way of ruining his Subjects.</p>
            <p>This was the firſt who put that way into his mind, and when it was once tried, it was quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtabliſhed, and never after laid aſide, but increaſed to that point, That if any Man had a deſire to overcome in any Suit, he had no more to do but to find out <hi>Leo,</hi> give him half of his pretentions to be divided with the Emperor, and his buſineſs was done before he went out of the Palace. By theſe means <hi>Leo</hi> got toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a vaſt ſum of Money, beſides a large quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Lands, and all at the expence of the State, which he utterly deſtroyed. Contracts were not binding by any legal Obligation, by any Promiſe made, by any Writing given under Hand and Seal, by any penalty agreed upon, nor by any other ſecurity that could be given , but by Money, to be preſented to <hi>Leo,</hi> and the Emperor: And that way alſo, was not always certain, for <hi>Leo</hi> would take bribes on both ſides, and when he did ſo, he cheated one of them
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60251:40"/>(no matter which) without any remorſe or ſhame, believing it no diſhonor to him to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front, or injure any Man, ſo it turned to his profit; and as he was, ſuch was <hi>Juſtinian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theodora</hi> was ſo hardned in her inclinations to cruelty, that ſhe never offended by perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of other people; but what ſhe fancied her ſelf, ſhe purſued with all imaginable impetuoſity, and uſed all endeavors to bring it about. Never any body interceded for the pardon of any man that was condemned ſo well were they ſatisfied, that neither length of time, cruelty of the puniſhment, the humbleſt and moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Prayers, nor the fear of Gods judgments were ſufficient to molifie her heart, or abate one jot of her fury. It was never ſeen, that any one who had once offended her, was ever for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, no not after they were dead; for the child that ſurvived, inherited the diſpleaſure of the Empreſs, with the Lands of his Father; and when he died, left it afterwards to his Sons. She was eaſily inraged, and that rage (not being to be withſtood) was the loſs of many a man. She had not ſo much care of her body, as of her pleaſure; and through her wanton mind, practiſed it with a tired appetite, when it was unneceſſary. She roſe very early in the morning to go into her Bath, where having continued a good time, ſhe eat her breakfaſt, and went again to ſleep. At dinner and ſupper there was no ſort of meat but ſhe would have, and that in abundance. She ſlept much, and often; in the day time, ſhe ſlept till night, and in the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60251:41"/>night, till day: And in this irregularity, ſhe believed the little time which ſhe had, was ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to diſpatch all affairs which concerned the whole Government of the Empire. If the Emperor imployed any man, without <hi>Theodoraes</hi> advice, the poor man was ſure to die in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, when he was once out of office.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Juſtinian</hi> was very proper Man to expedite buſineſs, not only for his continual watchings (as I ſaid before) but for the temper of his mind, and his eaſineſs of acceſs, which was ſo great; he gave people liberty to come to him, which he did not know, and that, not only to ſpeak, to him, but to converſe with him in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate. With the Empreſs it was quite contrary, For to her the greateſt Lords could not be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, but with much attendance, and a great deal of trouble: When at length ſhe vouchſafed to come to them, ſhe came to them into a little cloſe Chamber, where they were crammed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like ſo many Footmen, which ſhe did to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert or prevent any evil deſigns. They received her all ſtanding, and holding up their heads, with their faces uncovered, to be ſurveyed by the Eunuchs, who were going and coming all the while. Some indeed ſhe admitted into her Chamber, but it was very rarely, and after they had waited ſufficiently: When they did come in, they preſently withdrew (by way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect) having firſt kiſſed her feet; but they durſt not deliver any Petition, nor begin any Diſcourſe, till ſhe vouchſafed to command them. The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate went together moſt ignominiouſly and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60251:41"/>ſlaviſhly to kiſs her feet; and the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire loſt much of its magnanimity and ſplendor, partly by the eaſineſs of <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> and partly by the inſolence of <hi>Theodora,</hi> who thruſt her ſelf into all affairs, and obſtructed their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</p>
            <p>This difference there was betwixt their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, but in covetouſneſs and murder they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed well enough: Neither of them knew what it was to ſpeak truth, but on the contrary, both of them were great inventors of lies. If any one was in disfavor with <hi>Theodora,</hi> and had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any fault, how little ſoever, from that very time, ſhe would accuſe them of ſomething or other, which perhaps never came into their thoughts, and aggravating it ſo highly, That ſhe would charge others with confederacy, and never reſt till ſhe had delivered them up into the hands of Juſtice; and when the Judges met, they knew well enough that their ſentence muſt be accommodated to the cruelty of <hi>Theodora.</hi> Judgment being given and executed, and all the goods ſeiſed (let the party be as great as he will) ſhe cauſed him to be drubbed, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards either baniſhed him, or put him to death. On the other ſide, if any of her favorites tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed, and were guilty of aſſaſſination, or any Other crime (either in raillery, or by way of threat) ſhe took off the Informers, and ſtaid the proceſs. She had a way of turning things of greateſt importance into ridicule, mocking and drolling upon them, as if they were in a Play; and ſhe acting them as formerly upon the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60251:42"/>Stage. There was a perſon of quality, (who had been along time (and was grown old) in ſeveral charges and imployments) but his name I ſhall forbear, as being unwilling to do him that diſgrace, as to leave it to poſterity upon Record, for ſo diſhonorable an action. This Gentleman, I ſay, not being able to recover a good round ſum of Money, which he had lent to a friend Of the Empreſſes,: addreſſed himſelf to her for Juſtice, and that ſhe would be a means he might be reſtored to his right. <hi>Theodora</hi> to keep up the intereſt of her friend, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her Eunuchs to incompaſs the <hi>Patrician</hi> when he came; to obſerve what ſhe did, and ſecond her ſinging whenever ſhe ſhould begin. When the <hi>Patrician</hi> was introduced into her Chamber, he threw himfelf down at her feet (as the cuſtom was) and with tears in his eyes; began his Harangue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>The Condition of a Patrician is more then ordinarily miſerable, when reduced to want; for what would draw upon other people pitty and compaſſion, brings contempt upon a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, and makes his calamity the greater: When other people are in neceſſity, and acquaint their creditors therewith, their miſery makes them leſs miſerable; but when a Gentleman is in diſtreſs, and cannot pay his debts, he is aſhamed to own it; and if he can prevail with himſelf to do that, who will believe him? The World will never believe we are poor, and if they do believe it, farewel our dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and reputation. This Madam is my caſe, I ow Money, and I have Money owing me; for my
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:60251:42"/>own part, I would cheat no body, it would not be ſuitable to my quality; but my debtors are not of my mind, for not having had my birth nor education, they are not ſo careful of paying, but ſeek out all ways to defraud me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My moſt humble requeſt therefore is, That you would vouchſafe me your favor in ſo juſt a cauſe, and reſcue me from the misfortunes with which I am incumbred, and by no fault or provocation of my own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was his Speech to the Empreſs, who inſtead of anſwering, began to ſing, <hi>O Patrician, you have a very great rupture,</hi> and all her Eunuchs joyned with her in the Song. The Senator perſiſting in his Supplications, and adding new Reaſons to his former, <hi>Theodora</hi> replied in the ſame Dialect, and her Quire of Eunuchs ſtruck in with the <hi>Chorus,</hi> and made up the Conſort. At length the poor Gentleman, much afflicted at ſo cruel a piece of deriſion, made his reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Empreſs as was uſual, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired.</p>
            <p>A good part of the year, <hi>Theodora</hi> reſided in the Suburbs upon the Sea-ſhore, and moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly in that part called <hi>Herroteum,</hi> where her ſervants and attendants, which followed her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon endured great incommodity; not ſo much by the dearneſs of Proviſions, but by the dangers which they frequently incurred in paſſing the ſtreight, by the great Tides, ſudden Inundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or the ſurpriſes of Sea-monſters, which are frequent in that place: But they conſidered not theſe dangers, if they could but add any
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60251:43"/>thing to the divertiſement of their Miſtreſs, and enjoy the delights and pleaſures of her Court. I ſhall now conclude my Relation of her practiſes, to deſtroy ſuch as ſhe had any prejudice againſt, that I may not ſeem to have undertaken a work without end.</p>
            <p>After <hi>Amalaſontha</hi> had laid down, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the Government of the <hi>Gothiſh</hi> Affairs, and had (as I have ſaid in my other Books) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed an inclination to another kind of life, and to come, and live privately at <hi>Conſtantinople. Theodora</hi> conſidering the great extraction of that Princeſs, her quality as Queen , her ſingular Beauty, her excellent Wit, and above all, her admirable Wiſdom; ſhe did not queſtion, but ſuch extraordinary qualifications, would have ſome effect (to her diminution) upon the uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant nature of her Husband; but ſhe diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing of her apprehenſion, till ſhe had taken her meaſures aright.</p>
            <p>Being aſſured of one of her Creatures called <hi>Peter,</hi> ſhe perſwaded <hi>Juſtinian</hi> to ſend him Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador to <hi>Amalaſontha;</hi> the Emperor, when the ſaid Ambaſſador took his leave, in order to his paſſage into <hi>Italy,</hi> gave him ſuch Orders, as I have mentioned in my other Books; but the Empreſs (of whom, at that time, I durſt not ſpeak what I knew to be true) gave him particularly in charge, That above all things, he ſhould contrive, and procure the death of <hi>Amalaſontha,</hi> and promiſed him great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, if he compaſſed the buſineſs. The Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador, with all diligence purſued his voyage
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:60251:43"/>into <hi>Italy,</hi> incited by the great hopes he had of riches or preferment (for men are not naturally prone to miſcheif, without Foreign temptation) as ſoon as he was arrived, he obliged <hi>Theodat</hi> to kill <hi>Amalaſontha,</hi> but I do not know upon what pretence.</p>
            <p>After ſo great ſervice, <hi>Peter</hi> was advanced to very great Offices, and enjoyed them with great authority, but with the hatred and deteſtation of the whole World: And this trick <hi>Theodora</hi> plaid the poor <hi>Amalaſontha.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Juſtinian</hi> had a Secretary of his Cloſet, called <hi>Priſcus,</hi> a <hi>Paphlagonian</hi> born, and a Man very eminent and exact in all kinds of villany; by his conduct and humor, he was a likely Man to inſinuate with his Maſter; and he did it ſo effectually, he became the only favorite. The Emperor made no queſtion, but the friendſhip had been mutual, inſomuch, that in a ſhort time he got together unjuſtly an incredible eſtate. The Empreſs not being able to brook his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence and pride, to ruine him, began to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him to the Emperor, and charge him with crimes; but not ſucceeding in that, ſhe cauſed him to be ſurpriſed and ſent away ſuddenly in a ſhip, when he little thought of it; and having ordered him to be ſhaved, ſhe forced him to turn Prieſt: In the mean time, the Emperor carried himſelf as he had been privy to the plot, and did not ſo much as inquire into what part of the World poor <hi>Priſcus</hi> was gone, nay, I am perſwaded he never thought of him after, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it was, when he ſeiſed a ſum of Money of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60251:44"/>his, which he had left behind him. <hi>Theodora</hi> had a ſuſpition of one of her Servants called <hi>Areo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binde,</hi> who was a ſtranger, but from his very youth had given great marks of an excellent diſpoſition, and had been made Maſter of her Wardrobe. To puniſh a crime, of which ſhe imagined he was guilty, ſhe cauſed him to be beaten with Rods with extraordinary cruelty, though (as was reported) ſhe had a great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for him; but what became of him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, I cannot tell, nor I believe, any body elſe. For when <hi>Theodora</hi> deſigned to have any thing kept ſecret, to conceal it from the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and memory of man, ſhe ſo threatned and frightned the inſtruments in the action (which never any Tyrant had done before) that they never durſt mention it to the very neareſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their Relations: On the other ſide, there was nothing done by thoſe, for whom ſhe had a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, but ſhe knew it immediately; for thers<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was not a conſiderable Family, but ſhe had he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpies in it, who told her not only the diſcourſe but the very words which every man ſpoke; and when ſhe had a mind to puniſh any one, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no body know it, if he were a <hi>Patrician,</hi> ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſent for him privately, and dilivered him up to ſome ſingle perſon of her Confidents, whom ſhe had ſelected to be the inſtrument of her vengeance, with inſtruction to carry him to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> remoteſt part of the Empire. Having received her commands, the Officer bound the po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> man, muffled his face, and then putting his a Shipboard in a dark night, he conveyed his
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60251:44"/>according to directions, where he delivered him to another with Orders, to ſee him kept ſafe and cloſe, till the Empreſs ſhould think fit to commiſerate him; and there after he had led a miſerable life a long time, the continuation of his ſufferings, did many times put an end to them.</p>
            <p>There was a young Gentleman called <hi>Baſien,</hi> (of illuſtrious extraction, and of the <hi>Praſinian</hi> faction) who in his diſcourſe and raillery, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing been too bold with the Empreſs, knowing ſhe was incenſed, fled into the Church of Saint <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangel: But as ſoon as ſhe had notice, ſhe ſent the Pretor of the People, who ſeiſed upon him, not upon the ſcore of his ſawci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with the Empreſs, but as one that was guilty of Buggery. At the ſame time, in which he was raviſhed from the Church, the Officers put him to ſuch intolerable torments, that the People aſſembled in multitudes together, not being able to ſee under ſuch inſupportable tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, a perſon of his youth and quality, whoſe perſon had been brought up ſo delicately, and ſo unaccuſtomed to ſuch barbarous ſufferings, eſpecially when being ready to die, he cried out, and with grievious ſhrieks, implored their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion: But the unmerciful Woman perſiſted in her cruelty, and cauſed his puniſhment to be redoubled, till at laſt his privy parts being cut off, he died under their hands (though he was neither tried, nor condemned) and his eſtate was confiſcated to the Emperor: By degrees the fury of this <hi>Megera</hi> grew ſo great, that when
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60251:45"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:60251:45"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:60251:46"/>ſhe reſolved upon the deſtruction of any Man, neither the Sanctuary of the Church, the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the people, nor any other contrivance in the World, was ſufficient to preſerve him. She took a pique againſt another called <hi>Diogenes,</hi> born in <hi>Constantinople;</hi> and in no leſs favor with the Emperor, then with the reſt of mankind; being of the <hi>Praſinian</hi> party, ſhe determined his ruine, and having ſuborned two of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, ſhe cauſed them to accuſe him of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domy. But that being an affair which could not be clandeſtinely puniſhed, and he a perſon of dignity and imployment, ſeveral conſiderable men being deputed to the examination of the buſineſs, they rejected the teſtimony of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants as uncapable of giving evidence, both in reſpect of their condition, and the minority of their age. The Empreſs offended with their proceedings, cauſed one of <hi>Diogenes</hi> Confidents, called <hi>Theodorus,</hi> to be committed to one of her Dungeons, and would have perſwaded him to have depoſed againſt his friend; to which end, ſhe made uſe of flatteries, prayers, threats, and tortures but finding none of them ſucceeded, ſhe commanded his head to be bound hard about with a Cord, not doubting therewith but to have twiſted out his eyes, but the poor Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man choſe rather to endure whatever could be inflicted, then to tell a lie; which though it might have ſaved himſelf, muſt have ruined his friend. Hereupon the Judges acquitted him, as not finding any proof ſufficient to condemn him.</p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:60251:46"/>
            <p>This was the cruelty which ſhe exerciſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe people, for I have ſpoke before of the manner in which ſhe treated <hi>Belliſarius, Photius,</hi> and <hi>Buſez.</hi> There were two <hi>Cilicians</hi> of the faction of the <hi>Venetes,</hi> who in a mutiny attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the perſon of <hi>Callinicus,</hi> Governor of the ſecond <hi>Cilicia,</hi> and killed the Maſter of his Horſe (who endeavored to defend him) in his preſence, and before all the people; being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed of this, and ſeveral other murders, he cauſed them to be apprehended, and their heads cut off as they deſerved. Which piece of Juſtice coming to the ears of <hi>Theodora,</hi> to ſhow her paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the party of the <hi>Venetes,</hi> ſhe cauſed the Governor to be crucified in the ſame place where the Malefactors had been executed, though he was innocent, and had that office. The Emperor pretended to be much concerned, pitied his misfortune, and with tears in his eyes, complained heavily of <hi>Theodora,</hi> and gave out a thouſand threats againſt the inſtruments in that action; yet he made no ſcruple to ſeiſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his eſtate, and appropriate it to himſelf. <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dora</hi> likewiſe cauſed all the common Women to be puniſhed, baniſhing Five hundred of them at one time, for proſtituting themſelves at a certain place on the other ſide of the <hi>Boſphorus;</hi> and having clapped them into ſeveral Nunneries, ſhe conſtrained them to an honeſter courſe of life in ſpight of their teeths; but ſome of them threw themſelves down a Rock, and preferred a voluntary death, before a life ſo contrary to their inclinations.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:60251:47"/>
            <p>There were at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> two young Siſters, not only illuſtrious by the Conſulſhip of their Grandfather and Father, but by a long deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent of Nobility, as being of one of the cheif Families in the Senate. Theſe two young Ladies having loſt their Husbands betimes, devoted themſelves to perpetual Widowhood. <hi>Theodora</hi> abhorring their vertue and pious way of living, choſe out from among the dregs of the people, two the moſt execrable perſons that could be found, and deſigned them to be their Husbands. Having notice of the Empreſſes intention, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending ſhe would force them, they ſled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church of Saint <hi>Sophia,</hi> and entring into the holy Bath, they held faſt by the Fountain: But the Empreſs plagued them ſo many ways, and kept them in ſuch want of neceſſary things, that they were conſtrained to marry them, to deliver themſelves from their diſtreſs: And in this manner <hi>Theodora</hi> ſhewed her reverence to the Sanctuaries; and the two Gentlewomen who had been courted by ſeveral perſons of their own quality, were married to two fellows, poor, miſerable, infinitely below their condition, and in the preſence of their Mother, who was by, weeping and lamenting all the while. It is true, afterwards <hi>Theodora</hi> abhorring what ſhe had done, endeavored to make them amends by advancing their Husbands to the detriment of the publick: But all that would do no good; they were incapable of conſolation, ſeeing their Husbands act with ſuch inſuppportable cruelty againſt the Emperors ſubjects; for <hi>Theodora</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:60251:47"/>regarded not the dignity of the Magiſtrate, the intereſt of the State, nor any other conſideration in the World; ſo ſhe could but ſill her coffers, and ſatisfie her infatiable humor.</p>
            <p>When ſhe was a Comedian, <hi>Theodora</hi> was got with child by a perſon of her acquaintance, but perceived it not till it was late; after ſhe had tried all ways to make her ſelf miſcarry, and none of them ſucceded by reaſon ſhe was too far gone; ſhe troubled her ſelf no farther with theſe unprofitable remedies, but was fairly brought to Bed. But her gallant underſtanding ſhe was highly offended that her lying in had hindred her from getting of Money, knowing the temper of the Mother, and being in ſome fear for the life of the Child, he took it, named it <hi>John,</hi> and carried it with him into <hi>Arabia,</hi> whither of a long time he had reſolved to retire. When <hi>John</hi> was grown up, his Father fell ſick, and finding he ſhould die, he told his ſon who was his Mother, what was his fortune, and in few minutes departed. <hi>John</hi> having performed his laſt duty to his Father, not long after removed to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> diſcovered the buſineſs to ſome of the Officers of the Empreſs, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated them to introduce him to his Mother. The Officers not imagining, in the leaſt, ſhe could do any thing that was inhumane againſt him, repreſented to her that her ſon was in Town. The wicked Woman fearing it might come to the ears of the Emperor, cauſed him to be brought to her, and having received him very kindly before thoſe who preſented him,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60251:48"/>without any heſitation, ſhe delivered him into the hands of one of her executioners; but what became of the poor Creature, no body could tell, for he was never ſeen ſince, no not when his Mother was dead.</p>
            <p>Under the Reign of this cruel Princeſs, there was ſcarce a Woman which did not lie under ſome ſcandal, and indeed moſt of them were as bad as they were reported, having all poſſible liberty to tranſgreſs againſt their Husbands, and come off always unpuniſhed as oft as they were proſecuted for adultery: Their way was to apply to the Empreſs, who would be ſure to take care their ſentence ſhould be quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to what it ought, the Women ſent home acquitted of their crimes, their Husbands taken into cuſtody for falſe accuſations, which they were unable to prove, and condemned to pay ſometimes twice as much as ever they had with them; and where that was not to be had, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral puniſhment was inflicted, and they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued not only in priſon, but in irons, as long as they lived; which to conſummate their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, they were permitted to ſee their unchaſt Wives, in the embraces of their rivals, who as a reward for their crimes, received offices and preferments from the Empreſs. Hereupon many who feared that kind of uſage, and had no fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for her ſtripes, and her tortures, connived at the incontinence of their Wives; and that they might not be publickly ſurpriſed, they gave them all opportunity they could deſire.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:60251:48"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Theodora</hi> was grown to that authority in the Empire, that alone ſhe created all the Prelates, and Magiſtrates, and having abſolute power in her hands, ſhe managed it ſo well, there was not in all the Offices of the Empire, one good Man, whoſe Conſcience would not ſuffer him to obey her in her pernitious deſigns. She or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered it ſo, that all marriages were of her making; not a Man had the choice of his own Wife, but every one married, not (as the very <hi>Barbarians</hi> do) her he liked beſt, but her the Empreſs was pleaſed to command. Many times on the wedding night, ſhe would go her ſelf in perſon, tear out the Bride out of Bed, and turn away the poor Bridegroom, and meerly upon pretence it was done without her knowledge. This was her practice with ſeveral people, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly with <hi>Leontius</hi> the Referendary, and <hi>Saturnin</hi> who had married the Widow of <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogenes,</hi> who died not long after ſhe was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saturnin</hi> had a young Neice, free, of an honorable Family, and at age for a Husband, and this Lady, <hi>Cirillus</hi> her Father gave <hi>Saturnin</hi> in marriage after the death of <hi>Hermogenes</hi> his Widow. The wedding cloaths were bought, and all things prepared, when on a ſudden <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dora</hi> cauſed <hi>Saturnin</hi> to be ſeiſed and clapped into irons, and afterwards in ſpight of his tears, his complaints, and interceſſions, ſhe forced him to many <hi>Chriſomale,</hi> a Dancer, and one of the commoneſt Courtiſans in Town; for <hi>Theodora</hi> had no greater favorites then <hi>Chriſomale</hi> and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60251:49"/>
               <hi>Indare,</hi> who having been formerly her Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions upon the Stage, ſhe had made them her Colleagues, and cheif Miniſters in Matters of State.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saturnin</hi> having lain the firſt night with his new Wife, and found her otherwiſe then he expected, diſcovered to one of his Confidents, that he had married a perſon who was no Maid; his complaint being brought to the Empreſs, ſhe cauſed him to be ſecured by his own ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, whipped like a School Boy, upbraiding him all the time with his ſawcineſs with his Wife, called him perjured Raſcal, and having ſeen his backſide well torn with the Whip; ſhe adviſed him to keep his Tongue in his Mouth, and not talk with that liberty for the future.</p>
            <p>In my other Books, I have already declared the puniſhment which ſhe inflicted upon <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> revenging upon him the injuries he had done privately to her, and not any thing that he had acted publickly againſt the State; for ſhe paſſed by a thouſand greater Delinquents then he, and never medled with them at all.</p>
            <p>This <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Cappadocia</hi> was a great oppoſer of <hi>Theodoraes</hi> deſigns, and had often accuſed her of great crimes to the Emperor; ſo that once he was in ſome hopes of making a difference betwixt them. (This is the truth of the ſtory, and what I propoſed principally to communicate in this Book.) In ſhort, after ſhe had ſufficiently plagued the ſaid <hi>John,</hi> ſhe baniſhed him into <hi>Egypt,</hi> but that being too little, ſhe perſecuted him ſtill, and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:60251:49"/>watched him narrowly to find out new matter againſt him: Four years after, having appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended two of the <hi>Praſinian</hi> party who were in the Sedition at <hi>Cyzique,</hi> and accuſed of being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the aſſault upon the Biſhop, ſhe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, to corrupt them, the cruelty of her mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the greatneſs of her promiſes; and one of them frighted by her threats, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigled by her promiſes, impeached <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Cappadocia</hi> for murder, as ſhe deſired. The other could not be brought to give any ſuch evidence, though they tortured him ſo cruelly, he was thought to have been dead; by means of the conſtancy of that Man, ſhe had but one witneſs, and could not compaſs her ends. However, ſhe cauſed both their right hands to be chopped off, one becauſe he would not ſwear falſly againſt his Maſter; and the other, to terrifie him leaſt he ſhould diſcover her deteſtable intrigues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vainly deſirous, as it ſhould ſeem, to conceal thoſe practices which ſhe acted at the very Bar, in the ſight of all the World.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Juſtinian</hi> paſſed for a Fury in the ſhape of a Man, it was not without reaſon, conſidering the miſcheifs which he brought upon all people: For the actions of a Man diſcover his Nature and Power, it would be more caſie to number the Sands upon the Seaſhore, then the people which <hi>Juſtinian</hi> mined. For my own part, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well conſidered the Countreys that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed and depopulated, I do aſſure my ſelf they were more then two millions of Men, which periſhed by his cruelty and oppreſſion.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:60251:50"/>In effect, he diſpeopled the whole Tract of <hi>Africa</hi> in ſuch ſort, That in ſeveral days journey thorow that Countrey, it was a wonder to meet one ſingle man, and yet there were in his days 160000 <hi>Vandals</hi> bearing Arms, beſides Women, Children, and Servants. Beſides which, who can number the ancient inhabitants of that Countrey which remained in the Towns, manured the Fields, and exerciſed Trades and Marchandiſe, of which, I my ſelf have many times ſeen an incredible quantity. The Natives in <hi>Mauritania</hi> were more numerous then they, and they were all extirpated with their Wives and Children. The greateſt part of the <hi>Roman</hi> Army periſhed there likewiſe, and with them all the Auxilliary Troops of their Allies; ſo that I am of opinion, it may be affirmed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out extravagance, That in that Countrey alone, he was the deſtruction of above a million; and all, becauſe after he had defeated the <hi>Vandals,</hi> he took no care to eſtabliſh his Empire in thoſe parts, and fortifie his party by indulging the Natives, but called away <hi>Belliſarius</hi> upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, that he deſigned to make himſelf King; a thing he never thought of, nor was it any way convenient for him. But what ever he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, the true cauſe was, that he might have opportunity to pillage more freely, and ruine without obſtruction, the whole Coaſt of <hi>Africa:</hi> And to ſpeak truth, the Officers which he ſent, acquitted themſelves very faithfully of their Commiſſion from him; for under the new names of Impoſts, and Duties, they ſeiſed upon
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:60251:50"/>the beſt and richeſt part of the Countrey. This Emperor, who could not contain himſelf in one and the ſame ſtate, and ſeemed to be born to put all things in confuſion, forbid the <hi>Arians</hi> the exerciſe of their Religion, and deferred always to ſend ſupplies to his Army; till at length they began to mutiny, and ſo many Seditions were ready to break out, as would certainly have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered the peace and tranquility of the whole Government.</p>
            <p>He diſpeopled <hi>Italy</hi> of its Inhabitants, much more then he had done the Coaſt of <hi>Africa,</hi> which was three times of greater extent; from whence a probable computation may be made of the numbers which he occaſionally ruined; for I have elſwhere ſpoke of the original of his Wars in <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame exactions that he uſed in <hi>Africk,</hi> he uſed likewiſe in <hi>Italy,</hi> having ravaged all by the means of certain receivers which he called <hi>Logothetes:</hi> Before the Wars in <hi>Italy,</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of the <hi>Goths</hi> extended from <hi>Gaule</hi> or <hi>France,</hi> as far as the confines of <hi>Dacia,</hi> or the City of <hi>Sirmium;</hi> and when the <hi>Roman</hi> Troops were in <hi>Italy,</hi> the <hi>Germans</hi> poſſeſſed the beſt part of <hi>Gallia Ciſalpina,</hi> and the Countrey belonging to <hi>Venice. Sirmium</hi> and the Countrey adjacent, were in the hands of the <hi>Gepides:</hi> All this vaſt tract of Ground was depopulated in the Raign of the Emperor <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> partly by War, partly by Famine, partly by the Plague, and by other evils that are inſeparably concomitant with War. <hi>Illyrium, Thrace, Greece,</hi> the <hi>Cherſoneſs,</hi> and all
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:60251:51"/>the Provinces from the entrance into the <hi>Jonique</hi> Sea, to the very Walls of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> were cruelly ſpoiled under the Dominion of <hi>Juſtini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> by the annual incurſions of the <hi>Huns,</hi> the <hi>Sclavonians,</hi> and others. I do verily believe, that in every of theſe inroads, what of thoſe who were left behind, and of thoſe who were carried away priſoners, there periſhed above Two hundred thouſand <hi>Romans.</hi> And this is moſt certain, That in that Countrey which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was the moſt populous in the World, there were fewer people then in the uninhabited De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts of <hi>Scythia,</hi> and this was the effect of the Wars in <hi>Europe,</hi> and <hi>Africk. Aſia</hi> likewiſe was not without her ſufferings; for the <hi>Saracens</hi> (during thoſe Wars) having extended their Arms from <hi>Egypt,</hi> as far as the Borders of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> and made themſelves Maſters of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces which were under the Dominion of the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſo haraſſed them with ſuch conſtant cruelty, that there was not a perſon to be ſeen, and the numbers which were killed, or tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted, were infinite.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Perſian</hi> made three incurſions into the Lands of the Empire, under the conduct of <hi>Coſroes;</hi> and where ever they came, they ruined the Towns and Countreys; unpeopled them of their Inhabitants, and carrying the greateſt part away with them priſoners, they put the reſt to the Sword; but being afterwards got into <hi>Colchis,</hi> they made conſiderable devaſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, one after the other, as it had been in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of what the <hi>Laziens</hi> and <hi>Rormans</hi> had
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:60251:51"/>done there before; but neither the <hi>Perſians</hi> themsſelves, the <hi>Huns,</hi> the <hi>Sclavonians,</hi> nor other of the Barbarous Nations which invaded the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, could ever carry back their Armies whole and intire. They loſt many Men in their Conqueſts, in their Rencounters, Sieges, and pitched Battles, in which, <hi>Fortune</hi> was not always favorable to their ſide; ſo as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſenſible of <hi>Juſtinians</hi> fury, as well as his own Subjects. <hi>Coſroes</hi> alſo (as I have ſaid elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where) was a man of turbulent ſpirit, yet <hi>Juſtinian</hi> was always the aggreſſor, and ſerved as a Bonte-feu to the conflagrations which brake out; and in the conſequence, conſumed moſt of his Countrey. To be ſhort, in the affairs which he mannaged, he never conducted them accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the times and conjunctures, but did every thing improperly, during the whole War; and in times of Peace or Ceſſation, his thoughts were wholly taken up in contriving which way he might trouble his Neighbors. He invaded them bluntly, without declaring of War, but his preparations were always ſo backward (by reaſon of his extream covetouſneſs) he ſeldom ſucceeded; and inſtead of applying himſelf to the proſecution of his deſigns, he was for the moſt part taken up in Metaphiſical Notions about the Nature and exiſtence of God: Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, he kept his Armies conſtantly on foot to execute his cruel and tyrannical commands, never ſuffering them to come to any engagement with their Enemies, his avarice not permitting him to allow them what was neceſſary to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:60251:52"/>come them; ſo that in <hi>Juſtinians</hi> Reign, the Land was not only beſprinkled, but overflown with the Blood of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and all other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the World.</p>
            <p>Theſe were evils which ſucceeded upon the War at that time in the Territories of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Empire, but we ſhall find as many murders committed in the Cities, if we conſider what was done by the Factious, who had their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels and combats quite thorow the Empire; and indeed, how could it be otherwiſe, ſeeing no man was puniſhed as he deſerved; becauſe one faction adhered to the Emperor, and neither the one, nor the other, had patience to be at quiet: One of them finding themſelves backed and ſupported by the Emperor, puffed up with vanity, believed they might hazard all ſecurely, the other knowing the Emperor was their Enemy, grew deſperate upon an opinion that they could be no worſe, becauſe they had nothing left already to looſe. Hereupon they meet frequently in ſmall Parties, and fought ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral little Battles; ſometimes they met in Squadrons to fight, and ſometimes hand to hand in ſingle duels; ſometimes alſo they would lie in wait for one another, and murder one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other as they found opportunity. There was not a day paſſed, but a thouſand cruelties were exerciſed on both ſides for two and thirty years together, and continued without any inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion: Oftentimes the Governor of the Town would put ſome of them to death, but for the moſt part, his ſeverity was exerciſed againſt
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60251:52"/>the <hi>Praſinian</hi> faction, beſides which, ſo many <hi>Samaritans,</hi> and Hereticks were put to death, that the whole Empire ſeemed to be overflowed with Blood.</p>
            <p>Theſe things which I have now mentioned in ſhort, and inlarged upon in my other Books, were acted in the Reign of this Man, or rather of this Devil, and were purely the effect of his malice and rage: But for the things of which I am now ſpeaking, he did them by a power which I never underſtood. To be brief, in his time the Empire was afflicted with ſeveral judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which by many people were attributed to the evil genius which attended him; but others looked upon them more rationally, as the effect of the Divine diſpleaſure, and that God provoked, by the ſins of the people, had permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him and his inſtruments to oppreſs the whole Empire with all theſe miſchiefs. The River <hi>Scyrta</hi> overflowed <hi>Edeſſa,</hi> and drowned all the Inhabitants; the <hi>Nile</hi> overflowed all the Fields of <hi>Egypt,</hi> but not retiring as formerly, it brought great miſeries upon the Inhabitants, which I have related before; <hi>Lydne</hi> alſo being overflown, all <hi>Tarſis</hi> lay for ſeveral days toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther under Water, and it went not away, till it had brought irrepairable damage upon the Inhabitants: Several Cities were ruined by Earthquakes, as <hi>Antioch,</hi> the chief City of the Eaſt; <hi>Selucia,</hi> a Town not far from it; and <hi>Anazarbe,</hi> a great City in <hi>Cilicia.</hi> Beſides theſe, <hi>Ibere, Amaſia</hi> the cheif City in <hi>Pontus, Polybot,</hi> a Town in <hi>Phrygia;</hi> that Town which the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:60251:53"/>of <hi>Piſidea,</hi> called <hi>Philomide, Lycnide</hi> in <hi>Epirus,</hi> and <hi>Corinth,</hi> and populous Towns, were ruined, and for the moſt part ſubverted by Earthquakes, and the greateſt part of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants killed. After this the Plague (which I mentioned formerly) began to rage, and ſwept away half the people which were left. And theſe were the calamities which they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in the days of <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> when he govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Empire, at firſt under the authority of his Uncle <hi>Juſtin,</hi> and then after he came him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Throne.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now tell how he poſſeſſed himſelf of the wealth of the whole World; but firſt it will not be amiſs that I give a relation of a Dream, which a perſon of great quality had, when <hi>Juſtinian</hi> firſt entred upon the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Affairs.</p>
            <p>He affirmed, <hi>That he ſeemed to be on that ſide towards</hi> Chalcedon, <hi>and that he ſaw</hi> Juſtinian <hi>in the middle of the ſtreight, ſwallowing up all the Water of the Sea; and that after he had drunk up that, he reſted upon the ſhore to drink up the dirty and ſtinking Rivers, which received all the Jakes and Common-ſhores, both in</hi> Conſtantinople <hi>and</hi> Chalcedon, <hi>and diſ-imbogued them into the ſaid ſtreight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this he aſſured us was his Dream, and he was a credible perſon, of an Illuſtrious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, when <hi>Juſtin</hi> was advanced to the Throne, <hi>Juſtinian</hi> found his Coffers very well furniſhed; for his Predeceſſor <hi>Anaſtaſius,</hi>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:60251:53"/>was the Man of all the Emperors, the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, and the moſt proper for the Conduct, either of a State, or a private family. This <hi>Anaſtatius</hi> apprehending (as it hapned after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards) that his Succeſſor finding little Moneys in his Treaſury, would ſqueeze and moleſt his ſubjects to ſupply himſelf; therefore he left his Exchequer very well provided, both with Silver and Gold. But <hi>Juſtinian</hi> exhauſted it in a ſhort time, imploying part of it in impertinent Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which he erected unneceſſarily to keep out the Sea, and part in extravagant preſents to the Barbarians. Which Treaſure the moſt debauched and profligate Emperor would have been much troubled to diſſipate, though his profuſeneſs had continued a hundred years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: For the Treaſurers who had the charge of the Publick Stock, under the Emperor <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatius</hi> affirmed, That in the ſpace of Twenty ſeven years, which was the time of his Reign, he had ſaved by his frugality Three hundred and twenty thouſand Livres of Gold, which <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> conſumed in the days of his Uncle, as I have hinted elſwhere: Beſides which, it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible what vaſt quantities he extorted from his ſubjects, during his Reign, by moſt horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble oppreſſion, forcing the whole riches of the Empire into his own Cheſts by all imaginable ways, and all the cruelties that could be invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. So that it might be ſaid, he was a great Gulf that ſwallowed up all the wealth of his ſubjects, to diſgorge it among the Barbarians. After he had ſpent the Treaſures of the State,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60251:54"/>he began to caſt his eyes upon the riches of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons: He ruined ſeveral wealthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons both in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and other places, charging them with crimes, of which they were not guilty: Some he accuſed of Idolatry, others of Hereſie, others of Sodomy; ſome of having raviſhed the Nuns, ſome of Inceſt, ſome of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, ſome of inclination to the <hi>Praſinians;</hi> and ſome of High Treaſon: So that by his forged wills, and his pretended gifts, he made himſelf heir, as well to the living as dead. I have told before, how he made uſe of <hi>Victoriatus,</hi> to put himſelf into poſſeſſion of the Lands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Senate, which in his Reign hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be Seditious; and how he acted (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Sedition brake out) to hedge in, and unite to his Revenue, the Eſtates of particular Men: But it is not to be admired, if it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, That by his continual preſents he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched all the Barbarians in all the quarters of the World, Eaſt, Weſt, North, and South, as far as <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and other remoter places, of whom, we never had heard any thing, and ſaw their Ambaſſadors at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> before we knew of what Countrey to call them. Theſe people when they once found <hi>Juſtinian</hi> ſo liberal, they came to viſit him at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> from all parts of the World; and he (good Man) much pleaſed at what ought to have troubled him, overjoyed to ſee them in his Court, as a thing of mighty importance to him, drained the Treaſure of the Empire, and diſtributed among them what was remaining of his Buildings to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:60251:54"/>the Sea, and ſent them all home with very magnificent rewards. So that the wealth of the <hi>Romans</hi> ſeemed to be decreed wholly for the Barbarians, either by the preſents which were made them, their inroads into the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, the ranſom of their priſoners, or the ſums they paid for purchaſing Peace, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps a Truce, and that of no long continuance; and this was ſignified by the Dream which I mentioned before: But beſides theſe, he had ſeveral inventions to poſſeſs himſelf by degrees of all his ſubjects eſtates, of which, I ſhall give a particular as well as I am able.</p>
            <p>He inſtituted a new Magiſtrate among the people, and inveſted him with juriſdiction over thoſe who ſold ſlaves in their Shops, to whom the ſaid Officer gave Licence to ſell what they pleaſed, upon the payment of a yearly Rent to the Emperor. He obliged the Citizens to buy all they wanted in the Market, where they paid thrice as much as in other places; and though Commodities were racked never ſo high, and the buyer never ſo much cheated, it was not permitted to ſue him that had cheated him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the greateſt part of the gains went either to the Emperor or Magiſtrates. Thoſe who bought any thing, were in the ſame danger of being couzened by the deteſtable induſtry of the Magiſtrates Guards, and the abominable inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Merchants, whoſe impunity gave them encouragement to cheat ſecurely, not only in the prices of their Ware, but in chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goods: Afterwards <hi>Juſtinian</hi> ſet up
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60251:55"/>ſeveral Monopolies, that is, he gave priviledge to ſome particular perſons to ſell certain par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Commodities, with prohibition to the reſt; thereby ſelling the publick liberty to any Body, who would undertake that impious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and leaving them the adminiſtration of all things, for the payment of a certain duty agreed upon betwixt themſelves. The ſame practices he uſed with his other Magiſtrates, and ſuch as had Governments, and Offices, who plagued and pillaged thoſe who depended upon them with all manner of Liberty, becauſe no ſmall part of the profits accrued to the Emperor. Leaſt the number of former Magiſtrates ſhould have been too ſmall to execute his pernicious inventions, (for before his time, the Governor of the City took cognizance of all Crimes) he created two more, that he might ruine the poor ſubject with more eaſe and expedition. To one of them he gave the title of <hi>Pretor</hi> of the People, and his buſineſs was to correct Thieves; the other was called the <hi>Inquiſitor,</hi> and his office to puniſh Sodomy, Buggery, Idolatry, Hereſie, and Superſtition; and theſe two upſtart Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders followed his directions exactly accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Juſtinians</hi> intention. The <hi>Pretor,</hi> when any conſiderable Felony was committed, and the loſt Goods found about the Theif, ſeiſed them for the Emperor, pretending, he kept them for their right Maſter; by which way, <hi>Juſtinian</hi> got every day ſome rich thing or other, and without any expence. The <hi>Inquiſitor,</hi> when any Man was condemned, confiſcated what he
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60251:55"/>pleaſed of his eſtate, adjudged it to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and inriched himſelf by the ruine of other People: For at firſt, the Magiſtrates never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed themſelves, if a man were accuſed; though there were Witneſſes ready to prove the Fact; but without examining the Caſe, or any legal Conviction, they cauſed who they pleaſed to be put privately to death, and ſeiſed their eſtates for the uſe of the Emperor. At length the wicked <hi>Juſtinian</hi> committed the Judgment of all Criminal Affairs to theſe two Magiſtrates indifferently, and to the Governor of the Town, commanding each to do what they could, to deſtroy more People then his Companions. It is reported, That one of them coming to him, to know who ſhould determine in a Cauſe that had been heard before them all three, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror told him, <hi>He that had condemned moſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He debaſed the Office of the Treaſurer or Queſtor exceedingly, though all the Emperors his Predeceſſors, endeavored to raiſe it, and put in perſons who were to have cognizance of all things, but eſpecially of the Laws, chuſing them always as free from Covetouſneſs as they could, well knowing it impoſſible, but a State muſt be ſubject to many diſorders, under the adminiſtration of an ignorant Queſtor, or one that comes in to that place with a deſire to make himſelf rich: This Queſtorſhip <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> conferred upon <hi>Tribonian,</hi> whoſe manners I have elſwhere deſcribed: After his death, he took the beſt part of his eſtate (though he had a
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60251:56"/>Son living, and ſeveral Nephews) and gave his place to <hi>Junilus Apher,</hi> a man not at all verſed in the Laws, nor who had converſed among the Lawyers; he had indeed ſome knowledge in Latine, but had never ſtudied Greek; and his tongue was ſo little adapted to ſpeak it, that ſometimes when he ventured, he made all laugh that were preſent. He was ſo tranſcendently covetous, and ſo much beyond all reaſon ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to gain, he made no difficulty to ſell Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or Orders publickly, and was not aſhamed to receive bribes from any body, which deſired any thing of him.</p>
            <p>This infamous Queſtor executed that place ſeven years together, to the great prejudice and diſhonor of the Empire. Upon his death, the Emperor put in <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> who had indeed ſome notion of the Law, but was ſo young, he never had pleaded; beſides which, he was the greateſt and moſt impudent Theif in nature. <hi>Juſtinian</hi> loved him better then he had loved any before, if (to ſpeak truth) he ever loved any body: So that he made him ſuperintendant in thoſe affairs, and cheif miniſter of all his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice and Tyranny. With theſe advantages <hi>Conſtantine</hi> in a ſhort time got a vaſt eſtate, but his inſolence was inſupportable; for he affront<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any man, who came to him without ſome conſiderable preſent; and when any bribe was given to have their buſineſs diſpatched, they were obliged to intruſt it in the hands of his ſervants; for none was ſuffered to come near, or ſpeak with him, but when he was with the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:60251:56"/>Emperor, or returned from him, and then he would not vouchſafe them time to explain themſelves, for fear of being detained one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and gain nothing by it. In this manner <hi>Juſtinian</hi> made uſe of his Queſtor.</p>
            <p>The Captain of his Guards, beſides the uſual ſum, paid annually to the Emperor more then 3000 Livres in Gold; which Money was not to be raiſed, either according to Law, or anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Cuſtom, but was accounted to <hi>Juſtinian</hi> as dropped out of the air: For which reaſon (I conceive) it was called <hi>The Aerial Tribute,</hi> though it might more properly have been named <hi>The effect of the cunning and impiety of the Prince,</hi> who under the title of Tribute, gave occaſion to the Captains to ſqueeze the eſtates of thoſe under him without controul, upon pretence, that they were obliged to pay it into the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, though their own expences and manner of living was ſuitable to the Majeſty of a King. The Emperor let them alone in this manner, till they had cram'd their own Coffers, and got immenſe riches together, then taking advantage of ſome complaints againſt them he charged them with ſome crime, of which, they could not readily clear themſelves, and ſeiſed upon all they had got, as he ſerved <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Cappadocia.</hi> All who were ever in that Office, inriched them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves vaſtly, and got incredible eſtates, only two are to be excepted, <hi>Phocas</hi> whom I menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in my other Books (a perſon of great honeſtly, and ſo accompliſhed vertue, he could not be reproached with any thing that he had
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:60251:57"/>gained in that place;) and <hi>Baſſus,</hi> who ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, was the other; but they continued not long in their commands, being perſons who go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned too well, and could not frame themſelves to the Cuſtoms of that age: And becauſe I ſhould never conclude, ſhould I go about to be particular in every thing, I ſhall only ſay, That the Emperor did the ſame with every Officer he had, and all the other Magiſtrates in <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thorow all the reſt of the Towns in the Empire, <hi>Juſtinian</hi> put the cheifeſt Offices into the hands of the worſt men he could find, to the end, that he might have pretence to take from them what they ſhould get, and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate it to his own uſe; and indeed, an honeſt man, with but common ſence, would not have accepted them, and hazarded his own fortune to deſtroy other people. When <hi>Juſtinian</hi> had received the Money he agreed for, with thoſe he was to prefer, he ſuffered them to pillage the people, and the Provinces, that they might inrich themſelves in a ſhort time, and they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied with his deſign: For having borrowed at great intereſt, the Money which they paid for their places, when they were poſſeſſed of their Governments or other places, they treated the ſubjects with all manner of Tyranny, to diſcharge themſelves of the debts which they had contracted in the purchaſe, and to lay up for themſelves. And this they did with the greater liberty, becauſe they were in no appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of being queſtioned, much leſs condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:60251:57"/>for their exaction; but on the contrary were aſſured, That the exceſs of their violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, their murders, their thefts, and all their other cruelties, would rather be a means to gain them honor and reputation, ſeeing all thoſe Frauds and Extortions paſſed with that Prince; for marks of their induſtry and addreſs. But for all that, when <hi>Juſtinian</hi> obſerved they were ſufficiently rich he intangled them in ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended charge or other, and took all from them in a moment.</p>
            <p>There was a Law made, by which it was injoyned to all perſons who were to be advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to any Office or Government, to ſwear up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Evangeliſts, That they would not commit any violence or extortions upon the Subject; and, that there was nothing, either given or taken for their places; and that, whoever was guilty of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing that Law, ſhould be accurſed according to the cuſtom of the Antients:</hi> But the ſaid Law had not been in force a full year; but in deſpight of that Law, and the malediction that was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, he ſold thoſe Offices himſelf, not only privately, but with inimitable impudence, in the face of the whole World, and the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants which bought them; notwithſtanding their Oaths to the contrary, plundred and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaged the State more then ever before. Beſides theſe, he had another invention, which perhaps is not ſo eaſily to be believed; and that was not to ſell the great Offices in <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> as formerly, but to keep them in his own hands, and execute them by certain perſons, to whom
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60251:58"/>he allowed ſallaries for their pains, and received all the reſt of the profits to himſelf; and they (like Farmers) having received what they were to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from their Maſter; with inſupportable bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſqueezed, and extorted whatever they could to ſatisfie him, and indeed, brought him in moſt prodigious ſums.</p>
            <p>Theſe Mercenary Magiſtrates and Governors were to be ſeen paſſing from one Province to another, plaguing and tormenting the poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, under the fair pretence of their dignity. <hi>Juſtinian</hi> had always a great care to put the worſt men in his Empire, into the beſt places, and his deſign commonly ſucceeded. When he firſt advanced his wicked agents to the principal Dignities, and their power had diſcovered their ill inclinations, it was much admired, that the heart of man could be capable of ſuch malice: But after a conſiderable interval, thoſe who ſucceeded, having infinitely out-done them, the people were at as great a loſs to comprehend how it ſhould be poſſible for them to exceed their Predeceſſors, who had paſſed among them for ſuch abominable Creatures; and yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the preſent Officers, were very honeſt men. But the third ſucceſſion, and thoſe who came after them, exceeded the ſecond, as much as the ſecond had done the firſt, and did in a manner vindicate their Predeceſſors by the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendency of their crimes, and the extream in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry which they expreſſed in the conduct of their execrable actions, inſomuch, as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored them who were before them, to ſome
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60251:58"/>degree of reputation, though in their times it was thought impoſſible for any to have been more impious and cruel. In this manner the miſeries of the State daily increaſing, it was manifeſt by experience, That certain bounds cannot be preſcribed to the wickedneſs of Man, and that when it is confirmed by precedent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, and maintained and ſupported by great perſons, and power and authority, gives it means to exert, and ſhow its ſelf againſt Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors; no man can tell how far it will extend, but by the greatneſs of the miſeries which it pulls down upon the people. And theſe were the Magiſtrates in faſhion under the Reign of <hi>Juſtinian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It often fell out, that the <hi>Huns</hi> invaded the Lands of the Empire, and the Commanders in <hi>Thracia</hi> and <hi>Illyrium</hi> having reſolved to charge them in their Retreat, they received expreſs Orders from the Emperor to the contrary, as being allied with him againſt the <hi>Goths,</hi> and the reſt which were Enemies to the very name of the <hi>Romans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Barbarians</hi> making uſe of that occaſion, retreated, after they had committed a thouſand outrages upon the Subjects of the Empire, and the more, becauſe they found they ſhould paſs as Allies, though they carried with them a vaſt deal of plunder, and great quantity of priſoners. The <hi>Peaſants</hi> unable to endure, that their Wives and Children ſhould be carried into captivity, got together in conſiderable numbers, purſued, overtook, charged, defeated the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:60251:59"/>having taken all their Baggage, they recovered their priſoners, and all the ſpoil that they had loſt: But this victory was very unfortunate to the <hi>Peaſants,</hi> for the Emperor ſent Soldiers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, who beat, and wounded, and abuſed them, and eat up the whole Countrey, till they had ſurrendred the Horſes which they had taken from the <hi>Barbarians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Juſtinian</hi> and <hi>Theodora</hi> had quit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of <hi>John de Cappadocia,</hi> they looked out for another to put in his place; but they reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to chuſe none; but the worſt that they could find, that he might be a faithful miniſter of the cruelty and oppreſſion which they deſigned againſt their Subjects. For this reaſon they were very curious in examining the ſpirit and humors of all people about the Court; but finding none of them bad enough, they gave the place <hi>(pro tempore)</hi> to one <hi>Theodotus,</hi> who though no Saint, was not ſo wicked as they deſired; at length, after long and diligent ſearch, they found out a certain <hi>Syrian,</hi> called <hi>Peter Barzames;</hi> who had been a Banker by profeſſion; this Raſcal had got a great ſum of Money together by his cunning and juggling, cheating the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers, and other perſons, with the greateſt dexterity in the World, nimming their Money as they were telling it, ſo neatly, it was hard to perceive him; and when he was taken, he had the impudence to ſwear them down, that it ſtuck to his ſingers.</p>
            <p>This fellow, as I have diſcribed him, having liſted himſelf firſt in the <hi>Pretorian</hi> Bands, came
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:60251:59"/>by degrees to that perfection of wickedneſs, that he was always the firſt who offered his ſervice to <hi>Theodora,</hi> when ever any of her im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious reſolutions were to be put in execution. Upon this ſcore they put him in the place of <hi>Theodotus,</hi> who ſucceeded <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> as not being able to make choice of another man, ſo proper to aſſiſt in their barbarous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing he did, he cheated the Soldier of his pay, and he did it without the leaſt ſhame or fear in the World. His next exploit was, to expoſe to ſale the Offices and Commands, with the greateſt infamy that ever Man did, ſelling them much cheaper to any that was ready for an ill action; abandoning the goods and the lives of the people of the Provinces, to them who bought the Governments, and transferring to them, all the power which the Emperor had granted him of pilling and plundering with impunity, as ſoon as ever they had paid their Money; ſo that, what ever they received of the blood and lives of the Subject, was imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately conveyed into the Coffers of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror.</p>
            <p>There were likewiſe Diabolical Councils and Conventions about the deſtruction of Cities, held in the cheif Courts in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and (if I miſtake not) by publick allowance; for from that time, Officers were created with the title of <hi>Collectors,</hi> and diſtributed into the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, to raiſe Money under pretence of Juſtice; but in reality to reimburſe themſelves of what
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:60251:60"/>they had given for their places, which they levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon ſuch as were culpable with moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſs cruelty. At length <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf, among thoſe whom he imployed in his exactions, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tried many, found ſome who cheated him, and laid up for themſelves; and this was not his misfortune alone, but every mans who had borne the ſaid office before, and after him; the Maſters of the Offices, and ſuch as had been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced for their money or preſents; the Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers of the Emperors particular Demeſns; and in few words, all the Magiſtrates, not only in <hi>Coſtantinople,</hi> but the whole Empire: For in ſhort, from the time that <hi>Juſtinian</hi> (the greateſt Tyrant that ever was) had the adminiſtration of Affairs, there was not one place, but he ſold himſelf, or his Miniſters under hand; and thoſe who bought them, were obliged to ſerve him long, with much trouble and great loſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Juſtinian</hi> had made great proviſion of Corn in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and kept it till the greateſt part of it ſhrunk; nevertheleſs, though it was not fit to be uſed, he forced the Cities in the Eaſt to take it off on his hands, each of them a certain proportion, and ſold it to them at a much dearer rate, then if it had been good: So that the poor Citizens were conſtrained ſo throw it into the Sea, or the Common-ſhores, though it had coſt them ſo dear. And for that which was good, though there was great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of it in the Granaries in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the Emperor cauſed it to be ſold to ſuch Towns as wanted it, at double the price it bore in the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:60251:60"/>Provinces, from whence it was extorted and ſent thither. But the next year there being a ſcarcity of Corn, and the Ships having tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported leſs from the Provinces, then was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite for the ſubſiſtance of the people of that City, which was the greateſt in the World. <hi>Peter</hi> found himſelf in great perplexity, not knowing of what Wood to make his Arrow, nor what remedy to apply to their Diſtreſs. Having well conſidered of a way, at length he pitched upon this, to cauſe all the Corn to be tranſported out of <hi>Thrace, Phrygia,</hi> and <hi>Bithynia,</hi> to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and to compel the Inhabitants of thoſe Provinces to convey it themſelves to the Ports, where they were to ſhip it with a great deal of pains, and carry it by Sea to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople;</hi> having experimented in their paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, all the dangers that could be incurred, in a ſullen and outragious Sea.</p>
            <p>When they were arrived thorow all thoſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, and had perfected their voyage, they had but a third part of their due paid them for their pains, and the loſſes they received were ſo great and conſiderable, they had better have given away their Corn, and twice as much more: Yet all this Proviſion was too ſmall for the ſuſtenance of ſo populous a City, ſeveral perſons went to complain to the Emperor, and remonſtrate the true ſtate of affairs. The Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers who were in great arrears, and had no Money to furniſh themſelves with Victuals, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to murmur and repine, and to hold ſuch Meetings and Aſſemblies in the Town, as ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:60251:61"/>to preſage a Sedition which was ready to break out: Hereupon the Emperor conceiving a diſpleaſure againſt <hi>Peter</hi> for his male-admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, reſolved to take away his place, not only becauſe of the preſent inconveniencies, but becauſe he was aſſured he was very rich, and had heaped up vaſt ſums by his violences and oppreſſions: But <hi>Theodora</hi> oppoſed it, being a great friend to <hi>Barzames,</hi> by reaſon (as I ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine) of his wicked inclinations, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable cruelty wherewith he treated the Subjects; for as ſhe her ſelf was naturally cruel and inhumane, ſhe took particular care, to have ſuch people to execute her deſigns, as were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely conformable to her own pernicious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. Some there are notwithſtanding, who affirm, That <hi>Peter</hi> forced <hi>Theodora</hi> to be his friend, by vertue of certain charms, though ſhe was naturally his Enemy. The truth is, all his life long he had applied himſelf much to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments, and Necromancy, holding great correſpondence with the <hi>Manicheans,</hi> becauſe they ſtudied them much, and were open favorers of thoſe Arts, as <hi>Barzames</hi> was of them. Though <hi>Theodora</hi> underſtood all this, and more, ſhe loved him never the leſs; on the contrary ſhe ingaged in his intereſts with more kindneſs and zeal, having had her ſelf in her youth great converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with Sorcerers and Magicians, and placed much confidence in their Art, and many times made very much uſe of it. It was believed like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, That it was not alogether her flattery and complacency, which gave her ſuch influence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:60251:61"/>
               <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> but her Magick and intelligence with the Devil; for <hi>Juſtinian</hi> was not ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, nor of a nature ſo flexible to good, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himſelf againſt her ſtratagems, and wiles of this kind: On the contrary, his mind being entirely corrupted by cruelty, and avarice, he was every moment expoſed ſo much to ſubtilties and flattery, that in things of greateſt import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, he turned eaſily with the wind, there being no truſt or reliance upon him for the beſt friend, or neareſt relation that he had: For in ſhort, he was the moſt light, unconſtant, and uncertain man in all things, that ever was known. So that the Sorcerers who were very buſie about him with their charms, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly <hi>Theodora,</hi> found no great difficulty to arrive at their ends.</p>
            <p>The humors and inclinations of <hi>Peter,</hi> as I ſaid before, wrought ſo much upon <hi>Theodora,</hi> and gained him the favor of that Princeſs, ſo effectually, that the Emperor having with much ado removed him from his Prefectſhip, ſhe prevailed with him not long after to make him high Treaſurer of the Empire, having taken that place from <hi>John,</hi> who had been put into it but little before. This <hi>John</hi> was originally of <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> a man of that mildneſs, juſtice, and generoſity, he knew not how to exerciſe the little frugalities of a private family; and for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, he had never done it to any perſon alive. But the more grateful he was in the eyes of the people, the more odious he became to <hi>Juſtinian</hi> and <hi>Theodora,</hi> who no ſooner had notice of the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:60251:62"/>vertue and goodneſs of their Officers; but they turned their thoughts wholly upon ways of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving them, not being able to endure per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo oppoſite to their own natural temper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter,</hi> as I ſaid before, ſucceeding <hi>John,</hi> in the management of the Treaſury, was the cauſe of a thouſand miſeries to particular perſons, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing imbezled the Fund, which of a long time had been raiſing by an antient and laudable cuſtom, for the relief of ſeveral poor families; ſending part of it to the Emperor, and keeping the reſt for himſelf, whereby he acquired vaſt riches, whileſt they died with hunger, who had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe to maintain them, but thoſe annual Contributions. Beſides which, he coyned Money of Gold, much leſs then the former, and made it currant by Proclamation.</p>
            <p>Theſe in the Reign of <hi>Juſtinian</hi> were the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who managed all the Offices, and publick imployments. I ſhall now ſpeak of the methods which he uſed to ruine all, people of eſtates, though to exhibite their miſery, there needs (in ſtrictneſs) no more then what I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Governors of Provinces, and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors, who had private and peremptory in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, to ruine all people whoſe eſtates were in Land.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors were formerly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to remit to the people, the arrears of ſuch Money as was owing to the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> that ſuch of them as were unable to pay, might not be in fear all their life long; nor the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers have opportunity to raiſe Money, where
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:60251:62"/>many times it was not due. But <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> in Two and thirty years time, was not guilty of one of thoſe remiſſions; the poor people were forced from their Houſes and Countreys, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any hopes of return, whileſt ſuch as were honeſt, were liable to calumniations, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned perpetually to be complained of, as not having paid what was due to the Emperor for their Taxes upon their Lands; inſomuch, that the unfortunate Creatures were conſtrained to paſs away their Lands to the Emperor, or their Perſecutors; not ſo much out of apprehenſion of new Taxes, as for the impoſſibility which they found to ſupport long the unjuſt exactions, which for many years together they had been forced to pay.</p>
            <p>Moreover, though the greateſt part of <hi>Aſia</hi> had been ruined by the Arms of the <hi>Sarazens,</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> and all <hi>Europe</hi> haraſſed and infeſted by the incurſions of the <hi>Huns,</hi> and <hi>Sclavonians;</hi> the War of the <hi>Goths</hi> produced ſacking and burning of Towns, and devaſtations of Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; though the Inhabitants were carried away priſoners with all that they had; and thoſe few who eſcaped the hands of the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> were glad to forſake their Countrey, and baniſh themſelves: Yet none of theſe conſiderations could work upon <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> or prevail with him to remit one tribute or impoſt to any one Town in the whole Empire, unleſs it was ſuch as had been taken by the Enemy; and in that caſe, their exemption was but for a year, whereas, it he ſhould have excuſed them for ſeven years
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:60251:63"/>together, as his Predeceſſor <hi>Anaſtatius</hi> had done, it would have been no great matter, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the great miſery to which they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced. In ſhort, <hi>Cabades</hi> invaded the Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of the Emperor, and returned every way Victorious, but his Son <hi>Coſroes</hi> produc'd greater Conſternation, by Burning and Killing all where ever he paſſed with his Army. And yet thoſe of the Eaſt, who had been expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſo often to the Incurſions of the <hi>Huns,</hi> the <hi>Perſians,</hi> and <hi>Sarazins,</hi> and ruined by their Armies; and the <hi>Romans,</hi> who being ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in ſeveral parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> had many times felt the Hoſtility of the <hi>Barbarians;</hi> thoſe I ſay, who had ſuffered ſo much for their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the State, found more cruelty in <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> then among all the <hi>Barbarians;</hi> his Edicts and Impoſitions, compleating that Ruine, which the Enemy had but begun. I ſhall now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite what was the Contents of thoſe Edicts.</p>
            <p>Thoſe whoſe Eſtates were in Land, were by them obliged to furniſh a certain quantity of Proviſions for the Souldiers, at their own Charges, every Man paying his part; nor did they conſider what was given according to the Prizes of things, but according to a former Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſment made a long time before; and if at any time they were ſo unfortunate, not to have ſo much Cattle or Forrage upon their Lands, as would ſatisfie for their ſhare; they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to buy them at any rate, and convey them from the Provincial Magazines, which were very far off, to the place where the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:60251:63"/>Troops were in Garriſon, and then deliver them, in what quantity and at what rate the Officers pleaſed, and not according to what was reaſonable and juſt. This Impoſt was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>the Impoſt of Victuals,</hi> by which thoſe who had Lands, paid ten times greater Tribute then formerly, ſo that really it was taking from them, ſo much Blood out of their Veins, being obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to carry their Corn to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had ſuffered ſo much by quartering the Army. Theſe diſorders and oppreſſions the State owes to <hi>Barzames</hi> and <hi>John de Cappado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> whom their Succeſſors imitated exactly in the Continuation of their Crime: And ſo much for the Tax called <hi>the Impoſt of Victuals.</hi> The Impoſitions were like a Plague, which came ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly upon thoſe whoſe Eſtates were in Land, and took from them, not only the hopes of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving tolerably well, but the means of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing their Life, as miſerable as it was. For though the Lands were all thrown up, and deſerted by the Ruine or Flight of the Owners, or their Tenants, who were either Killed or Frighted out of their Country, or elſe hid them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to avoid Perſecution, <hi>Juſtinian</hi> without any reluctance exacted theſe Impoſitions, which were very frequent in his time; I conclude in few words, the Taxes call the <hi>Deſcriptions</hi> were impoſed to repair the Loſſes which the Cities had brought upon ſuch as were proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in the Country. But it would be an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Trouble, to undertake an Account of all the Evil Effects which enſued upon theſe Taxes,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:60251:64"/>or the idle and trivial pretences, upon which they were Impoſed; for the Miſeries of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple increaſed daily, and though the Inhabitants in the Country were moſt of them dead of the Plague, (which the Roman Empire was no leſs afflicted at that time, then the other parts of the World) and though the Contagion was ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, the Fields and the Farms lay uninha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited and untilled, <hi>Juſtinian</hi> never made the leaſt Abatement in his Duties, and Impoſts that he had Eſtabliſhed; on the contrary, he conſtrained with great ſeverity, thoſe who were alive, to pay the proportions of ſuch of their Neighbors, as were Dead of the Infection.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, their fineſt and richeſt Apartments they gave for Quarters to the Souldiers, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them with all poſſible liberality and civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, whilſt they were glad to make ſhift with any by place or ſtinking hole to lye in themſelves. In this manner things paſſed in the Reign of <hi>Juſtinian</hi> and <hi>Theodora,</hi> who though they were but Mortal as other Men are, acted more like Furies then Men; for during all their time, there was not one Moments intermiſſion of War, or other Calamities, but a general and deplorable deſolation, like a Flood, óverwhelmed the whole Empire at one time.</p>
            <p>But becauſe by accident I have mentioned the word Quarters, I will not forget to ſay, that there was at <hi>Conſt antinople</hi> 70000 <hi>Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and Foreigners, which the Houſe Keepers were obliged to Quarter, and to ſuffer many other Incommodities, beſides what they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:60251:64"/>by Lodging them. And now I ſhall declare how <hi>Juſtinian</hi> behaved himſelf with his Armies. He ſent Commiſſaries call'd <hi>Logothetes</hi> among them, with directions to pinch and abate as much of their Pay as was poſſible, giving thoſe Miſcreants a Twelfth part of what by their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veliſh Arts they could retrench of their pay. By the Eſtabliſhment in the <hi>Roman Army,</hi> all Soldiers had not equal pay: Thoſe who were new, had leſs then the reſt, thoſe who had any thing of Experience, had more, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if they had been Liſted any time; but the greateſt and moſt conſiderable Penſions, were to the <hi>Veterans,</hi> who had ſerved too long to be diſmiſſed without allowance, for not being looked upon as under Ingagement, but as pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſons belonging to the Eſtabliſhment, they were able to ſubſiſt with more Eaſe, and leave to their Families, out of their Wages and Pay, what would keep them, when they themſelves were dead: The Eſtabliſhment running thus, <hi>When any of the</hi> Veterans <hi>dyed, or were to be diſmiſſed, thoſe who were next under, were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly preferred according to the Antiquity of their Services, and receive Pay with the higheſt.</hi> But theſe deteſtable Commiſſaries would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the Names of ſuch as were ſlain to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pung'd, nor the Rolls to be called over, but in a very long time, by which it came to paſs, that the Troops were very thin, and thoſe few Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers which were left, remained in ſpight of their Merits, in ranks beneath what was their due, and by conſequence their pay was ſo much
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:60251:65"/>leſs then it ought to have been, whilſt in the mean time the Commiſſaries conveyed to <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> all the Money that they purloind from the Army, which ſuffered beſides that, a thouſand other injuſtices, in recompence of the dangers they had run, and the Wounds they had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in their almoſt daily Rencounters and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements. For example, ſome were deſpiſed for being <hi>Greeks,</hi> as if <hi>Greece</hi> never had produced any one perſon that was worthy of the Name of a Souldier: ſome were caſhierd, as being in ſervice without the Emperors Order; The Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificates of others were with great difficulty allow'd, and others disbanded for having been abſent ſome ſmall time from their Quarters. After all this, certain of the Pretorian Bands were choſen to take an exact: review, quite through the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> of all the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers which were capable of bearing Armes. Some who had been a long time in the Service, were caſhiered, as unfit for the War, and were to be ſeen begging about the Streets, as having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſuſtain them but the Charity of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which to good Men, was a ſad object, and well worthy of Compaſſion. Others to defend themſelves againſt thoſe Extremities, gave great ſums of Money to the Commiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries by way of Redemption: So that the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my being grown feeble and weak, by a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſuch practices, and deſtitute of neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, began to conceive ſuch a hatred againſt the ſervice, that the affairs of the Empire went ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ill on all ſides, and eſpecially in <hi>Italy:</hi> For
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:60251:65"/>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> who was ſent thither in the Quality of Commiſſarie, brought a thouſand Miſchiefs and Incommodities upon the Souldiers, reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them impudently by the ſmalneſs of their Numbers, (which was not their fault, but the Emperors) and cauſing large ſums of Money to be payd to the <hi>Italians,</hi> under pretence of vindicating the Emp. from the violences of <hi>Theodoric</hi> and his <hi>Goths.</hi> Nay, this buſineſs was carryed on yet farther, for the ravenous Commiſſaries having ruined the Common Souldiers, reduced the Officers to the greateſt poverty imaginable, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, as they had nothing left to ſubſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though their Services had been extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, and the Laurels where with they had been Crowned a long time, ought to have ſheltred them againſt ſo unreaſonable a Storm: And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I am ſpeaking of the Army, I ſhall add, That formerly the Roman Emperors, had a Cuſtom to maintain ſeveral ſmall Armies upon the Frontiers of the Empire, to ſecure them againſt Incurſions, and particularly in the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Provinces, to reſiſt the Inroads of the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians,</hi> and <hi>Sarazins,</hi> and theſe Troops were called the Troops of the Frontiers. In the firſt place <hi>Juſtinian</hi> took ſo little care of theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that he deferred the payment of them from four years to four years, and ſometimes to five; and when the Truce was concluded betwixt the <hi>Romans</hi> and the <hi>Perſians,</hi> ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it would drain his Coffers unneceſſarily, to maintain thoſe poor Troops in time of Peace, he disbanded them all in one day, and leaving
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:60251:66"/>the Frontiers unſurniſhed, he brought thoſe Troops to ſuch indigence, that they had nothing to ſubſiſt upon, but the benevolence of good people.</p>
            <p>The Emperors Guard conſiſted formerly of 3500 men, whoſe pay was greater than the reſt of the Army, and ſutable to the dignity of the place, as being intended for the choice Souldiers of <hi>Armenia,</hi> and a ſelect number to be cull'd out of the whole Army, no other being capable thereof: But from the time that <hi>Zeno</hi> was Emperor, all ſorts of people were entertained, and no body ſo lewd or inexperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced but might be admitted for his money. In the Reign of <hi>Juſtin, Juſtinian</hi> received ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral into the Guards upon the ſame termes, paying him conſiderably for it, and finding his number compleat, he entertained near 2000 more, and called them Supernumeraries, but he caſhired them as ſoon as he came himſelf to the Throne, without any reimburſment. But the beſt of his Exploits was, That pretending a deſigne to ſend Armies into <hi>Perſia</hi> and <hi>Affrick</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> he gave orders for 3500 of the oldeſt Souldiers to be picked out and prepared for that Expedition as perſons of more then ordinary experience, when to ſpeak truth they were utterly unfit for the Warr, and had not the leaſt thought or inclination thereunto; where-upon apprehending that journey exceedingly, they choſe rather to remit their arrears to the Emperor, than to undertake the Expedition, and this was not the firſt time that trick had
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:60251:66"/>been practiſed. Theſe troops of the Guards were often (or rather daily) expoſed to the deriſions and contempt of <hi>Peter</hi> who was <hi>Maſter of the Offices,</hi> who though he was naturally Gentle and loved not to do any man hurt, was nevertheleſs the laſt man who by his exactions and immoderate deſire of Wealth, put the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror upon thoſe things, and made him (as I ſaid before) conſpire the deſtruction of <hi>Amala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lazonte</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Theodorick</hi> King of the <hi>Goths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are belonging to the Emperors hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold, a ſort of Souldiers of much higher qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity than the reſt, who buying their places at a dearer rate have better pay than any of their Brethren. Theſe are called his Domeſtick Guards, or his Protectors; They never go to the Warrs, and are never received into the Emperors Palace but according to their Ranks. Part of theſe were conſtantly in Gariſon in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> others in <hi>Galatia,</hi> and others in other of the Provinces. By the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty and artifice, <hi>Juſtinian</hi> conſtrained them not to demand of him their Arrears: But to bring all that may be ſaid of this ſubject, to one point; according to antient Cuſtom the Emperor every five years had a General Muſter, ſo that every five years Commiſſaries were ſent from <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> to all the Provinces, Armys and Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and gave from the Emperor a piece of Gold of five <hi>Stateras</hi> to every Soldier: This had been practiſed a long time, but for this laſt 32 years ſince <hi>Juſtinian</hi> came to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:60251:67"/>he took ſo little care to continue it, it is almoſt forgot that ever there was ſuch a Cuſtom. But let us now paſs to his practices upon the poor Subject.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who are received into Office in the Emperors Houſhold, or admitted to any degree of Magiſtracy in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> take their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces loweſt and are afterwards advanced, as any of thoſe above them dye, or retire, and that courſe they continue till they come at the higheſt. For ſuch perſons, by antient Inſtitution there was eſtabliſhed a Fund of above 10000 <hi>Livers</hi> of Gold every year, to the end that having a comfortable and honorable ſubſiſtance for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves when they grow aged, they might be able in ſome meaſure to give reliefe to other people: which indeed was a very good thing, to oblige the Officers, and incourage them to accquit themſelves handſomly of their imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the adminiſtration of publick affairs. But this unmerciful Prince having retrenched all their penſions, and taken from them all means to ſubſiſt, ruined not only them, but many others beſides: for as we cannot but be the better for ſome peoples plenty, ſo we muſt needs ſuffer dammage when they are undone, in whoſe plenty we ſhared. In ſhort, he that will compute the retrenchments which he upon them and other people during the thirty two years of his Reign, will find the ſumms to be vaſt which he brought into his Exchequer. And this was the Courſe this great Tyrant obſerved to ruin and vex the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:60251:67"/>Soldiers, the Officers, the Officers of his houſhold, and the Magiſtrates: I ſhall now mention his deportment with the Merchants, Mariners, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks, and all that kept Shop in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and in a word his univerſal injuſtice to all people.</p>
            <p>There are two Streights not far from <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> one in the <hi>Heleſpont</hi> betwixt <hi>Seſtos</hi> and <hi>Abydos,</hi> the other at the mouth of the <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea not far from the famous Church of our Lady. In the Streight upon the <hi>Heleſpont</hi> there was never any Cuſtom-houſe, or Office, or Partiſans, or Publicans, but a Perſon was eſtabliſhed by the Emperor at <hi>Abydos</hi> who had the charge of Surveying all Goods and Armes that were tranſported, and to ſee that nothing of that nature ſhould be carried from <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> but by the Emperours permiſſion, nor any Veſſel ſuffered to paſs without a Ticket from the Magiſtrates appointed to that purpoſe: For no ſhip was allowed to go out, but by leave from the Commiſſary or Secretary to the Maſter of the Offices, and what <hi>Pretor</hi> exacted of the Maſters of the Ships under the title of Duties, was ſo inconſiderable, no body regarded it. To the other Streight a <hi>Pretor</hi> was ſent likewiſe, whoſe buſineſs was the ſame, that is to ſay, to take care that no body tranſportet to the barbarous Nations any Merchandize or Effects which were forbidden to be Exported out of the Empire; but with this Caution, That he ſhould not exact any Duties either from the Merchant or maſter of the Ship. But from the time <hi>Juſtinian</hi> had the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:60251:68"/>of Aſſairs, he eſtabliſhed both in one place and the other Officers of his cuſtomes and two <hi>Pretors</hi> to whom he gave a certain Sallary by the year upon condition they would apply their utmoſt endeavor to draw as much money from thoſe duties as was poſſible. Theſe Mercenary Officers who had no greater deſire, than to demonſtrate to the Emperor their Zeal and affection to his ſervice, ſerewed and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed from the Mariners by violence, illegal and unaccuſtomed Gabels upon all ſorts of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities. And at this rate were things ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged in thoſe Streights; But for the part of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> he gave the charge of that to one of his Court a great favorite called <hi>Addeus</hi> born in <hi>Syria,</hi> with Order to take Dutyes of all Veſſels whatever, whether outward or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bound. This <hi>Addeus</hi> to ſatisfy the inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable Avarice of his Maſter, when the Ships had been a certain time in the Harbor, obliged the Maſters to pay money for their exemption, or elſe he would lade their Ships with Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities to be tranſported into <hi>Africk</hi> or <hi>Italy;</hi> Inſomuch that many people unable to endure thoſe injuries and oppreſſions, nor the great Expenſes they were neceſſitated to be at in their Navigation, burned their Ships and ſled, chooſing rather to looſe all at once, than to be hourly expoſed to the Cares and miſeries of their condition. But others who were forced to continue their Trade for ſubſiſtance, would not let their Ships to the Merchants under three times the rate as formerly, and then the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:60251:68"/>being enforced to ſell accordingly, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imburſe himſelf of what he was out; by theſe unlucky projects, <hi>Juſtinian</hi> found out a way to ruin all the Subjects which he had: and this was the face of affairs in thoſe kind of things; But if think my ſelf bound in this place to give a deſcription of the Courſes which <hi>Juſtinian</hi> and <hi>Theodora</hi> made uſe of to raiſe profit out of the Moneys. The Officers of the Mint uſed to make a certain coin of Gold of the value of two hundred and ten <hi>Obolas,</hi> which they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Pholes. Juſtinian</hi> to make his advantage, cauſed them to be melted down, and new ones to be Coined, weighing but 180. ſo that he got a ſixth part out of every piece to the great prejudice of his Subjects. Moreover ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſettled impoſts upon all Merchandize (which could not be done without vaſt detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Buyers) there was nothing exempt but Cloaths, which were not liable to Cuſtoms, but <hi>Juſtinian</hi> and <hi>Theodora</hi> found out a way to draw money out of them as well as the reſt.</p>
            <p>Formerly the Workmen and Merchants of Silk Stuffs, had their Factorys in <hi>Beryte,</hi> and <hi>Tyre,</hi> two Townes in <hi>Phoenicia,</hi> where they ſettled their Trade, and from whence after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it was propogated quite through the World: but in the Reign of <hi>Juſtinian</hi> thoſe who lived in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and other Towns under the Roman Dominion, raiſed the prices of their Silks, pretending they were dearer in <hi>Perſia,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Dutyes which were required and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:60251:69"/>at the entrance into the Empire. It was known not long after that the Emperor was acceſſary, for he put forth an Edict prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any to ſell under Eight gold pieces a pound of Silk, with conſiſcation of Goods, and loſs of Eſtate to any that ſhould diſobey: This appearing altogether unreaſonable, to the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, who could not afford his Commodities which coſt him much dearer at the uſual rate, he choſe rather to give over and trade no more: Whereupon ſeveral of them gave away, (ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) all the remainder of their Wares, to ſuch of their friends as delighted in ſuch unneceſſary expences, and loved to appear glorious in the World, or to ſuch as had any other occaſion for them: but as privately as they carried it, a rumor was ſpread abroad, no body knew from Whence, which coming to the Ears of <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> ſhe fined the Merchants an hundred pound in Gold, and ſeized upon their Silks into the bargain. At preſent there is none but the grand Treaſurer who can licence, that Manufactory, in Which <hi>Perzames</hi> who had that Office was permitted to play a thouſand juggling tricks; In effect, he took the Workmen to himſelf, conſtrained them to work only for him, and would not ſuffer them to deal with any body elſe; beſides he ſold publickly in the Ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes which he had ſet up, an ounce of any coloured Silk for ſix pieces of Gold, but if it were in Grain, or the Colour Royal which they called <hi>Holovere;</hi> he ſold it for four and twenty; ſo that by theſe unconſcionable wayes he raiſed
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:60251:69"/>vaſt Summes of Money for the Emperor, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his own ſhips, which he kept very pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, and were ſuppoſed as conſiderable as the other, and this trade he drives to this day, with prohibition to every body elſe: For this cauſe the Merchants both in <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and other Citys reſented highly their uſage, and the loſs which they ſuſtained by the ruin of their Workmen: And for as much as in <hi>Tyre,</hi> and <hi>Beryte</hi> moſt of the popular ſubſiſted by that ſort of Manufactory, they were brought to a neceſſity of begging the charity of good people, or ſtarving with hunger and miſery. And thoſe few who eſcaped, quitted their own Countrey, and fled among the <hi>Parthians,</hi> for (as I ſaid before) none but the Treaſurer-Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the Empire was permitted to meddle in that commodity, and he returning a ſmall part of his gains to the Emperor, kept the greateſt to himſelf, raiſing a prodigious eſtate out of the ruins of the people, and his happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, out of the Calamities of the State, but enough of this, I ſhall now proceed, and give an account how he deſpoild <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and the other Towns of all their Ornaments. His firſt deſigne was againſt the Lawyers, whom he reſolved utterly to undo, leſſening their fees, and forbiding gratuities, though after the Cauſe was determined, which were commonly very conſiderable: In all Suits that were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending he cauſed deciſion to be made by oath, which rendred the Lawyers uſeleſs and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible, to their great prejudice and diſpleaſure:
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:60251:70"/>Moreover, from the time in which <hi>Juſtinian</hi> made bold with the Senators, and ſeized upon their Eſtates, and other great Citizens in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> which were as Wealthy as they, the Advocates and Lawyers were become very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable, as not having Work for any one Hearing; ſo that they whoſe number and eſteem was formerly very great, were now grown but few, and they not only deſpiſed by all the World, but deſtitute of all Neceſſaries, having nothing left them, but their old Inſtitution to diſtinguiſh them from other people. Nor was <hi>Juſtinians</hi> Malice peculiar to the Lawyers; the ſame kind of Severity he uſed upon the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, and all other Profeſſors of Learning, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenching their Fees, and taking away their Penſions, which had been given by the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Emperors, and payd conſtantly. As to the Revenue of every Town, which had been given by their Predeceſſors, for Exhibition of publick ſhows, or ſupplying publick Neceſſities, he made no Bones to ingroſs them to himſelf, by which means the Phyſitians, and other Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Profeſſors, loſt their ſubſiſtance. No pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Buildings were Erected, no Lights in the Night for the convenience of Paſſengers; No Feaſting; nor rejoycing among the Citizens; baiting of wild Beaſts, Comedies, and the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimes of the <hi>Cyreus,</hi> were layd aſide along time by <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> whoſe Wife had been bred and advanced from thoſe very Theaters which he deſtroyed; at length when he had put down theſe ſhews in all the other Cities, he ſuppreſſed
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:60251:70"/>them in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and all to ſave the Money which he was thereby neceſſitated annually to disburſe, without the leaſt regard or conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he would ſtarve an infinite number of poor people, whoſe ſubſiſtance depended wholly upon thoſe kind of things. So that in a manner the whole world was invalu'd in, and depreſſed with extream ſadneſs, as well pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Societies, as particular perſons, every Man paſſing, his time without any Diverſion, and groaning under his Misfortune, as heavy and immoveable. To be ſhort, their Diſcourſe and Communication at home, in the Streets, in the Churches and every where, was nothing but of the Miſeries, the Calamities of that age, and the ſad and deplorable condition of their preſent Affairs; and this was the manner in which he Treated the Cities: but now it is neceſſary I ſay ſomething of what followed, and ſo compleat this Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>It was a Cuſtom to create every year two Conſuls, one at <hi>Rome,</hi> the other at <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople;</hi> whoever was advanced to that Dignity, was obliged at his Entrance, to an Expence of two thouſand pound in Gold, a ſmall part of it was generally his own Money, but the greateſt part was from the liberality of the Prince; and this Money which the Conſuls commonly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in Preſents, that were to be given upon their admiſſion, or to the poor, or in Gifts to the Comedians, was of great Relief to thoſe Cities, and helped well towards the ſubſiſtance of the people. But ſince <hi>Juſtinian</hi> came to the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:60251:71"/>Empire, no certain time was kept for the Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſaid Conſuls, the ſame perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing continued ſeveral years, and no Aſſemblies allowed for the Creation of new, ſo that all people were fallen into extream Miſery, the Emperor not only retained in his own hand what was wont to be diſtributed among his Subjects, but robb'd and diſpoſſeſſed them of what they had of their own, in all places, and by all ways imaginable! I ſuppoſe I have ſaid enough of the Violences which he uſed in his adminiſtration of the publick Moneys, as alſo when he ſequeſtred the Eſtates of the whole Senate, and every particular Member therein, (with which he cramm'd his own Coffers, but could not ſatiate his Mind) as like wiſe in the deſcriptions of the Arts and. Calumnies which he uſed to get the Eſtates of all rich Men into his hands, his Tyranny, and the ſad effects of it, upon the Emperors Guards, and other Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks; his cruelty to the Common Souldiers of his Army, and of his particular Guards; To the Inhabitants of the Country; To the Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Land; To the Profeſſors of Sciences, Merchants, Maſters of Ships, Seamen, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryers, Meſſengers, Mechanicks, Comedians, Lawyers, Officers of Juſtice of all ſorts, and in a word to all thoſe who were Expos'd and ſenſible of the miſery above mentioned, and to thoſe who could not be happy when the other were miſerable. But now I muſt ſpeak of his Inhumanity to the Poor, and inferiour ſort of people, whom he reduc'd to the greateſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:60251:71"/>of Indigence imaginable, and after that I ſhall relate how he behaved himſelf towards the Prieſts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Juſtinian</hi> (as I ſaid before) had ingroſſed and impropriated, all the old Duties upon Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, and layd new upon every thing, not exempting ſuch as were neceſſary for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, by which he got a third part of what ever was ſold by his Subjects: But I will not go about to make a particular Enumeration of all the Injuries that I have ſeen; it would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to an incredible buſineſs; I ſhall only ſay, he layd a grievous Tax upon the Bread, which the Artiſans, the poor, and the ſick, bought every year, which by Computation amounted annually to 300 Livres of Gold, and thereby conſtrained thoſe poor Creatures to ſuſtain themſelves upon very ill bread, full of duſt, and ſcarce poſſible to be eaten; ſo far had the Exceſs of his Impiety tranſported him. In the mean time, thoſe who had the Charge of Proviſions, taking that Example, to make their own Markets, heaped up vaſt Riches as well as he, and by their wicked Inventions and Projects, ſtarv'd thoſe poor wretches, whoſe Miſery had more need to have had ſome way found out, to have made things cheaper, then that they ſhould be ſold to them by their weight in Gold: For no Man was permitted to bring any Corn from other parts, and all were obliged to take their Bread of him.</p>
            <p>The Pipes which conveyed the Water into the City being broke, the Emperor was ſenſible it
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:60251:72"/>was not eaſily to be ſupplyed any where elſe, for the Baths were moſt of them dry, and there was not a day, but ſome or other were ſtifled in the Crowds, which thronged continually to thoſe Fountains which were remaining; Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, he took no notice of it, would be at no expence to repair them, but let them lie, though they were of ſo univerſal importance, and in the mean time ſquandred away prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sums in fine, but uſeleſs and vain Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings upon the Banks of the Sea, in the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burbs of <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> as if the Palace which had been the Reſidence of ſo many great Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces his Predeceſſors, and had pleaſed them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, had not been good enough for the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of him and his Empreſs. So that thereby he clearly evinc'd, it was not purely Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetuouſneſs, or deſire to ſpare, which made him act in this manner; but he was reſtrained from the repairing thoſe Aquaducts, by an unparra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leld piece of Cruelty, that would not ſuffer him to have the leaſt Commiſeration, for the Evils which he brought upon his Miſerable Subjects: For never was there Man in the World that with more Impudence and <hi>Effronterie,</hi> ſought out unjuſt ways of raiſing of Money, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted it with more Cruelty, nor ſpent it more profuſely when he had done. Inſomuch, that the poor people in the Extremity they were in, being brought to nothing but Bread, (and that of their worſt ſort) and Water for the Subſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance (had been in ſome Meaſure happy, if they could have held there) but they had now loſt
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:60251:72"/>both of them, at leaſt they could not ſo eaſily come at them, for the Dearneſs of the one, and the Scarceneſs of the other, the Bread by reaſon of the Emperors Impoſitions, and the Water by his Cruelty or Negligence; Nor was this confined only to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> but alaſs, he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted the Poor in all places, and by all the Arts he could uſe, ſome of which I ſhall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ſhort.</p>
            <p>After that <hi>Theodorick</hi> King of the <hi>Goths</hi> had made himſelf Maſter of <hi>Italy,</hi> to leave ſome markes behind him of the Ancient Dignity of this Roman Commonwealth, he permitted the <hi>Pretorian Bands</hi> to continue in their former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and ordered them the ſame Allowance, which by long Cuſtom they had had every day. Theſe Souldiers were very numerous, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended under that Name, <hi>The Troops of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> the <hi>Domeſticks,</hi> and ſeveral others. Though this priviledge of Conſervation could not make them rich, yet by that means they remained ſtill as Souldiers upon the Rolls, and had a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable ſubſiſtance thereby, though what they received, was ſcarce ſufficient alone; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this, <hi>Theodorick</hi> condeſcended, that their Children, and Grandchildren ſhould inherite their Eſtates. To the poor, who were reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red about the Churches of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> he orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a yearly Diſtribution of 3000 Veſſels of Corn, to be paid out of the publick Stores. Theſe Gifts were continued both to the one and the other, till the arrival of <hi>Alexander For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficula</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> who quickly aboliſhed thoſe
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:60251:73"/>good Cuſtoms, and having ſent word thereof to <hi>Juſtinian</hi> the Emperor, he expreſſed his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, by the many Acts of Grace which he conferred upon the ſaid <hi>Alexander,</hi> who plaid another unlucky prank with the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of <hi>Helene,</hi> in his Voyage into <hi>Italy.</hi> The people of the Country about <hi>Thermopyles,</hi> had alwayes had the keeping of that Paſs, and at the time of <hi>Alexanders</hi> Expedition into thoſe parts, being apprehenſive leaſt the <hi>Barbarians</hi> ſhould make an Inroad into <hi>Peloponeſſus,</hi> the Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants kept Guard by Turns, in the place of the Mountains where they were moſt likely to paſs. <hi>Alexander</hi> being arrived, pretended he did not think it ſafe to truſt ſo conſiderable a Paſs, to the Defence of the Countrey people, and as if his Deſign had been nothing but the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Peloponeſſus,</hi> he left there 10000 Men, which were paid not out of the Coffers of the Emperor, but at the charge of the Neighbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Towns, in the Province of <hi>Hellade,</hi> by which means he annexed to the Emperors Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, what ever had been formerly given to the ſaid Towns, for the Building or repairing publick Structures, or the Expenſe of their ſhews, under pretence of imploying it for the payment of thoſe Souldiers, which were of ſo great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance for the preſervation of that Country, ſo that from that time, neither in the Province of <hi>Hellade,</hi> nor in <hi>Athens</hi> it ſelf, could any Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings be erected or repaired, any ſhows exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, or any other thing promoted for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of thoſe Towns, at the Charge of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:60251:73"/>all that <hi>Forticula</hi> did, being poſitively confirmed. We will now ſpeak of the Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which were ſuffered by the poor <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was in <hi>Alexandria</hi> one <hi>Epheſtus,</hi> an Advocate by profeſſion, who being advanced to the Supream Magiſtracy in that Town, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed all the Tumults and Factions that aroſe in it: But he himſelf was more pernicious to the Citizens, then the greateſt Sedition that could have been, for he reduced them to an extremity of Diſtreſs.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, having appointed Offices for all Commodities, which he had forbidden other Merchants to ſell, reſerving them wholly for himſelf, he ſold all things at his own rates, and put great prices upon them, which the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Office would make good. Hereupon the people wanted the neceſſaries of life, not being able to ſupply themſelves with ſuch things as were to be bought at an eaſie and indifferent rate, before <hi>Epheſtus</hi> was made Governor: For having ingroſſed all the Corn that came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> not permitting any man to buy ſo much as one buſhel, he put what price upon it he pleaſed; ſo that, in a ſhort time, having acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a vaſt wealth himſelf, he endeavored like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to content the inſatiable avarice of the Emperor: And the people of <hi>Alexandria</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured all this ill treatment without complaint, for fear of provoking their Governor to uſe them worſe: And the Emperor taking ſingular delight to ſee Money flowing into his <hi>Exchequer</hi>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:60251:74"/>from thoſe parts, took a particular kindneſs and affection to <hi>Epheſtus,</hi> whileſt he, to continue and advance it, did as I ſhall relate.</p>
            <p>The Emperor <hi>Diocleſian</hi> had ordained a year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtribution of Corn to the poor of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> which from that very time was conſtantly obſerved, the poor having received it, in thoſe times, and left it afterwards to their poſterity. But <hi>Epheſtus</hi> ſtopped this diſtribution, and cauſed two thouſand Barrels of Corn (which was the uſual quantity to be diſpoſed among the people) to be ſecured in the Emperors Granaries, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, That the <hi>Alexandrines</hi> had enjoyed it by Uſurpation, and contrary to all Juſtice, and the intereſt of the State. The Emperor ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved what he had done, confirmed it by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, and had a higher eſteem for <hi>Epheſtus</hi> then before, whileſt the poor people of that City, whoſe hopes of livelihood depended much upon ſo conſiderable a relief, was by this unparalleld cruelty reduced to the greateſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity; and they were the more ſenſible of it, becauſe it fell out at a time when there was great ſcarcity in <hi>Egypt.</hi> But <hi>Juſtinian</hi> committed ſo many cruelties of this nature, it would tire any man to number them: Wherefore I ſhall only ſelect out of that vaſt number, ſome few which I conceive will be ſufficient to convince poſterity of his fraud, hypocriſie, contempt of God, his Prieſts, and his Laws, how he perſecuted thoſe who were moſt religious and devout; and that he had neither ſhame nor modeſty, nor care of the State, his whole thoughts being bent upon
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:60251:74"/>contriving plauſible pretences; for his Crimes, when indeed his end was nothing but to ruine the whole World, and get their Eſtates.</p>
            <p>At firſt, he put in one <hi>Paul</hi> into the Biſhoprick of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> (at the time when <hi>Rhodon,</hi> a <hi>Phenician,</hi> was Governor) to whom he writ to execute what ever <hi>Paul</hi> recommended to him, and to be ſure to aſſiſt him; for by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry he hoped to oblige all the chief perſons in that City, and prevail with them to ſtand for the Council of <hi>Chalcedon.</hi> There was at that time a native of <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> called <hi>Arſenius,</hi> the wickedeſt man alive, who having made himſelf neceſſary to the Empreſs, by the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agement of her intrigues, had got a vaſt eſtate, and with it, great credit and authority. This miſcreant was of the ſame Religion with the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> but he had always pretended to be a Chriſtian, and his Father and Brother diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling the ſame Faith, being ſupported by his intereſt, and acted by his deviliſh perſwaſions, they brought a thouſand miſeries upon the Chriſtians of <hi>Scythopolis</hi> where they lived: Whereupon the Citizens revolted, and put them to death, after they had puniſhed them ſeverely, which was the occaſion afterwards of much miſcheif to <hi>Paleſtine;</hi> for as to <hi>Arſenius</hi> (though he was really the Author of thoſe troubles) the Emperor inflicted no other puniſhment upon him, but to forbid him the Court, and that he did only to ſatisfie the Chriſtians who were very importunate againſt him.</p>
            <pb n="144" facs="tcp:60251:75"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Arſenius</hi> being baniſhed the Court, conceiving he ſhould do a thing very acceptable to the Emperor, went a while after with <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria:</hi> For during the time of his abſence from the Court, he pretended to have inſtructed himſelf in all the Niceties and Criticiſms of the Chriſtian Faith; but inſtead of ſucceeding in his deſign, he fell into <hi>Theodoraes</hi> diſpleaſure, who ſeemed to act in that affair by motives al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together oppoſite to the Emperors.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Paul</hi> was arrived at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and ſetled there, he cauſed the Deacon <hi>Pſoes</hi> to be ſeiſed, and delivered into the hands of <hi>Rhodon</hi> (the Governor of the City) to be put to death, objecting, That he was the only man who op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed his deſigns, and obſtructed the execution of the Emperors orders. <hi>Rhodon</hi> had Letters continually from the Emperor, preſſing him to do whatever <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould deſire; wherefore he cauſed <hi>Pſoes</hi> to be whipped, and <hi>Pſoes</hi> being an infirm man, died under the correction. The news of his death being brought to the Court, by the inſtigation of <hi>Theodora</hi> (who with her prayers and perſwaſions, never let him reſt.) <hi>Juſtinian</hi> expreſſed great indignation againſt <hi>Paul, Rhodon,</hi> and <hi>Arſenius,</hi> as if he had forgot the orders which he had given them. He gave the Government of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> to a <hi>Roman</hi> of a <hi>Patrician</hi> family, called <hi>Liberius,</hi> and made choice of ſeveral Biſhops of approved integrity, to go and examine the buſineſs upon the place; in which number, one was <hi>Pelagius,</hi> Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, whom the Pope <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilius</hi>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:60251:75"/>had ſent as his Agent, to act as effectually, as if he had been there himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> being convicted of homicide, was turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of his Biſhoprick, <hi>Rhodon</hi> having fled to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and falling into the hands of <hi>Juſtinian</hi> was put to death, and his eſtate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcated, though in his own juſtification he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced ſix of the Emperors own Letters, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding his poſitive obedience in what ever <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould order; and to give him liberty to do what he pleaſed in Matters of Religion. <hi>Arſenius</hi> was put upon the Croſs by <hi>Liberius,</hi> according to directions which he received from <hi>Theodora,</hi> and his eſtate confiſcated; and all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on no other pretence, but his friendſhip for <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not trouble my ſelf ſo far as to diſpute, Whether this was done juſtly, or otherwiſe; but I ſhall tell upon what grounds I inſerted this paſſage.</p>
            <p>Not long after <hi>Paul</hi> came to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to endeavor by the offer of 300 Livers in Gold, to prevail with the Emperor to be reſtored to his Biſhoprick, having been (as he pretended) unjuſtly diſpoſſeſſed. <hi>Juſtinian</hi> took his Money, treated him with as much honor and reſpect as was poſſible, and promiſing to reſtore him with the firſt opportunity, though at the ſame time another was in poſſeſſion; and the ſaid <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> had cauſed two of the Biſhops beſt friends to be put to death, and confiſcated their eſtates. The Emperor pretended to deſire it much, and no body made the leaſt queſtion, but <hi>Paul</hi> would
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:60251:76"/>be reſtored; but Pope <hi>Vigilius,</hi> who was at the ſame time in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> would not conſent; not enduring that they ſhould act contrary to the ſentence which <hi>Pelagius</hi> had given in his name: So that in all his affairs, <hi>Juſtinians</hi> cheif deſigns was getting of Money, by what means was poſſible to gain it. I am now writing of a Hiſtory to the ſame purpoſe, which hath ſome Analogy with the former.</p>
            <p>There was in <hi>Paleſine</hi> a Man called <hi>Fauſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> of <hi>Jewiſh</hi> extraction, having been born and bred by his Parents in that Religion; but for ſecurity ſake, had taken upon him the name of a Chriſtian. This perſon being choſen a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nator, came at length to be. Governor of <hi>Pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine;</hi> but when the time of his Office was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired, he was accuſed at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> by the Prieſts, for pretending to be a Chriſtian, when he was really a Jew, and for having committed ſeveral cruelties againſt the Chriſtians, during his Government. Upon this information <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> was tranſported into the higheſt paſſion imaginable, holding himſelf affronted in his perſon, in that any one durſt be ſo audacious in his Reign, to contemn the name of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. The cauſe being brought before the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, upon the inſtance of the Emperor, <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinus</hi> was, condemned to be baniſhed the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. but having by degrees, and by a good round ſum of Money, mollified the Emperor, he cauſed execution of the Senates Dewer to be ſuſpended, and reſtored him to his imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with as much Authority as before; after
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:60251:76"/>which, his credit was ſo great with the Emperor; he had the management of the Imperial De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſns in <hi>Phenicia</hi> and <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> and diſpoſed of them with full liberty.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſay no more of this buſineſs, but theſe two examples are ſufficient to diſcover how <hi>Juſtinian</hi> delighted himſelf in perverting all the orders eſtabliſhed among the Chriſtians; and for the Laws which he aboliſhed for Money, I ſhall ſpeak of them in very few words.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Emeſus</hi> there was a Perſon called <hi>Priſous,</hi> exceedingly dexterous at counterfeiting of Seals, in which art he was the moſt expert Man in the World. Many years before <hi>Mamianus</hi> (who had been a Senator, and of no leſs eminence for his great birth, then his prodigious riches) had given all his eſtate by Will to the Church of <hi>Emeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In proceſs of time, under the Reign of <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> the Emperor, <hi>Priſous</hi> made a Catalogue of the beſt Families of that Town, which were in greateſt reputation for wealth, and from whom he might hope for the moſt conſiderable booty. He obſerved accurately the pedigrees of thoſe who were the cheif, and having found the names of ſuch of their Anceſtors as were contemporary with <hi>Mamianus,</hi> he counterfeited ſeveral Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts and Recogniſances under their names, by which they confeſſed themſelves indebted to <hi>Mamianus</hi> in very great ſums; by which kind of forgeries he made a ſhift among ſeveral of them to pretend to 10000 Livers of Gold. In ſhort, having imitated very neatly the hand of
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:60251:77"/>the Notary, who drew up the Writings, ſigned them in <hi>Mamians</hi> days, and was a Man of known honeſty, and vertue; he put his Papers into the hands of thoſe who managed the affairs of the Church of <hi>Emeſus,</hi> upon condition he ſhould go ſnips, and have ſuch a ſhare of the Money as ſhould be agreed off betwixt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: But there being a Law in force, expreſly contrary to their deſign, becauſe it reduced all Proceſſes to the Preſcription of thirty years, unleſs in Caſes of Mortgage; and ſeveral others where the Preſcriptions were to extend but to forty years; they concluded to go to <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> and give a round ſum to the Emperor, to favor them in their pernicious deſign of ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Fellow Citizens.</p>
            <p>Being arrived at his Court, they did as they had reſolved, and the Emperor having got his Money, put forth a Decree, by which he requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, That affairs which related any way to the Church, ſhould not be reſtrained to the ordinary Preſcription, but that any thing might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, if claimed within a hundred years; and this he commanded ſhould be obſerved quite thorow the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, but more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the City of <hi>Emeſus;</hi> and not long after he ſent <hi>Longinus</hi> thither, a high ſpirited, and exceeding ſtrong man, whom he made Governor of that City, on purpoſe to ſee that new Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance put in execution. At firſt, the Officers of the Church of <hi>Emeſus,</hi> having proſecuted ſome of their Fellow Citizens upon their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended obligations, for a ſum of Two hundred
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:60251:77"/>Livers in Gold, they were condemned to pay it, the poor men not being able to rake out of the darkneſs of Antiquity any objection that might defend them. This put the whole Town of <hi>Emeſus</hi> in ſtrange conſternation, eſpecially the principal Citizens, who were more highly inraged againſt their Accuſors, becauſe the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger was directed more particularly againſt them. But when all the Inhabitants of that Town were ready to be involved in this common ruine, God Almighty prevented it in his mercy. One day <hi>Longinus</hi> having ordered <hi>Priſous</hi> (the Author of this deteſtable invention) to bring him all his Claims, that he might ſee how they were grounded; obſerving him unwilling, and to make more difficulty then was neceſſary, he grew angry, and in his paſſion, gave him a Box on the Ear, as hard as he could ſtrike. The wretch ſwounded with the ſtroke (which came unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectedly, and from the ſtrongeſt Man in the World) fell backward upon the ground; and apprehending <hi>Longinus</hi> had had ſome light of his forgery, he confeſt the whole buſineſs, whereby all being diſcovered, the Suits which were commenced were ſtopped, and all their Proceſſes ceaſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Juſtinian</hi> was not contented to ſubvert the Laws of the Empire every day, but he muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfere with the <hi>Jews,</hi> and aboliſh ſuch of theirs, as were the very Fundamentals of their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In a word, if <hi>Eaſter</hi> fell out ſooner in their Kalander, then the Chriſtians (which might very well happen, becauſe their ways of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:60251:78"/>were ſeveral) he would not ſuffer them to make their ſolemnities on their own uſual day, nor to exerciſe ſuch offices of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, as their Religion required. The Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate likewiſe fined ſeveral of them, upon an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, That they had eaten the Paſchal Lamb, as a thing contrary to the Laws of that State.</p>
            <p>I know a thouſand Crimes of this nature, which I could charge upon <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> but I paſs them over in ſilence, becauſe it is time to finiſh my Hiſtory which is already too long, and I think has ſufficiently diſcovered the temper of that Tyrant: Nevertheleſs, I ſhall add two words to ſhow his Falſhood and Hypocriſie.</p>
            <p>He turned <hi>Liberius</hi> (of whom I have ſpoke before) out of his Government, and put an <hi>Egyptian</hi> called <hi>Laxarion</hi> into his place; which coming to the ears of <hi>Pelagius</hi> the Pope, who was a great friend to <hi>Liberius,</hi> he went to <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> to know, if what was reported of <hi>Laxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion,</hi> was true. <hi>Juſtinian</hi> denied there was any ſuch thing, and to convince his Holineſs, that he had no intention to remove <hi>Liberius,</hi> he put into his Holineſs his hand a new Commiſſion, confirming the ſaid <hi>Liberius</hi> in his Government, and requiring him not to quit it, without new orders from him. There was at that time in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> an Uncle of <hi>Johns</hi> called <hi>Eude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> a rich man, who had been Conſul, and had then the charge of the Emperors Demeſns. This <hi>Eudemon</hi> having heard what had paſſed betwixt the Emperor, and the Pope, went to
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:60251:78"/>the Emperor to inform himſelf, whether his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew was turned out of his Government, or not. The Emperor taking no notice to <hi>Eudemon</hi> of the Commiſſion which he had delivered for <hi>Liberius</hi> to the Pope, gave <hi>Eudemon</hi> another, to put his Nephew <hi>Laxarion</hi> into the ſaid Government, and declaring, That he did ſtill retain the ſame good will towards him, that he had always ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> believing himſelf ſafe under the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Commiſſion, ſent to require <hi>Liberius</hi> to remove out of the Governors Palace, as hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to do there no farther: <hi>Liberius</hi> refuſed it, and to juſtifie himſelf, produced the Emperors Patents. <hi>John</hi> ſeeing he would not obey, cauſed his friends to take Arms, and try to remove him by force; <hi>Liberius</hi> defended himſelf with his Guards, and the conflict was ſo bloody, that ſeveral perſons were ſlain, and <hi>Laxarion.</hi> among the reſt. <hi>Eudemon</hi> followed the buſineſs very cloſe afterwards, and upon his ſolicitation, <hi>Liberius</hi> was ſent for to <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> where being heard before the Senate, he was acquitted of the murder, as done in his own defence. Nevertheleſs, <hi>Juſtinian</hi> would not let him eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape ſo, but forced him to give him a good ſum of Money, before he could be quiet. By this we may ſee an inſtance of the friendſhip which <hi>Juſtinian</hi> bare to the truth, and of the great care he took, never to offend againſt if. I ſhall now make (and I ſuppoſe not impertinently) a little digreſſion in this place, and inſert it by way of addition to my Book.</p>
            <pb n="152" facs="tcp:60251:79"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Eudemon,</hi> whom I mentioned but now, died not long after, without either Children or Will, but his heirs general were numerous. About the ſame time, the cheif Eunuch of the Court called <hi>Euphratas,</hi> died likewiſe without diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of any thing of the great riches which he poſſeſſed, becauſe he left a Siſters Son, who was in Law to be his heir: But the Emperor got both their eſtates into his hands, giving only a third part to their heirs; and that was the way he expreſſed his tenderneſs for the Laws, and his moderation to the Children of thoſe Perſons, who had been his great Favorites whileſt they were living. He ſeiſed likewiſe all the eſtate of <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> who had been dead a long time without any right, or ſo much as reaſonable pretence. And there was another thing hapned about this time, which I cannot omit.</p>
            <p>There was at <hi>Aſcalone,</hi> a perſon called <hi>Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> without contradiction the cheif Man in the Senate of that Town, whoſe only Daughter, <hi>Mammilianus</hi> (who was of the ſame quality in <hi>Ceſaria</hi>) had married, and by her had the inheritance of his eſtate. There was an antient Law, by which it was provided, That when ever a Senator died without Iſſue-male, the fourth part of his eſtate ſhould go to the uſe of the Senate, and the reſt to the heirs at Law. In this caſe alſo, <hi>Juſtinian</hi> gave great teſtimony of his good nature; for he decreed, That for the future, when any Senator died without Iſſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, the Cuſtom ſhould be inverted, the fourth part only deſcending to the heirs, and the three
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:60251:79"/>other parts to go to the uſe of the Senate, or to the Coffers of the Emperor, though in no time it had been known, That the eſtate of any Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nator had been confiſcated, or ſequeſtred to the uſe of the Publick, or for the Purſe of the Emperor.</p>
            <p>After the publication of this Ordinance, <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolius</hi> died, and his Daughter was preparing to divide her Inheritance with the Emperor and the Senate; when ſhe received a Letter from each of them, importing a remiſſion of what belonged to them: Not long after, <hi>Mammil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ian</hi> died alſo, leaving only one Daughter, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing married to a perſon of quality, died with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iſſue, during the life of her Mother. On a ſudden, <hi>Juſtinian</hi> ſeiſed upon all, pretending (forſooth) That it was not fit the Daughter of <hi>Anatolius,</hi> at that age, ſhould be ſuffered to be rich, by two ways at once, that is, by her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony from her Father, and her eſtate by her Husband: But to keep her from want, he grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her an allowance of one <hi>Statera</hi> of Gold a day, to continue whileſt ſhe lived; and in the Grant which he gave her, there were theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing words. <hi>We have ordered her a Statera of Gold, only in Charity; for we have been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed by our Actions to give conſtant marks of our vertuous inclinations.</hi> But enough of this ſubject, I fear the length of my Book would diſſatisfie, ſhould I write any farther, though indeed I think it a hard matter for the memory of one man to retain all; yet I cannot but add, That he conſidered nothing at all when
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:60251:80"/>Money was in the caſe; and this appeared by his comportment with the <hi>Venetes;</hi> which facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had always ſtood for him, and he had ever profeſſed himſelf as cordially for it.</p>
            <p>He made choice of <hi>Malthanes,</hi> Son in Law to <hi>Leo,</hi> the Referendary, and a <hi>Cilician,</hi> as he was, to ſend into that Countrey to appeaſe the Seditions which had ſome times ſince been raiſed in thoſe parts. This new Governor find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the power in his own hands, uſed ſeveral of the <hi>Cilicians</hi> very ill, cauſed them to ſuffer a thouſand indignities, and of the Money which he extorted unjuſtly from that Province; part he tranſported into the Emperors Coffers, and the reſt he kept himſelf to augment the great riches which he had gotten before. Some there were who ſwallowed their grievances without any complaint; but thoſe of the faction of the <hi>Venetes</hi> who were in <hi>Tarſis,</hi> ſeeing themſelves ſupported by their reputation and intereſt with the Empreſs, complained publickly of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of <hi>Malthanes,</hi> who was not then there to defend himſelf. The news of it coming to his ears, he got his Troops together, and march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Tarſis</hi> in the night, by break of day he cauſed them to enter into the houſes, with or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to ſpare no body. The <hi>Venetes</hi> ſuppoſing the Town was ſurpriſed by the Enemy, took Armes and ſtood upon their guard: Several Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Engagements hapned in the Town; in one of which, <hi>Damianus</hi> the Senator, who was cheif of the party of the <hi>Venetes</hi> in <hi>Tarſis,</hi> was ſlain with an Arrow.</p>
            <pb n="155" facs="tcp:60251:80"/>
            <p>This news arriving at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netes</hi> began to aſſemble in the ſtreets, and to murmur highly at their uſage; they complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Emperor, of the violences which had been exerciſed againſt their Brethren, and threatned to revenge themſelves upon <hi>Leo</hi> and <hi>Malthanes.</hi> But <hi>Leo</hi> by a magnificent preſent, prevented the execution of the Order which <hi>Juſtinian</hi> had paſſed, and abated ſo much of the ardor which he had always ſhown for that faction, that the Proceſs was ſtopped; and when <hi>Malthanes</hi> came to Court a while after, the Emperor received him very honorably, and treated him as kindly as he could wiſh: But the <hi>Venetes</hi> inraged, having ſet upon him as he was paſſing from the Emperors apartment, wounded him ſeverely, and had certainly kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, had not ſome of their own party, whom <hi>Leo</hi> had corrupted with his Money, preſerved him.</p>
            <p>Is there any man living, that thinks not that State in an unhappy condition, where the Prince ſuffering himſelf to be bribed and corrupted with Money, leaves offences unpuniſhed; and where the Malecontents are ſo audacious as to attempt a Magiſtrate in the Palace, and before the eyes of their Emperor? In ſhort, <hi>Malthanes</hi> and his aſſaſins remained equally unpuniſhed, which may eaſily inſinuate the temper of <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian:</hi> Yet for further eviction, and to ſhow how much he applied himſelf to the good of the Commonwealth, I ſhall only add his behavior towards the Poſts and the Spies.</p>
            <pb n="156" facs="tcp:60251:81"/>
            <p>The Emperors which had Reigned before him, had Eſtabliſhed ways of Intelligence, for the ſpeedier underſtanding the Motions and Attempts of their Enemies upon the Frontiers, and particularly they had ſetled a Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency in every City and Village in thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, that thereby they might be adverti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of any Sedition or other accident that might happen; as alſo of the Deportment of their Governors and Lieutenant Generals; and for the ſafer and more ſpeedy Conveyance of ſuch ſums of Money, as ſhould be raiſed in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces more immediately under the Jurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Empire, or in ſuch as were only tributary: To this purpoſe in every days jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, they had ſetled a Man who was to Poſt Eight Stages a day, but in ſome places their Stages were not ſo many, though five were the feweſt. In theſe ſeveral Stages, there were about forty layd Horſes, and a juſt proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Grooms: Thoſe therefore who had any important Affairs, made uſe of this way, and by frequent change of Horſes, which were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in Breath, they would make as much way eaſily in one day, as in ten any other way. This was not only convenient to ſuch as had bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of importance, but was likewiſe of great advantage to thoſe whoſe Lands lay in the middle of the Provinces, and yielded them a conſiderable Revenue, by giving them oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of putting off their Grain and other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, to ſuch as had the Charge of thoſe Horſes, and were to provide for the Paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers;
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:60251:81"/>Theſe Poſt Maſters likewiſe conveying in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Emperors Treſurie, the Moneys which were returned, had the liberty to difalke what Wages was due to them for their pains; ſo that all was very well ordered for the good of the State, and this was the Method which had been Eſtabliſhed of old. But <hi>Juſtinian</hi> having rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Poſt betwixt <hi>Calcedonia</hi> and <hi>Dacibile,</hi> all who had buſineſs that way, were conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to paſs betwixt <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and <hi>Heleno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis,</hi> in the little Boats, which were uſed before only to waſt them over the <hi>Streight,</hi> whereby they were perpetually obnoxious to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts which are very frequent in that paſſage, for when a Man is preſſed by the Neceſſity of his Affairs, he ſtands not to conſider whether it be fair or fowl, or what danger there is of the Weather. The Road to <hi>Perſia, Juſtinian</hi> left as he found it eſtabliſhed, but for all the reſt, either into the Eaſt or <hi>Egypt,</hi> in every days journey, he would not ſuffer thoſe ſtables of Horſes to be continued for the convenience of Travellers, but the paſſage was made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Aſſes, and thoſe very few: By which means it came to paſs, that Advertiſements were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſlow from the Provinces, and moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly too late for any Remedy to be applyed: Thoſe whoſe Eſtates lay upon the Roads, were exceedingly impoveriſhed, having no vent nor utterance for their Commodities; and ſo much for the Meſſengers or Poſts: I ſhall ſpeak now of the Spyes. There were great numbers of
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:60251:82"/>them entertained by the State, who under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Trading, or ſome other Invention, went every day among the Enemies, and ſome of them into the very Court of the King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> where having diſcovered the Intrigues of the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> they returned with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, to make Report to the Emperors, who thereby had time not only to foreſee, but to prevent moſt of their Deſigns, as having Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement a long time before. Tis now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years ſince, the <hi>Perſians</hi> have taken this Cuſtome from us, but <hi>Coſroes</hi> made better uſe of it, then any of his Predeceſſors, having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven more then ordinary Wages to his Spyes, and great and magnificent Rewards, when any thing did happily ſucceed, never employing any that was born a Subject of <hi>Rome.</hi> But <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> having cut off this Entercourſe, was the occaſion of very great Loſſes, and particularly of the Country of the <hi>Laziens,</hi> which was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered by the Enemy, becauſe <hi>Juſtinian</hi> could never get Intelligence of the place, againſt which the King of the <hi>Perſians</hi> deſigned. It had been likewiſe a Cuſtome of old, to keep a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Cammels, at the Charges of the State, which were to follow the Army upon its March in time of War, to carry the Baggage, that the Country people might not be diſturbed in their Buſineſs, and that nothing might be wanting to the Souldiers: But <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> Retrenched them likewiſe for the greateſt part, ſo that at preſent when one has any accaſion more then ordinary,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:60251:82"/>and deſires to make more then ordinary Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, he wants every thing that is neceſſary, as having no convenience to carry his Baggage: And this was the great care he took of things which were of the greateſt conſequence for the Conſervation of the State; and to which, he ought to have applied himſelf with particular diligence. Though this that has been ſaid, has been ſufficient, I cannot contain from adding another ſtory of him, which in my judgment is very ridiculous.</p>
            <p>There was in <hi>Ceſarea</hi> an Advocate called <hi>Evangelus,</hi> who having had very good fortune, was grown ſo rich, that he bought for Three hundred Livers of Gold, a great Town called <hi>Porphyrian,</hi> which is ſcituate upon the Sea-ſhore. The news of his purchaſe being brought to <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> he took it from him, returning but a very inconſiderable part of what it coſt, and alledging only, That it was not a decent thing to ſee ſo great, and ſo beautiful a Town in the hands of ſuch a Lawyer as <hi>Evangelus.</hi> But enough of this ſubject, what remains to be ſpoken of, is only of ſome things which were innovated by <hi>Juſtinian</hi> and <hi>Theodora.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Senators went to ſalute the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, they did it as follows. Every one who was of a <hi>Patrician</hi> family, kiſſed the Emperors right Cheek, when he came in, and when he went out the Emperor kiſſed his Head: All the reſt that were of inferior rank, retired after they had clapped their right knee upon the ground;
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:60251:83"/>and for the Empreſs, the Men never made any compliments to her. But thoſe who came to ſalute <hi>Juſtinian</hi> and <hi>Theodora,</hi> whether Senators, or of inferior degree, proſtrated themſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their face, ſtretched our their hands and their feet; kiſſed both his feet, one after another, and then retired. <hi>Theodora</hi> ſuffered the ſame houors to be done to her, receiving at her own Palace the Ambaſſadors from <hi>Perſia,</hi> and other Foreign Nations, and (which was never practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced before, at leaſt ſince Hiſtory has preſented us with the occurences of paſſed ages) giving them rich and magnificent preſents, to let them ſee that ſhe was abſolute Miſtreſs, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the whole Empire. Formerly, when the Emperor was ſpoken of, he was called <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and his Wife <hi>Auguſta,</hi> and other Princes had their Titles according to their qualities: But when any Addreſs was made to <hi>Theodora</hi> or <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> if they were called only Emperor and Empreſs, without the addition of Soveraign Lord, or Soveraign Princeſs; the perſon was not only looked upon as ill-bred, and a Clown, but he was ſure to be ill received, and turned out as one that was guilty of ſome hainous offence. Formerly few perſons went to Court, and thoſe few who did go, went very rarely; but ſince the Government of <hi>Juſtinian</hi> and <hi>Theodora,</hi> all the Magiſtrates, and all other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, were continuity in the Palace, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it was, becauſe heretofore the Magiſtrates might freely adminiſter Juſtice, and execute
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:60251:83"/>their Sentences and Decrees among themſelves, according to Cuſtom, and the parties never troubled the Emperor with their importunities, being perſwaded within themſelves, that no injuſtice would be done them. But <hi>Juſtinian</hi> having ingroſſed all buſineſs, that thereby he might more eaſily ruine his ſubjects, he brought them to a condition that was little better then ſlavery. The Courts of Juſtice were always empty, and ſcarce a Man to be ſeen; whereas in the Palace, infinite multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes were continually to be ſeen, preſſing and crouding to out-do one another in the ſervility of their obedience. Thoſe who were in moſt favor with them, and ſeemed to have the greateſt intereſt in their affection, waited whole days, and a great part of the night, but they got nothing but their labor for their pains, having no other compenſation for all their aſſiduity and attendance, then a vain image of felicity and good fortune. Others who were not intangled in thoſe cares and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities, had yet their troubles to think what was become of all the Treaſure and Riches of the Empire. Some ſaid the <hi>Barbarians</hi> had divided it among them, others, that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror had hid it in ſeveral places, which very few knew. For my part, I will not ſpeak my ſentiment, only this I will ſay, That when <hi>Juſtinian</hi> dies, (for he is but a Man, and
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:60251:84"/>mortal as we) or when he has ruined and confounded every thing if he be a Devil (as many imagine) thoſe who are then living, will be able to judge of the truth.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:60251:84"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
